Linux on Windows wow and windows on
Linux this is WSL or the windows
subsystem for Linux in 2 minutes I'm
going to have two flavors of Linux
running on your Windows machine Ubuntu
and C Linux for the hackers guey support
GPU access shared files between Windows
and Linux you can use Linux commands on
Windows and windows commands on Linux
it's crazy it's like Linux and windows
became one person is it too powerful yes
it is and even if you think you know WSL
everything there is to know about it I
bet you in this video you're going to
learn something new in fact that's a
challenge if you watch this video and
you don't learn anything I give you
permission to leave a mean comment about
me like really make it personal attack
me as a person I'm giving you permission
get your coffee ready let's go okay
before we go crazy let's talk about what
you need who can run wsl2 and by the way
this is wsl2 there was a one this one is
obviously better for Hardware you'll
want a 64-bit processor and arm is
supported you want a minimum of 4 gigs
of RAM and like anything in it any
project I've covered the more Rim you
have the better you'll probably have the
best time with 16 or higher now before
we move on if you don't already have it
enabled you'll need to jump into your
bios and enable virtualization because
wsl2 uses lightweight virtual machines
so reboot your computer jump into your
bios you'll either hit Escape or F2 or
F10 or something it'll tell you and if
you have an Intel processor look for
something called Intel VTX and enable
that if you have AMD look for amdv that
will enable virtualization and you'll be
all set WSL doesn't need much so I hope
this includes most people let's talk
about software now of of course you want
to be running Windows this is Linux on
Windows but what flavor you will 100%
have the best time if you're running
Windows 11 if you're still holding the
line at Windows 10 you are supported but
you got to be at build
19041 almost forgot it or higher you can
very quickly check that by going to your
search bar and typing in w i n v r for
wind there and it should show you right
there hopefully you see a big Windows 11
there and of course there's one more
thing you need coffee everything in it
requires coffee Eric Chuck coffee
now here comes the 2-minute WSL install
first you'll launch your windows
terminal we'll just go to our search bar
type in terminal and it should be this
guy right here now we're about to
install it with one command but just
know this user account you're using for
me it's me Chuck it does need admin
privileges you'll find out real quick if
you don't have them because this command
will not work type this in with me WSL
D- install that's literally all we have
to do now to install WSL it was much
harder before check this out hit enter
you'll get a UAC prompt just say yes
and it's doing it it first enables the
virtual machine platform service another
UAC prompt will click yes now it's
installing the windows subsystem for
Linux it's going pretty quick actually
and notice it is installing Ubuntu
that's the default drro and now that
it's done we're going to go ahead and um
restart because it told us to just close
this out and reboot your
PC okay once your computer has rebooted
you should arrive here it's going to ask
you to set up a username I'll put in my
network Chuck and then set up a password
and just like that I'm in side Linux I'm
Ubuntu now we can leave WSL by tying in
exit or just by simply closing the
window but it's always there we can
launch our terminal once more and by
default it's going to launch you right
back into Powershell to launch Ubuntu
again just type in WSL DD and Ubuntu
we're back in let's type in exit to get
out and we can install more than just
Ubuntu watch this type in WSL d-list D-
online this will show you all the
available dros that you can download and
install one I care about is C Linux the
hacking Linux drro now we could install
that right here from the command line
similar to Ubuntu but it gave me some
problems let me show you a better way to
do it did you know you can install these
things right from the Windows store
watch this we'll go to our search bar
and type in store and launch the
Microsoft store here I'm simply going to
search for C Linux in the search bar at
the top hit enter and there it is now it
says I already have it installed it's
lying I don't know why we'll go and
click on that you should see the option
to install where mine says open liar go
and click on whatever your option is and
it should install and launch another
terminal simp similar to how it did with
Ubuntu proing you for a username and a
password and now I'm in Cali Linux we
can launch Ubuntu at the same time open
up another tab type in WSL DD and the
name of your Dro Ubuntu if you spell it
right it'll open now we're running
Ubuntu and Cali Linux and windows sign
by side now right now C Linux has no
tools installed it's a minimal install
let's change that run the command C-
tweaks let we get a nice menu let's
click on Madea packages just use your
directional arrows and go down hit enter
put your pseudo password in which will
be the password you set for the system
and let's install C linux's top 10 tools
scroll down hit the space bar to select
it tab hit enter to apply and hit okay
and hit enter again it's going to ask
you a few times maybe perfect time for a
coffee
break now actually while it's doing that
what do you say we play a newu I want to
show you a few cool things like first
how we can run a Windows command inside
Linux watch this ip config is how you
find out what your IP address is in the
Windows command prompt I can run that
right here inside Linux what I can use
the windows ping ping.exe I can open
files with notepad if I add exe at the
end exe I can even open up my current
location inside Windows Explorer type in
explorer.exe type in dot right after
that these are my Linux files right here
inside Windows Explorer that's nuts
let's reverse it let's go to Powershell
open up a new Powershell window this is
all windows I can type in ip config
which will give me my IP addresses but I
can filter using a Linux command I'll
type in ip config I'll pipe out of pipe
and then type in WSL to invoke a Linux
command and I'll say grap 410 dot how
cool is that by the way grap is a Linux
based command to filter based on search
it does more than that but that's just
one thing I can use the Linux cat
command WSL cat and then my file name
it's like Linux and windows have become
one person and I'm here for it now this
might take a minute it did for me I just
got some more coffee no big deal uh
we'll just tab over over and quit that
now you should have a few more C Linux
tools now there is one let me see if I
already have it installed here
spiderfoot let me install it this tool
is kind of crazy I just had to show you
it's an ENT tool or open source
intelligence tool for hackers I'm going
to launch it spiderfoot DL specify my IP
address which will be local here 1271
Port 51 oh wait
spiderfoot and now I got a web server
running on my WSL so cool I'm going to
launch my web browser real quick and go
to local post 51 and they're spiderfoot
this thing can find a ton of information
about people I want to do a scan I'll
name it my scan and then you scan your
target you can scan anything I'm going
to scan um a name Chuck Keith which is
my name let's run the scan and see what
it finds and watch the cool command
light stuff happening in the background
ooh we found stuff human
name and hacked email address what is
that no way okay this right here it's
not me but what it is was my dad's old
email address at a previous company yes
we're both named Chuck Keith it's a
thing that's kind of scary right hackers
use these tools all the time actually do
you want to see something
scary and honestly this makes me kind of
mad I'm going to launch my network Chuck
Cloud browser and go to a website called
truthfinder you don't have to be a
hacker to use this anyone can do it I
signed up for an account paid 30 bucks
and I searched for information on me and
not only did it find me it revealed so
much about me like my home address my
family members my age birth birthday
criminal record don't tell anybody my
assets social profiles and not just
where I currently live every place I've
lived this makes me mad because this is
public information anyone can create an
account here and find this information
about me that's not okay I actually had
someone go on Twitter and post my home
address publicly for everyone to see my
kids are legit afraid to walk outside by
themselves so what do I do about this
how do I get my information off these
sites and cogne they are the sponsor of
this video and they are a tool that can
help you get your information off this
stuff off all these lists and yeah these
are all just a list a database of
information about all of us I mean go
ahead look yourself up you're probably
there this information is bought sold
and traded amongst data Brokers so like
marketing companies research companies
HR companies will buy this information
so they can screen potential employees
profile them and of course the sides
like truthfinder who will buy up all
this information and offer it as a
service someone to try it out I'm going
to set up in cogy right now okay so I
just signed up I gave it some
information about me and I authorized it
to contact companies based on my behalf
now what does that mean look right here
I signed up and immediately it sent 83
requests to have my information removed
from some list or data broker so for
example look at the activity log
telephone list It's s request to remove
my information this is the reason I
never answer my phone a phone call comes
in if it's not a contact I know I don't
answer because every call is Spam I went
whenever it's election season because I
know I'm about to get a dozen calls a
day text emails it's an onslaught of
just spam and I feel helpless like what
do I do about that I suppose I could go
out to all these places that I didn't
already know about I have to research
and request my information to be removed
but that would take forever in cogni
estimates it takes the average person
about 304 hours too all that research
and submit the removal request but then
you have to like follow up because they
probably not going to do it the first
time you know and then maybe in a year
you get back on a few list I don't have
time for that do you have time for that
no you probably don't you're busy
studying right and that's where incog
comes in so they're doing this in
removal process currently these are
being sent out to all the private
databases and they're scanning right now
all the public databases and we'll
submit it on my behalf automatically not
only that it's going to be a regular
process they will constantly reach out
to the list of their data Brokers and
request my information be removed
they're on it like honestly I'm paying
for this myself but I'm going to keep
using it so I challenge you right now to
go out there and try to find information
on yourself go to truthfinder go to
People Finder see if you're out there if
you are do something about it incog will
take care of it for you I've got a link
below if you use the code Network Chuck
you'll get 60% off an annual plan and
honestly like this right here is a
no-brainer for me I felt pretty helpless
knowing that all my data was out there
and not really knowing what to do about
it anyways thanks to incog for
sponsoring this video and for helping me
deal with my really crazy problem okay
I'm going to stop running spiderfoot
it's kind of a creepy name for a tool I
don't like it I don't like spiders
comment below if you hate spiders like
me now I'm going to pop out of my demo
machine and get to my personal machine
here and show you some cool stuff let's
do some WSL command Basics now we
already saw how we could list available
dros online by typing in WSL d-list D-
online these are dros we can download
and install let's install um open sus
tumble weed that just sounds fun to
install that I'll type in WSL D- install
and then the drro name it's that simple
go oh look at this nice little screen I
wasn't expecting this have a lot of fun
I will okay cool I'm in open sus I'm
going to exit though now to see what I
have currently installed I can type in
WSL d-list D- verbos to see some more
stuff like which ones are running and
which ones are stopped speaking of
stopped how do I stop WSL or stop the
machines I have running if I type in WSL
D- shutdown that will shut down
everything if I run that same list
command as before with verbose all of
them stopped so now I have C and ubun 2
running how do I stop just one with this
command WSL D-
terminate and then specify the dro name
so let's say Cali
Linux and it's done it is is stopped now
notice in my list here I've got Ubuntu
with an asterisk next to it that means
that's my default drro if I want to make
C my default I can do it with this
command WSL D- set- default and then the
drro name but I don't want to do that I
like Ubuntu to check the status of WSL
we can type in WSL D- status which tells
us stuff we already know like our
default drro and we're running WSL to
now what if we want to remove a drro
uninstall it delete it this command so
I'm going to list my stuff once more
I'll remove open sus even even though he
had a really cool way to set him up the
command will be WSL D- unregister and
then the name of the uh drro it's kind
of wordy and with that it should be gone
if I do the same command before list for
Bose disappeared now one of the coolest
things about WSL is the fact that you
can use Windows files inside Linux so
for example if I'm in Ubuntu let me jump
over to my Ubuntu tab I can CD or change
directory to my C drive by go into SL
Mount SLC if I LS that's my windows hard
drive and I can jump into my directories
CD user
Chuck go to my downloads folder and
interact with anything here like let me
GP for a text file oh here's one and I
can mess with that that I use all the
time but you can also access your Linux
files so I've got a bunch of stuff in my
Linux directory let me get to my home
directory here I can access these and
windows there's a couple of ways to get
there but right now from the Linux
terminal if I type in Explorer a Windows
command. exe and just put the period
it's going to open up where I am inside
windows just opened up on my other
screen but here it is how cool is that
notice my location here this location is
actually saved by default in uh Windows
11 to your home bar on the side you've
got a little location here called Linux
your little penguin just hanging out and
if I expand that or even just click on
it I can see I have the locations and
storage for all of my Linux dros and I
can jump into those and I can copy and
paste files manipulate them whatever
again I'm telling you Linux and windows
became one now let's talk about gooey
apps wsl2 has a thing called WS LG which
allows you to launch apps from your
Linux command line and they open up as a
goey in your windows environment it
doesn't make any sense but it's awesome
watch this so check this out here in
auntu if I were to install wire shark a
tool used for capturing packets with
pseudo AP install wire shark I've
already got it installed now if I want
to launch it I'll just do pseudo wire
shark this is so cool it launched a
little gooey version of wire shark on
it's trying to get loaded up that's why
it's doing this weird thing don't judge
it by bad and this is an app just
running in Ubuntu I can launch Google
Chrome Google Chrome running inside
Ubuntu on Windows let me have wire
sharkk up to capturing these packets
here how cool is that that's just wild
so you can install any app that has a
guey and launch it from Ubuntu or CI
Linux and that just works out the gate
but cie C does something different kind
of uh a little insane check this out C
has a tool called winex and we're going
to install that right now with pseudo AP
install C-
win- we'll do a-y and run the install
after we put our pseudo password in with
it installed I'm going to run one
command kex just like this it's going to
ask me to set a password I'll put no for
view only and Watch What Happens at
first it's like what's going on it's not
doing anything but
then boom how cool is that full-blown
Cali works like a charm super quick I
love this you hit f8 to get your options
here you can get out of full screen just
make it a little window you can move
around to officially close it just go to
your log out options and just just log
out and if you want to stop it just type
in kex D dwin Das D stop now getting
back to Ubuntu over here I want to talk
about Nano if you've been watching me
for a while you know that Nano is my
favorite text editor in Linux open up me
a file super easy but that's been
replaced because Linux and windows
they're like this now and know I'm not
talking about notepad watch this if you
got VSS code installed now if you don't
know what VSS code is I got a video on
it VSS code's amazing right here in my
Linux terminal simply type in code and
the name of my file and it opens that
bad boy and vs code like and this isn't
like a a gooey app for Linux this is my
vs code installed in Windows doesn't
stop there though VSS code if I go to my
extensions I can search for WSL they
have a WSL extension I'll close vs code
and just open it again with the code
text.txt now notice when I'm opening vs
code the bottom left it connect me to
wuntu by default I can open up terminals
right here I'm auntu right now I can
access all the files easily keeping all
the auto complete goodness and all the
code things I like to have and then WSL
gets even crazier with Docker yes you
can run Docker containers inside WSL
opening up an entire world for you so
check this out you can install it in a
number of ways one way is to install
Docker from your terminal pseudo AP
install docker.io that's one way or if
you're wanting something special you can
install Docker desktop and what this
will do is use wsl2 as its source for
creating and managing Docker containers
and Docker desktop is really neat it
allows you to manage those uh containers
and look at them and look at the
networks and everything you create it's
very fun but I'll start start the
install here and notice in the config it
does say use WSL 2 instead of hyperv
okay now speaking of many people don't
like WSL or like to use it because it
interferes with using virtualization
software like virtual box which is
amazing and allows you to create virtual
machines that is not the case anymore
because virtual box has made an update
to where it'll default use hyperv which
will be enabled so you can use wsl2 with
virtual box side by side okay it wants
me to restart Windows okay fine I hate
it when it does that all right it
rebooted I'm going to accept a bunch of
stuff blindly I don't want to sign in I
want to continue without signing in I'm
going to skip the survey I'm not doing
anything and that's it Docker install
and jump back into auntu notice that it
did auto start because Docker desktop
started it I'm going to run a quick
Docker container I could do this from
Docker desktop I just prefer and and
we're comfortable with the command line
if I go to Docker desktop bam there's my
guy right there I can see images volumes
that's super slick it's not just that
though because back to VSS code you can
look at your Docker containers in WSL
via V code as well there's a Docker
extension which I'll install right now I
think I actually prefer it in VSS code
because it's just it's weird that you
can do that but I click on the little
Docker guy here with my extension
installed I can see my guy right here
files and everything that's so Nifty I
love it so much attached to the Shell
I'm inside my busy box guy isn't that
just cool I mean I just I love how
everything's just right here it's so
easy and powerful and speaking of
powerful my Linux stuff has access to my
GPU just as Windows does if I type in
nvidia-smi Linux can see my 3080 on my
demo machine here try doing that with a
virtual machine that's a pain in the
butt if even possible can virtual box or
VMware do that right now I'm not sure
now last thing I want to show you as we
go deeper and deeper down the rabbit
hole of WSL is the custom config you can
do WSL has two config files that you can
mess with first is our local one each
individual machine or drro you deploy
has its own little config file it's
called wsl.com we can find it here let
me show you real quick here in auntu I'm
going to go to I'll just open it up
Nano Etsy wsl.com
there it is now one thing I want to
point out that's just fun is that WSL
does fully support systemd but it is a
configurable option notice it is by
default set to true it's using systemd
and you can add other config here I'm
not going to demo everything or really
anything on that because I don't care
about it but you can do things like Auto
settings Auto mounting drives and yes
you can mount remote drives I mount my
Nas inside my WSL instance all the time
you can do some host name config with
network settings interoperability
settings user settings you can add a
default user you can have stuff run when
the instance boots and here's an example
file right here now the other file you
can have is a global file and I like
this one better because it has cooler
options this will apply to every single
WSL and sense you're running and this is
going to be stored in your Windows
operating system by default it's not
created it's going to be awsl conf fake
file and WSL is going to look for it
inside your user directory let's create
it real quick I got this one little
quick Snappy command that we're going to
run inside Powershell so here Powershell
window all windows baby run this command
notepad and it's going to open up a new
file within our user profile WSL config
and notepad it's going to go hey that
file is not created we're going to
create it right now cool no big deal now
one thing just one thing I want to demo
and show you how to do is changing the
networking mode so check this out we're
going to uh set up the file right now
first we'll do opening bracket and say
wsl2 closing bracket it's just telling
it hey we're doing wsl2 file it's going
to look for that and actually uh need it
there and then we're going to change
networking mode and the M will need to
be capitalized and I'll say equals
mirrored Now by default the networking
mode for WSL is natat I'm not going to
cover natat in too much detail just know
that this is my windows IP address I
think I actually don't know my WSL
instances are connected to this with a
separate Network work through net and
they'll look something like this
17216 3.4 I'm just assuming let me go
see what it actually is do an IP address
command yeah it's 17227 25390 this is
not on my local network it's a knat
connection its own separate Network and
by the way there's an 8sec rule they
have I'm Legit this is what they call it
like I'm not making this up uh if you go
to their documentation they call it the
8sec rule for configuration changes you
want to wait 8 seconds after you shut
the WSL instances down for the changes
to take effect cool think we are in that
limit so I'm in C Linux if I type in if
config once more didn't change what I do
wrong let me do it longer you know what
it did it added a txt to this bad boy
why did it do
that let's just remove that txt and now
WSL will use it that was a pain let's
shut them all down count to
eight and launch Cali once more fingers
crossed if config it matches Windows
right there mirrored mode versus not
mode removes a lot of issues you might
have and you can connect a WSL directly
from your local area network which is
pretty cool now one last thing I want to
show you one last Deep dive that's how
to back up your WSL instances your
little virtual machines that you might
pour a lot of love into to configure and
add tools you want to make sure you can
protect those so let's try it out with
this command I can back up a WSL machine
so uh with this command I'll list my
stuff WSL d-list D- veros to see what
they're doing I've got Ubuntu I'm going
to back him up to what's called a tower
file so I'll do WSL -- exort and I'll
specify Ubuntu and then the name of the
file I want to store it in so I'll just
call it
Ubuntu dotar and right now it's
exporting my Ubuntu machine and that's
it if I were to LS that and then grep
I'll use WSL to grep for it there it is
right there now what I want to try and
do is import this on another machine so
I'm going to open this up see where did
he go there it is ubun to.ar it's only
1.9 gigs I'm going to copy that onto my
main machine all right with it copied
over and by the way this is the first
time I've tried this hope it works I'm
going to do WSL D- import I'm going to
name it I can name this anything I'll
name it Tokyo specify where I want to
store it I'll put it here dwsl and then
the name of the tar file the location of
it it's right here Ready set go okay
it's importing that's it so now if I
list my stuff try it out WSL d-list
there's Tokyo let me connect to Tokyo SI
sick okay cool that worked oh I forgot
one thing I had to turn my cameras back
on just to tell you this when connecting
to an imported instance notice it kind
of defaulted to the root user and that
kind of freaked me out because I had
some files here and they're not here but
they were here in my other auntu I
created like two little test text files
well you can specify the user account
you connect as so I do WSL DD and Tokyo
then I'll do dasu for user and specify
Network Chuck to connect as Network
Chuck and there we go type in Ln
there's my files sorry I almost forgot
that also if you like the way my stuff
looks let me know if you want me to make
a video on how to do that I kind of love
it especially when I can do this and
have it look like a boont and be nice
and clean okay that's everything WSL
from the flashy cool stuff to the nerdy
things that you may want to do to back
things up or make your networking work I
hope you enjoyed it I'll catch you guys
next time