hi everyone welcome back to my channel
today i wanted to make
a gmail tutorial for beginners i feel
like a lot of people
nowadays are maybe switching to gmail
getting gmail accounts
using google me things like that and i
personally
love gmail i think it has a lot of
really great features
but if you're not familiar with them or
aren't used to them i can understand how
they could be confusing so
i wanted to go over some of them today i
will leave a list in the description box
of the topics that i'll be covering
today along with their time stamps so
let's get started
i obviously want to start with the
basics and talk about composing an
email and everything that you can do
with composing an email
so to start drafting an email you're
just going to go up here
to the plus sign or where it says
compose
click on that and this box will pop up
right here
and you can easily just start typing
your email but if you want to make this
little pop-up larger you can do that by
clicking this button right here
which is full screen it doesn't make it
totally full screen but it does expand
it if you are going to be typing a
longer email and want to see it in a
larger format
you can also set this as your default
email draft method so instead of the
small pop-up window you can set this as
your default
by going to more options and default to
full screen
so now if you compose an email it's
going to default to the larger box
instead of the smaller pop-up but if you
do
want to go back to the smaller pop-up
you just click this button again
and it will go to the smaller pop-up
window now i want to talk about
something called
smart compose which you may or may not
have noticed
happens while you're typing out emails
in gmail
so when you start typing a sentence
google has this feature
where it will kind of guess what you're
trying to say
so let's say good morning i hope
and then it fills in the rest this email
finds you well
and if i do if that's exactly what i
wanted to say i can just click
tab and it will finish filling it in for
me
if you like that feature you can keep it
but there's also a way to turn it off if
you do not like it
which i will show you how to do so if
you go up here to settings
you might have to minimize your window
to see the settings
you want to click see all settings so
here are all the settings and if you
scroll down
you'll see smart compose and it tells
you a little bit about what smart
compose
is and so you can turn the writing
suggestions
on or off in this general settings
section you can also change
the undo send settings which can be
really helpful
if you didn't know once you send an
email there is a little bit of a delay
where you can actually click
undo send if you made a mistake or
attached to the wrong document
so in this undo send section right here
you can see that you can change the send
cancellation period
to all the way up to 30 seconds
if you do make any changes make sure you
scroll all the way to the bottom to
click
save changes and
now i'll show you what it looks like if
you actually do accidentally send an
email that you want
to undo so i'm just going to add
random recipient say good morning
i hope and let's just say you
accidentally sent it without saying i
hope this email finds you well
this box will pop up down here for 30
seconds if that's what you send it to
so for 30 seconds you have the option to
click undo
if you realize right as you sent it that
you had a typo or sent the wrong
attachment
or something like that if you click undo
it will just take you back to the email
as a draft
and you can fix whatever your typo was
and send it again you can also choose to
schedule an email instead of
sending it right at the time you draft
it and the way you do that is
right next to send there's this drop
down and you can click schedule send
these are just kind of standard times
that they pick for you but if you want
to pick your own
you just click pick date and time and
you can change
the exact time that you
want to send it and then schedule send
and then to see the messages that you've
scheduled on the left-hand side here you
can see scheduled
and then if something changes before
it's
scheduled to go out you can of course
click cancel send
and then it'll just bring you back to
the draft you can make any changes that
you need to
before it gets sent out next up i want
to talk about changing your default
text style so within your email if you
highlight you can go down here
to change font size all of that to
maybe make typing or reading your emails
easier
but you can also change that as a
default setting so we're just going to
discard this draft for a second
go to settings see all settings again
and here is the default text style so if
you want to change it to be
large or huge you can do that and it
will show you what it's going to look
like if you wanted to change
your default text to be read
you can also change the font and then
again if that's what you wanted you can
just scroll down and click save changes
another thing you may have noticed if
you use gmail for work or something
like that sometimes if somebody sends
you an email with the same subject line
as an email somebody else sent you it
will actually
group those emails together and
sometimes that can be
very unhelpful when you're trying to
search for emails so you can turn that
setting off
which is something that i like to do on
my gmail personally so
if you go to general settings of course
and scroll down
to conversation view you can turn
conversation view
off and that way emails with the same
subject line
won't be grouped together which will
make it easier for you to find
and sort through your emails if you want
to add a signature you can just
go to general settings again scroll down
and there is a signature section right
here so
you can click create new you'll just
have to name it something like
default signature maybe phone and email
whatever you want to name it and then to
the right right here
you can start with your email signature
so
you can make it bold
you can make your name larger you can
underline italics
you can also insert a link maybe to your
website if you want to do that
you can also add an image if you want to
add a logo for your business
you can insert an image and this is
another important feature
so for signature defaults for new emails
use
no signature or the default signature
and on reply and forward you can also
change if you want no signature or the
default
so we're gonna click for new emails use
default signature slash
phone we're gonna do it for replies and
forwards as well
so then we're gonna click save changes
so that way when i go to compose a new
email my signature is just already in
there and i can start typing
above it if you're going to be out of
the office and not responding to emails
you can of course
set an out of office or vacation
reminder which is in
general settings so if you scroll all
the way to the bottom
that's where the vacation responder is
so
if you're gonna turn it on obviously
click on and then you can do the first
day
you can also select the last day or you
can manually cancel it which i'll show
you how to do
you just need to add a subject
i will be unavailable till monday save
changes
and now as you can see this yellow bar
is telling me that i have an out of
office message
on so if i wanted to manually end it
maybe i was just out of office for the
afternoon
i can click end now and once that yellow
bar goes away
that means that you're out of office
message is turned off so the next thing
i want to talk about is email
forwarding so i pulled up an email here
that i would like to forward along to
somebody else
so the way i can do that is by scrolling
down and clicking
forward or you can go to these three
dots up here
and click forward as well so as you can
see it's forwarding the entire chain
and i have sent two emails in this chain
email number one
and email number two but i only want to
forward email
number two i don't want email number one
to be in this thread
so what i can do is just highlight that
and delete it and now only email number
two is coming up
you can also erase all of this right
here at the top
you know with the emails and everything
just delete that so it just says
forwarded message at the top and then
right underneath it is the forwarded
message you can also just delete the
forwarded message
and now the only thing that the person's
gonna see that you're forwarding is
email number two
also let's say that there was an
attachment in the email that you don't
need to send you just need to send the
body of the email
at the bottom here any attachments will
show up so if you scroll all the way
down to the bottom
you can just click this x button and it
will remove any attachments and then you
can send along this email with just the
text in the body of the email
finally i want to talk about some
settings that can make it easier for you
to find your old mail in your inbox
which is a complaint that my dad has he
thinks it's hard to find
old messages in gmail so if you go to
your settings again
and scroll down there's a couple inbox
types that you can choose from
you can choose default which is it just
puts all of your emails
in chronological order from when you
received them
regardless if you've opened them or not
but another option is to do
unread first which i find to be very
helpful
because now all the messages that i have
not read that i know i need to go
through
are at the top of my inbox and all the
ones i have read
are down here at the bottom if you're
looking for something specific
you can obviously just search your mail
for
either a person or a subject line or
the content in an email and hopefully it
will pop up
you can also check your trash and the
way you do that
is on the left hand side if you click
more
and scroll down you can click trash and
anything that you
maybe accidentally deleted might be in
the trash
after 30 days as you can see here
messages in the trash are automatically
deleted so this is really only like
recently deleted emails
but this is also where you can check
your spam sometimes you get messages
from like
health charts or things like that that
might go to your spam folder
this is where you would look for your
spam emails
that is it for today i really hope you
enjoyed this video if you did
please give it a thumbs up and also
subscribe to my channel i really
appreciate the support
if you want me to make another video
with some more advanced gmail tips or
just additional gmail tips
let me know in the comments and i would
be happy to do that thank you so much
for watching today and i will see you in
my next video
bye
you