Obsidian tutorial 2025. In this video,
I'll be showing you how to use Obsidian
for organizing your notes, creating
linked ideas, and building a clean,
structured workspace. We will be going
step by step through the basics so you
can start using Obsidian efficiently,
even if you are a complete beginner. In
this video, I will be showing you how to
use Obsidian to organize your notes,
link ideas, manage projects, and build a
clean knowledge system from scratch. So
before we start, let's get to know
Obsidian a little bit. Obsidian is
basically a powerful a very powerful
note takingaking app. It is based on
plain text markdown files. And the main
idea behind Obsidian is that your notes
stay on your device and you can connect
them together using backlinks. This
makes it perfect for students,
freelancers, content creators, and
basically anyone who wants a long-term
knowledge base. And now in this video,
we are going to start by creating our
vault. Then we make some pages, link
notes, uh build daily notes, add tags,
and use community plugins, create simple
project management workflow. Now,
everything I'm going to show in this
video is going to be done using the free
version. So, this is the free version
and it is enough to be doing any of the
tasks that I'm going to show you. If you
need to go further ahead and, you know,
go for more advanced um features, then
you can go for the you can upgrade your
plan. So, let's dive in. Over here we
have Obsidian. You're you're going to
open it on your web and then you are
going to get Obsidian for Windows. So
you're going to have to install Obsidian
uh in order to get it to work. We are
going to download it for Windows. There
is the information about it. So just go
ahead and download. All right. So what
we need to do is download Obsidian for
Windows. And once you do that, you're
going to end up with the Obsidian setup.
Now you have to run this and click
finish. So it starts um installing and
you are going to create your new vault.
So in Obsidian um what you have is you
have a vault in there. So you're going
to create a new Obsidian vault under a
folder. Now other options include
opening uh the folder as a vault and you
also have open vault from obsidian sync.
So because we are new here and we are
going on Obsidian for the first time. So
for the first time you are going to have
to create a new vault. Now, this is just
syncing and this is using an older
folder. So, we're not going to use
those. We are going to create a new
vault. And just click on the create
button over here. And it says that uh it
is going to create a local vault. So,
you need to put in your vault name,
whatever you're going to name your
vault. So, I'm just going to name it
Nicole's vault. And then you need to
choose the location for your vault. So,
you're going to pick a place to put your
new vault. So just browse and click
decide where you want to put your vault.
And after selecting that you're just
going to click on create. And there we
go. This is our new vault. It has been
created. That was fairly simple. Nothing
complicated and no hurdles involved. So
this is the vault. It says the vault
name down here. Nicole's vault. Let me
see what other options there are. You
can just you can manage vaults. You can
have more than one vault, I guess. So uh
you can manage that from here. So now
what I am seeing over here is first we
have the welcome section here and then
on the right over here we have the graph
view. The graph view is more of like a
visual view. It says welcome and then
create a link. So right now we are at
welcome. So right now we are over here
at welcome and then you are going to
create a link. So I think that is going
to be the second step. Now let's read
what it says here. It says welcome. This
is your new vault. Make a note of
something. create a link or try the
importer. When you're ready, delete this
note and make the vault your own. So,
you're going to erase this and then
you're going to uh create your own note.
But before we do that, let's go over
here to the left and see what we have in
the toolbarss over here. So, first you
have open quick switcher. You have a
graph view which is uh over here that we
viewed. Then you have create new canvas.
So, you can create a new canvas. So this
is a create new canvas. You can create a
new canvas from here. Right now we are
on the uh welcome note. So if you want
to you want a completely blank canvas.
So you're going to click that and you
can create a new canvas. This is just
like uh when you click a new file. So
you get a new page. So that's what it is
going to do. Then you can open today's
daily note. So from here you can open
today's daily note. When you click on
that this is going to show up the date
over here. And then you can write
whatever note you want. This is the
daily note. So what anything you want to
note down daily, this is going to be
part of that. Now the welcome note has
slided down. And then this has come
above that. So if you want to keep it,
you can keep it. So this is going to be
listed. All your notes are going to be
listed here with their titles. This is
the title for this one here. If I click
here, I can edit that. So if I uh click
here, it got removed and it got deleted.
Uh in fact not just the note the the
whole tab got removed. The note did not
get deleted. So that is what you get
when you open the daily note and this is
the welcome note here. So when I go here
I just want to delete this. So right
click and delete that. I don't want to
um keep that daily note. Now what I
still do have is the welcome note that
was here when I came here. So after
going to open today's daily note, you
can go down here and it says insert
template. So when you click here you can
insert template. When you click here,
some templates should open up. This is
failed to list templates because no
template folder is configured. So once
you do that, you will be able to insert
any templates that you would like. And
there is the open command palette. So
now this is a list of all the commands
that you can use. Um there is the add
alias, add file property. Uh so there
are so many uh there are bookmarks,
canvas, change theme. There are so many
commands to choose from and some of them
have shortcuts as well. So if you're
someone who likes to use shortcuts, you
can come here and memorize these or
remember to use them whenever you like.
And then there are a lot of options for
these commands. So you can use these.
And in case if you are someone forgetful
like me, uh you can come here and you
can just come here for inspiration and
see what kind of commands you can give.
If you're someone new, you can come here
and see what kind of commands you can
get. What kind of functions are possible
in here. So, let's just exit that. So,
those were the commands. Then you have
create new base. And once you click on
that, what you're going to see is a a
whole new base is going to be created.
This is uh untitled. It it does appear
in the list. Um there is no title, but
it says base right next to it. And
what's going to happen is you can create
a table. You can create it in table
view. So, this is going to be your table
view. Uh other than that you also have
another view. You can add other kinds of
views that you would like. The other
view could be in the form of cards or in
the form of list. So the view you can
adjust according to your preference. And
then the rows the row height you can
decide which kind of height you want for
your row short, medium, tall or extra
tall. So let's just keep that medium.
And that is what the medium height for
the rows appears like. Now, uh, I would
like to see a second view. So, I do want
to make changes to the second view. So,
I do want to make some changes to this
view. So, I'm going to right click on
here and it says view and the layout is
the table and the row height is medium.
So, and we're going to keep the height
as medium and the table. I want to
change the table view to cards view. So,
this is what the art view is going to
look like. There isn't a lot of stuff in
here in the cards, but you can see that
the view is for cards. This is what the
view is going to look like. And going
back to the table view, this is what the
table view is going to look like. So, we
have two kinds of views. We have the
table view and then we have the um cards
view. And I should have named it
differently. I should have named it
card. So, these are the two kinds of
views that I have here. You can create
uh another kind of view if you like. So,
now this view is called the base. This
is basically uh it really actually is
the base of the whole vision over here.
Now this is very neat, very uh clean.
There's this panel over here and there's
this space over here for your notes. So
this it's not distracting at all. It's
very organized and neat and clean. So
now just to uh actually keep it uh clean
as it was, I would like to remove this
base which I have just created. So I'm
just going to delete that because it's
not really serving any purpose uh for me
right now. So we've seen these tools
over here. Okay. What uh up here what we
have is the collapse function. You do
that. So now this file over here what
it's going to do is basically it's going
to hold all of your files in like this
list over here. So this is where all
your files are going to be uh all the
files that you have created that you
have added that you have shared that you
have imported that you have saved those
all are going to be here. Now over here
you can search for the different
options. You can search a path, you can
search any file, a tag, um anything. So
this is the search section like us
usually is in all kinds of platforms.
And then you have your bookmarks. So the
bookmarks over here. Now going back to
our files. Now this is the file that we
have. So what mainly uh this platform
what this obsidian is for is that you
can create your notes here and then you
can actually create links between your
notes. So now you must have noticed how
uh the view has changed a little bit
since we started. So first when we came
in we had the panel we had the welcome
note here and then on this side we had
the the graph view. So the graph view
has disappeared. Now let's bring the
graph view back. Uh what you're going to
do for that is you're going to go to the
three dots here and you are going to go
down to split right. Now you can split
the this uh section here uh downwards as
well. But what we're going to do is
we're going to split it uh to the right.
And there are a lot of other options
here as well which are really
self-explanatory. But just to get back
our graph view, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to split it to the right. Now
on this right side, I'm going to open up
the graph view. And that is the graph
view. And this is the welcome. So we're
back to how the view was right at the
start. And we were at welcome. And next
we want to create a link. So let's click
on create link. Now this is create link.
Now of course if we want to uh create a
link we need to have one thing uh ready
to create a link with the other. So I'm
going to do is not move this back to
graph view. Graph view. Uh, I want you
to see the graph view because it's going
to be very interesting when you see um
the things are going to get linked up.
So, we're going to leave that on the
side. Now, what I'm going to do is and
I'm going to delete this as well. What
I'm going to do is I'm going to um name
uh our first uh note. So, in this note,
I'm going to remove this and I'm going
to write a uh small note. I'm going to
call this the welcome page. And then I'm
going to come down here. And so that was
the heading. And then I'm going to come
down here. So I'm going to type in we
are going to start using obsidian. And
so see that has a spelling correction.
We're going to start using obsidian and
add an exclamation mark because we are
so excited. So now you can highlight
this and then if you uh right click you
have um you can uh cut paste and you can
uh use these options as well. And then
for um formatting if you go there you
can uh convert it to bold italics or
anything else. So I hope it goes well
and um you can um edit that as well. So
what you basically what you want to do
is uh just you know type in some uh text
and familiarize yourself with um all
these options and the kind of formatting
you can do which is basically pretty
much the same actually. So no no no
specific practice is needed but you can
also highlight this. So now this is how
it goes. Uh so this is our welcome page.
Now I'm going to uh create another note.
So let's go here and click on new note.
So our previous note is saved here. Now
we're going to create our new note and
I'm going to title this note ideas. So
these are going to be our ideas. And
over here you can put in anything uh
that you usually brainstorm about. So
what I'm going to put in is I'm going to
put in a video topics and tasks research
notes. So now uh this is our second
note. The first note was welcome page
and the second is ideas. So within
welcome page I have written things
related to you know our welcome and then
in the second note I have written things
related to the ideas that I have. Now
they don't have any link with each
other. So there is no link no link has
been created. Now, what I'm going to
show you Obsidian is famous for and what
is absolutely impressive about this and
what makes u Obsidian more powerful or
what the most powerful part of Obsidian
is that it makes these links by itself
on its own. So, when I go to the welcome
page, I'm just going to go uh down here
and I'm going to type in ideas and I'm
going to add um brackets here. So, I'm
going to add the brackets here. And once
the brackets are set in, we have ideas.
Now this has turned uh purple. So this
is highlighted and some link has been
created. Now uh as soon as the link has
been created, you can see in the graphic
view, this is why I wanted the graphic
view to stay open. A link has been
created between these two notes. Now
what is the link? The ideas. I wrote
ideas here and then in this we had ideas
here. This was this had the title ideas
and then it had those ideas there. So a
link has been created between both of
these two notes and I did not have to
make the link. Obsidian has made that
link for us. Now uh because we are aware
of what we're doing and um I did this
intentionally to show you but um other
times what can happen is you can have a
long list of notes here so many notes
here and you can just keep brainstorming
and storing your ideas writing down your
ideas uh importing any uh notes here and
then as soon as the connections are
being made uh you might not be aware of
the connections that they have with one
another but Obsidian is going to map out
those connections for you and connect
them for you which would be very
impressive and sometimes you're just
going to surprise yourself and see how
this connection is made and you had no
idea that these connections were made.
Sometimes you would not know that there
a connection is there but uh
intentionally if you are using obsidian
for that purpose you definitely would
know that uh these connections are going
to be made. So you're going to take
notes on uh different topics but which
are interrelated. So you're going to uh
take your neat notes. Your notes are
going to be neat and you're going to uh
note them down and store them here. And
the way they are connected is going to
be displayed in the graph view here or
uh it would be highlighted how those
different notes are connected would be
shown to you very clearly. Now this is
something which is uh you know you have
a very visual kind of display of all the
thoughts which are jumbled up in your
brain. uh you can uh display them out
here very neatly or uh without worrying
about overlapping concepts or missing
something out or you know just
scrambling to when you're writing you
don't want to scramble back to your
previous note and say oh no I missed I
missed this from there so I'm going to
wait hold on I'm going to go back and
I'm going to put this uh in the other
note so you don't have to do that you're
just going to note it here and the
connections will be made for you so that
is uh absolutely so convenient and so
helping. It just um frees your brain of
any worries of organizing and noting
down your notes in an orderly manner or
you know being very uh cautious of what
you are noting and where. So you just uh
note down very freely with a calm brain
and focus more on your creativity and
your productivity and that is basically
the aim of obsidian. So now I am going
to create another node and I'm going to
name it content. So I'm going to name
that content and I'm going to write here
um I store new ideas here. So and then
over here I'm going to type in I I store
new content
idea in in ideas. So a link has been
created as you can see. So I store uh
the new content ideas are going to be
stored in ideas over here. So a link has
been made again and you can see a visual
or graphic representation of that. You
have the ideas is linked to the welcome
page and ideas is linked to content as
well. So that is some pretty neat stuff.
Now another very useful thing you can do
is is you can use hashtags um in your
notes. So over here what you can do is
you can add a hashtag and you can type
in content. So uh this is where we've
mentioned content and then you can go to
ideas and over here you can enter in the
hashtag again and you can name it
content and uh that link is already
created and then you can go back to the
welcome page and then you can add that
here as well. Add your hashtag and
content. So we are talking about content
in all three of these pages now. And
then once you have your uh hashtags set,
so you have the hashtag here and here
and here. So you have it in all three.
Now when you uh click on the hashtag, so
it's going to display all the notes
which have that hashtag. So it's going
to say uh this tag is in this note and
this note and this note. So let's go and
uh change our notes and let's remove one
from here. So let's remove it from
ideas. So let's remove the hashtag from
here. And then uh then when we go to for
example we go to the welcome page, it's
not in ideas and it's in content. So
when you click here, only those two show
up which have content. So that is uh
using the hashtag is also a pretty neat
feature. All right. So now that we know
uh the basics of notes, let's move
towards uh plugins. So uh in order to go
to plugins you need to first of all go
to your settings uh click here and you
are going to go down here. Now there are
a lot of other options. You have the
core plugins and the hotkeys and you can
also um adjust the appearance over here.
Um actually this is the accent color
here. So you can uh change that as well
if you would like and you can also
change the base color scheme. So um in
order to adapt to the system and I uh
you know I have deviated from what I
came here for but I really want to
change this to dark version. Uh that is
my preference. So this is also very
good. Now so uh what we came here for
was to um go to was to get to the
plugins. So you also have hotkeys and
you have the canvas and there are some
other settings as well which are pretty
straightforward and clear and
self-explanatory. So you can uh figure
out those. So uh for the plugins you're
going to go to the community uh you're
going to click on community plugins and
then over here you are going to go to uh
what you need to do here is you need to
turn on community plugins. This is going
to remove you from restricted mode. Um
so you want to do that in order to turn
on the community plugins. So you turn
that on and you and you are not in uh
restricted mode anymore. Restricted mode
is off. And then you have a current you
do not have any current plugins either.
So you're going to go to community
plugins and you're going to browse the
plugins that you can use. Now I am going
to suggest some plugins that uh
beginners can use. So some recommended
uh beginner plugins are the calendar. So
you can go down here and so these are
all the plugins that are available and
you can use over here is the calendar
that you can use. Over here is the
calendar that you can use and this is
for u daily notes navigation. So uh that
is very important. Then you can go to uh
let's see where if I can see it here. So
it's not visible uh right here. I can
just uh search for it. Yes, here we go.
So this is the canvan view here. uh you
want to select that uh or you want to
have that plugin because it makes uh
Trello style boards inside of Obsidian
and um I I personally really like those
boards. So uh if you want to incorporate
that into your uh Obsidian then you want
to uh get that plug-in as well. Uh you
also want to get data view uh because it
has powerful databases using notes. So,
you're going to uh type in data view and
you are going to uh you can get like
you're not going to but you can if you
would like uh so you can get that. These
are just my personal recommendations for
uh any beginner plugins that you would
like. Uh after that you can get a task.
So that has advanced to-do list filters.
So if you have any to-do lists um you
know in advanced form you can uh get
tasks for that. You can also get
advanced tables which is easy table
formatting. So for the tables you can
get that. So what you're going to do is
you're just going to install that and
then you are going to go back and you
are going to start using it and you you
can use uh those views and you can start
incorporating those with your um
Obsidian. So those were just some of my
personal uh recommendations for
beginning uh here at uh Vault. So I'm
just going to give you some useful tips
on staying organized at Obsidian. What
you should always be mindful of is to
use short note titles. So all your
titles you want to keep them short
because you know there is just limited
space and to be more organized you just
want to use short titles because there
are going to be numerous uh a lot of
notes over here and they're going to get
stored. So you just want to uh from the
very start I mean it looks pretty
organized right now. When you have a lot
of notes it's not going to be so
organized. So you need to keep the
titles very short. Now, another thing
you want to be mindful of is to link the
notes often. So, you want to make links
uh with the notes. Then you also want to
add tags consistently. So, the hashtags
that we added, you want to consistently
add them because, you know, this kind of
management is really important when you
have a lot of notes. Then, you need to,
you know, to be at the top of your game,
you need to be able to pull out
whichever notes you need. And with tags,
that would be very helpful. Uh, you also
want to create a weekly review note. So,
you want to review things and you want
to create a note for that and go over
the notes from that week. You also want
to move old notes into an archive folder
instead of deleting them. So, don't
delete notes as they get older. You just
want to archive them. You also should
try to use templates to save time. So,
uh like we checked here, uh we did not
have any templates. Um, so, uh,
templates, we did not have any
templates, but when you go in here, uh,
there is a way to add in templates that
you want. So, uh, do a little more
research on that and add templates and
make sure to use those templates to save
your time. And lastly, you really want
to keep your vault simple. So, expand
only when you need it. You don't uh over
complicate things uh just because you've
started and this is, you know, you're a
beginner. So, don't over complicate
things. Keep it simple is always best.
And that is it. That is how to use
Obsidian for notetaking and project
management in 2025.