We'll guide you through how to insert a
PDF file in Word. If you find this
useful, then consider subscribing and
liking the video. Here we are in Word
and so you want to go and add and insert
a PDF file into your document. We're
going to guide you through this step by
step. Make sure she's full guide and
don't skip anything as there are
different ways this can be done and so
you can go and learn about them and then
you can go and decide the way you want
to because for example you could go add
in a PDF icon to go and open it up or we
can go and add it into it. So you can go
and see the look that you want to go and
achieve. So make sure you know where
you've got the file. In this case I've
got on my desktop. Now that we know that
what you need to do is you want to go to
the top of Word to the top ribbon. go
and find the option for insert and you
want to go and click on it. Next, you
want to go over to the right into this
section which says text and you want to
go and find the option for object and
you want to go and click on it like so.
You then go and get this popup. So, it
says create new but what you need to do
is go to the top and you want to go and
press create from file like so. Now, we
need to go and find the file first of
all. So, we'll go and say file name.
Don't worry, just press browse to the
right. Now what you need to do is go and
locate the PDF you want to do it with.
So as I said mine is on my desktop so
I've located here but go wherever you
need to. You can select it and you can
then go and press insert in the bottom
right and you can then come over to the
right here. So what you can do is you
can go and choose whether you want to go
and display it as the icon or we can go
and add the contents in. So we're going
to start with just displaying it as the
file itself not the icon. So you can
press okay and as you can see it's now
been added in. So that's the worst way
you can add it in. And of course you can
then go and resize it by using the
corner points like so. Click hold and
drag and that's useful. Now
alternatively as I said you can go and
add it as the icon. So let's press
objects. Press create from file and
press browse to the right. Then what you
can do is select the PDF and press
insert and you can go and press display
as icon. You'll go and see how it will
look there. Change it if you want to. I
like the look of it though. And press
okay. And there it is. So that's it. You
can then adjust it to your liking. If
you found this useful and you want to
see more guides like this, then please
consider subscribing and liking the