sql it's more than an injection get out
of here it's the love language of our
databases you know the massive excel
spreadsheets that run the world you need
to learn sql
probably right now especially if you
want this job or this job or this job or
pretty much any job at it and it's a
skill i've actually had to use a lot
almost too much too much my comfort
cameron have you had to use sql yeah
whenever i was a aws cloud engineer i
dealt with databases all the time so
whether you're an aspiring hacker
looking to do some sql injections get
out of here or you're a cloud engineer
wanting to query all your qualms away
say that 10 times fast query all your
qualms away
i can't do it one time two times oh my
gosh this is definitely a skill you want
to add to your toolbox right now now
before you freak out we're not going too
deep here you don't need to become a sql
expert unless you want to become a dba
or something you poor brave stupid soul
but you're making bank and you're rich
but knowing the basics like hey what
even is a database that goes a long way
in pretty much every area of i.t so in
this video i'm going to teach you sql
not too much like a goldilocks amount of
sequel just enough to make you dangerous
but not too dangerous i don't want you
dropping elbows on some poor
unsuspecting tables so by the end of
this video you will know how to create
your own my sequel or mysql database
and you're gonna add some stuff into it
remove some stuff query some things so
get your coffee ready mine is right here
and let's learn some sql
now while you're sipping that coffee
getting all fueled up ready to go to
learn some sql let me tell you a scary
story did you know that your usernames
and your passwords they're often stored
inside a sql database and sometimes
these databases spring a leak spilling
your username and password all over the
dark web david bumble i'm disappointed
you gotta protect yourself this is where
our sponsor dashlane comes in dashlane
does a great job at protecting you from
yourself come on johnny i love their
password health feature which obviously
i got some work to do i got 28
compromise passwords and two weak ones
no weakness allowed and i also love
their dark web monitoring because i
wasn't kidding these databases full of
your passwords and emails and all kinds
of stuff get hacked and leaked all the
time on the dark web they monitor that
stuff for you and they'll tell you hey
change your day and password and then
right here is my favorite feature of
dashlane it's got two factors built
right into it so log into networkcheck
academy i've got my security code right
here oh don't copy that no it's gonna
change so i pretty much use dashlane for
everything including my business i
forced all of my employees to use
dashlane because they're crazy and they
still write their passwords down on
post-it notes come on so if you have a
business use dashlane they've got a
great admin section little admin console
where you can manage all your passwords
for your employees gotta keep them
suckers in line and it's not just
passwords you can put secure notes you
can put your payments in here i use this
all the time it makes paying for things
so much easier so don't let someone
else's bad database put you at risk get
yourself the password manager i
recommend dashlane go out to
dashlane.com slash network chuck 50. and
you do get a discount let me double
check what that is i forgot
oh sweet you get 50 off so use that code
you can use it on pretty much any device
you have which i do on every device
thank you to dashlane for sponsoring
this video now let's get back to sequel
here we go
so sql or sql it stands for structured
query language focus on that term
language because it is kind of like a
programming language similar to python
except the primary use of sql is to talk
to databases i told you it's their love
language they love it that's my database
by the way i'm going to label it using
this query language we'll talk to our
database we'll create things we'll read
things we'll update things we'll delete
things crud you've heard of crud right
well you just did so here we go we are
going to learn some sql here in a bit
but first let's talk about what's a
database i joked earlier how it's just
one big giant excel spreadsheet that's
kind of true you've probably seen an
excel spreadsheet before right it has
columns
or fields it has rows or we might call
those records and these rows or records
contain our data and while excel might
work for carrying the account and
keeping track of your budget you bought
45 raspberry pi's for bigger sets of
data like websites might have companies
even network chuck coffee they won't
store these in excel they'll store them
inside a database which will function
very similarly to an excel spreadsheet
because we're still working with this
which we'll call a table but we might
need more than one and we might need a
lot more data so in my network coffee
database i might have three excel
spreadsheets or three tables one for all
my customers which did you know that
marvel characters love my coffee thor
can't get enough of the help desk he
loves it and then i'll have a table of
all the copies i offer and then of
course an order table
tracking all the orders that are placed
and this is a very very small
abbreviated example of all the data my
network check coffee database might have
which it does have so the takeaway here
is that databases are used to store
large amounts of data data that karen
and her spreadsheet in excel couldn't
even dream about now these databases
they need a manager they need someone to
control them to get them in line because
they can act pretty crazy if they don't
have someone watching them that's why we
have dbms a david bumble management
system i'm just kidding i've been
picking out him a lot in this video love
you david dbms stands for database
management system and actually you've
probably heard of a few of them
microsoft sql server mysql or i'm sorry
mysql get
am i saying that right i don't know
oracle there's a lot out there but just
know that whatever dbms you choose
whether it be mysql sql oracle whatever
their job is to manage your databases
they will have different ways they do
that but they're all going to use sql
the structure clearly i can't say it
structured query language there we go 10
times fast on that one this is actually
a standard that's been ratified by the
iso iso so if you learn sql you can
pretty much approach most databases with
relative ease now there are some nuances
some differences going from like
microsoft sequel to mysql but it's
nothing you can't google as long as you
understand the concepts now just so you
know we're going to create these three
databases ourselves we're going to
install one and actually make it happen
with mysql but before we do that there
are two database types you have to know
about this one we're talking about here
this is a relational database you might
see it abbreviated as rdbms and they by
far are the most popular it's what i
drew out here and what makes it
relational is these tables here kind of
like they're related
they're cousins or brothers i don't know
they're in the family and what i mean is
like when in this table here on my
orders table it says for order zero zero
one the coffee was one you're like what
is what does that mean well it's
actually tying back to the coffee
database and then when it says customer
is three you probably guessed it's
looking back at the customer database
saying hey
tony stark
ordered the default route he loves that
stuff now again we're going to zero in
on the relational database but the other
type you want to know about is the
non-relational this one doesn't have any
family or any friends he's very sad
we're not going to cover what it is here
but one type or one dbms you might hear
about is nosql which fireship did a
great joke on twitter when i asked you
guys if you know sql well played sir but
in nonrelational it's not like this it's
not related it's kind of unstructured
data and it definitely has its use case
and purpose but we're not going to cover
that right here okay enough about
databases let's actually make one right
now it's completely free and completely
fun now here's what you need you won't
need much pretty much any computer
that's it we're going to be playing with
mysql or mysql and you can pretty much
install that anywhere for free including
windows now i will be walking you
through linux because i love linux and
it's so easy so if you want to follow
along with me exactly from the beginning
from the start i'm going to be running
the latest version of ubuntu desktop
inside a virtual box vm if you're like
wait what what's he doing i've got a
video right here on how to set up
virtual machines and what they are and
why they're incredible you should go
watch that
if you haven't already and it's
completely free to run this
and yeah that's it oh i forgot you need
coffee
because everything in i.t it requires
coffee never chucked out coffee
so here in ubuntu we're going to launch
our terminal first like always we'll get
our repositories updated
sudo apt
update
and quick sip of coffee while it does
its thing next we'll install sql server
with one command
sudo apt install
my
sql
dash server
we'll do a tick y at the end
and that's it it'll take just a few
moments and perfect time for a coffee
break we can never have too much now at
this point you're pretty much running my
sequel let's verify it real quick though
let's make sure the service is up and
running we'll do a pseudo system ctl
status
mysql
and fingers crossed you should see
active and running that means it's
healthy good to go and just hit q to get
out of there
now go ahead and play with your database
just go crazy
you're like wait where is it
to access it all you have to do is type
in my
sql that's it
well not it you're gonna have to do sudo
my sequel
let's try it now
yeah we're there look at that we got a
nice little mysql command prompt down
here just waiting for us the cursor's
blinking ready to go now just so you
know the command my sequel without any
parameters at all worked for us because
we're connecting to our local host
it also worked because we don't have a
password set
which is fine for us as we're just
playing around but often you might see
something like this
specifying a username a remote server
you want to connect to the port and then
saying dash p for password but we don't
have to do that here so we're not going
to worry about it so here in sql let's
get the lay of the land first what's
happening right now we'll first do a
show
databases command now just know every
time you type a command in my sql you
have to end it with a semicolon
otherwise it's like what you're not done
yet come on so do that and boom
some good old default databases what do
you say we create our own let's do that
right now we'll create the database for
network chuck coffee
this one's very hard i'm just kidding
it'll be so easy simply type in create
database
the name of your database which will
name
nc
underscore copy
and then semicolon that's it
done and how hard was that right you
just created a database that's awesome
if we do show databases once more
there it is
our very own database but he's just
sitting there doing nothing he's got
nothing going on let's change that now
to play with our database to do things
with it
to use it we're going to type in the
command use and then the name of our
database nc underscore copy
semicolon and that's it database change
now we're interacting with that guy
right now now remember a database will
have a bunch of tables assuming you
created them but right now ours won't
have any and i can prove it to you let's
type in the command show
tables with the semicolon empty set
nothing there
so let's change that let's create our
first table and this is so cool this is
gonna be fun the first table we'll
create is our coffee table but um and
right now i want you to just ignore the
rows don't worry about the rows the data
all right here
all i want you to focus on are the
columns
id name region and roast we're gonna
deal with that right now so to create a
table we're going to type in create
table crazy right
and then right after that we'll name our
table of course we can name it coffee
table
don't want to miss that opportunity
and then right after that we'll do an
open parenthesis and go ahead and hit
enter it'll be fine because we didn't
put a semicolon semicolon means you're
done doing anything else means like
i'm not done yet that's that's what it
means now here inside these parentheses
we'll be defining our columns we saw
before id name blah blah you know you
got it so our first column we'll simply
call id
and then right after that i'm going to
type in int now what is that so here's
our column we're defining the name of
our column that guy right there but then
we also have to define what type of data
is going to be in that column or in the
rows that we're going to have underneath
it here we're saying we want it to be an
integer or a number that's the type of
data that will live in that column
that's pretty much all there is to it
we'll type in a comma to tell them that
hey we're not done with our columns just
yet
hit enter our next column will be name
and then we'll define what type of data
we want inside that column here i'm
going to type in
v-a-r-c-h-a-r or variable character
which is an indeterminate length string
data type
basically it's just letters
and stuff it's a string i can also
define how long i want that to be how
many characters are allowed so i'll just
say 255
and parentheses just like that and let's
keep going comma next
thing or column it was region this will
also be a string or variable character
and we'll keep going until we're done oh
we'll have one more
roast
now my last column here i'm not going to
add a comma you only had a comma when
you're saying hey i have more to say we
don't have more to say we're done i'll
hit enter i'll do a closing parenthesis
and then to end our command like we do
in all my sql stuff we're going to type
in a semicolon that's it we're about to
create our first table inside our
database ready set enter go let's take a
look at it show tables
there it is there's our coffee table now
that's just the name of it what do you
say we look inside and see the actual
columns we made we can type in describe
coffee
table and that'll give us some more info
we got our field and our type and we'll
cover more on this stuff here in a
minute oh by the way when we're defining
our table
and defining the columns and everything
the fields that's part of defining our
schema or how our databases are arranged
and
organized we're not going to go too deep
into that just know that when people say
schema that's pretty much what they mean
now there's nothing on our coffee table
let's add some stuff to it
looking at our database let's add the
default route let's insert a row into
our table in my sql we'll type in insert
and 2 and then we'll specify our table
which was coffee
table then we'll say here are the values
we'll actually use the word the command
values and we'll define our values
inside parentheses the first one's an
integer and i'm just going to put it in
as one that's the first id
second one was name which will be a
string default route then origin
ethiopia also a string
and finally roast which was light
so what's happening here we have the
insert into command so we're telling my
sequel we're inserting into the coffee
table table and it's like what are you
inserting well here are our values
bam and notice we're going in order
of our columns and we have to do that
got the id
the name the region and the roast then
once we're done what do we do
we type in semicolon to say we are done
and awesome now what i love about mysql
and most sql things is uh it'll tell us
hey the query it's okay
we got this it's good and it tells us
there was one row affected which row
well the one we just added now i know
you want to see that data inside your
database but so far i haven't shown you
how to do that because if we do
show tables
or describe
coffee table
it doesn't show us the data inside yet
so i guess i can go ahead and show you
your first select statement um
should i wait you know let's do it right
now i know you can't wait so here's how
we look inside of our table let's pull
some data out of there we'll type in
select
we'll do an asterisk and i'll explain
this here in a second and we'll say from
our table coffee
table semicolon now what's happening
here we're telling my sql i want to
select some data and it's like well what
data from what column and we're saying
all of it
i want everything that's what the
asterisk means and it's like okay fine
from what table where are you getting
this from
well we're getting it from our coffee
table i want to see my coffee stuff and
that's what we're doing here it's a very
basic select statement you'll see this
one all the time but if you want to pull
all the info from a table that's how you
do it let's take a look
there it is how cool is that so if you
just did this
clap pat yourself on the back that's a
big deal you created a database created
a table inside the database and you
added some data to it simple but killer
now here's a challenge for you what i
want you to do is fill out the rest of
this database all the rest of our copies
go and pause the video pause
on pause let's see how you did let's do
our select statement once more
select everything from
coffee table
and we should see a lot more things
yes it's so nice and neat i love it if
yours looks like this congrats that's
awesome now another challenge for you i
want you to select only the names of the
coffee from that table that's all i want
to see can you do that let's try it out
select
instead of saying everything let's just
select the name
from coffee table
bam just got the names of our coffee
that's it now here's the next challenge
for you i want you to create our next
table and do this by yourself i'm not
going to show you create our customer
table with all of our marvel customers
and also name your table avengers just
like this okay pause the video go
on pause let's see how you did now again
i wanted you to create this table and if
you haven't already go ahead and fill it
out with all this information it'll take
about two minutes but it gives you
practice but if you did it right it
should look like this let's go ahead and
select everything from that table
select
all columns from avengers
let's see how it looks
oh
nice clean tidy data i love it now here
with our marvel characters let me show
you some of the power of sql and how we
can find or query our data so let's try
this let's do a select statement just
like we did before select everything
from avengers but let's say we only want
to see the avengers that are from earth
that's all we want to see how do we do
that with where no i'm not losing my
mind watch this i can add another filter
saying where
origin equals the string
earth semicolon so let's break it down
i'm selecting all columns from the table
avengers but i only want to see
where
the column origin equals earth that's it
let's see what happens bam only got the
earthlings check it out isn't that cool
though if you had a large amount of data
being able to just select pinpoint the
data you want like that is killer and
that's just a basic sql statement let me
show you a few more quick ones let's
pull up that same statement let's say we
wanted to see all the avengers from
earth and asgard how would we do that
it's pretty simple actually all i have
to do is add one more filter to it i'll
just say or or or ajin
equals asgard
so my filter says hey origin can be
earth or
or origin can be asgard
let's see what happens bam just added
thor let's try this one maybe i want to
see all the avengers that are under the
age of 30. let's try that
in fact actually pause the video see if
you can do this pause
on pause we'll select the alias column
from avengers
where
age
is less
than 30.
we can do stuff like that bam how cool
is that i just got the aliases
spider-man and well tree and that's
pretty much an endless combination of
how you can filter things i can say
where
not
origin
equals earth i want to see everyone
that's not from earth using our not
statement so you can go crazy with
queries and often you may be typing in a
terminal doing these queries or it could
be a gui application or it's
programmatic you're programming things
in python to search for data with
queries like this it's super powerful
now so far i've shown you how to add
data to a
table but what if we want to remove
stuff because did you notice this look
at this
some dude named jeff snuck into my table
he's not an avenger how do you even get
in there so real quick go ahead and add
jeff add this data to your table and
then let's remove him so pause the video
real quick adam and then let's remove
them
we can remove the records from our
tables with the delete command we'll say
delete from then we'll specify our table
avengers and we'll tell them what we're
wanting to delete we can delete a lot of
things all at once gotta be careful but
all we care about is jeff so we'll say
where we'll use our filtering again
where we'll say first name
equals
jeff
that should do it that should take out
jeff goodbye jeff and he's gone i think
let's do our select statement once more
okay jeff is gone now we can also update
these stuff in our table for example
i was informed of this groot doesn't
have a last name it's just groot my bad
so let's change that let's delete that
we can update entries in our table with
the update command we're going to update
avengers
and we'll use the set command to set a
certain column equal to
something so we'll set last name equal
to
null
to nothing that's how we do that empty
and because we don't want to set every
last name to null we'll say where first
name
equals groot that should do it let's try
it out awesome so actually i i didn't
test this before i want to make sure it
works
excellent groot is now accurate and you
guys can stop yelling at me now last
thing on this before we get kind of
crazy let's go ahead and select all the
avengers once more all their columns but
let's say we want to see them in order
of their age youngest to oldest let's
see that we can do that by typing in
order
by the column age and we'll say because
we're going from younger to older it'll
be ascending so we'll do asc let's try
it out perfect look at that 17 18 35 42
500 that's a big jump let's do it
reverse let's do oldest to youngest
we'll change that to d s
sorry d e c descending awesome okay last
thing i'm going to show you
maybe i might get too excited to show
you something else but we'll see okay
let's try this right now our table is
looking pretty amazing all the avengers
are here well some of them but let's say
we want to know one more thing about
them i want to know if they have a beard
so it'll be beard it'll be yes or no or
actually true or false let's do that
so here in our database our table we're
going to alter the table to have another
column after it's already created let's
do it right now pretty simple actually
the command is alter we want to alter it
we got to tell sql what we want to alter
we're going to alter a table
specifically the avengers table we're
going to add a new column we'll name it
beard and then we'll tell it what type
of data is going to be now because i
want it to be true false i'm going to
type in boolean
because boolean is true or false that's
a special data type so here we're
telling sql we want to alter the table
avengers and the way we're altering it
is by adding the column beard with the
boolean
data type hit enter done now let's
select and see what it looks like right
now
look at that
new information new column now here's a
challenge for you i want you to go in
and update the record for the beard
column for each of these avengers
whether or not they have a beard you
should know that already right so go
ahead and do it real quick pause the
video
on pause here's how you would do that
like we just covered with the update
command we'll update the table avengers
we'll set beard
equal to true
where let's just say first name
equals
thor
because we know thor has a beard bam
let's see what happens perfect and for
groot he doesn't have a beard so we'll
set beard to false
where first name equals groot let's see
what happened noticing that
one is true zero is false okay we're
going to stop here i could keep going
there are things i have not covered but
i don't want to make this video too long
but i hope in this video i gave you
enough to make you like
feel semi-confident like i know what a
database is i can create one i can
select things but also i want to give
you that hunger that drive to learn just
a bit more go beyond what i'm showing
you here because there are things i
didn't cover like look here we did build
these two tables inside our database but
we never built the orders table and more
importantly we never built the
relationships between all these tables
which would involve making the id field
of both our customers our avengers and
our coffee the primary key and then when
we reference those fields in our order
table those will be foreign keys and
that unlocks the full power of
relational databases allowing us to do
things like joins and creating views
which basically is pulling data from all
these tables and only seeing what we
want to see like how many times did
spider-man order the dark roast we could
find stuff like that so i'm not going to
cover that here if you want me to create
a video on that let me know below
anyways that's all i got for today thank
you for
taking some time to have some coffee
with me and talk about sql or sql