Today I'm going to teach you how to
build a really useful daily planning
dashboard inside of Notion. This is
something that I built for myself about
a year ago. I've used it every single
day since then, and I legitimately think
it is the most useful thing I've ever
built in Notion, at least for me. So,
here's a quick look at what we're going
to build today. This is a page called my
day, and it is essentially a hyper
opinionated daily planner. It has three
sections. One is called plan. This is
sort of our traditional task manager
views. We have our due today view,
overdue views, inbox, everything else.
We have a section down here called
execute, which is the most important
section, and then a section down here
called wrap up for wrapping up your day.
And essentially, the way that you work
with this dashboard is that you work
through this three-step process. First,
in the morning, or perhaps the night
before, you plan what you're going to
work on. And you'll see there's this
little check box over here called the my
day checkbox. When we check it, we add
this task down to the execute view. So
the idea is that execute starts blank
every single day. We add tasks
deliberately to it and then instead of
looking at our bigger task management
views or perhaps looking at a due today
view where a bunch of tasks are overdue
all the time, we have this really clean,
really tight list of deliberately chosen
tasks that we think we can actually get
done today. And then at the end of the
day, we actually clear it. So down here
in wrap-up, we have a button called
clear my day. that will actually make
the execute section empty once more. And
if we need to, if we added tasks to the
system or to the daily plan that need to
have their project edited or their due
date changed, we can make those changes
from here. And you can essentially run
your life from a page like this. But
it's this execute section right here
that is the most important because when
you have clarity, when you know what to
work on next, you actually get to work
faster and you get a lot more done. So,
I'm going to show you how to build this
page. We're going to build off of my
free task management template and
basically add this in. I've made a whole
video on how to build a task manager
from scratch. So, either go through that
or grab my free task management template
in the description down below. It's
called Ultimate Tasks. It looks just
like this and we're going to be building
on top of this. I will also note before
we get started that my day is a feature
that comes inside of Ultimate Brain,
which is my whole life organization
template for Notion. If you just want
this done for you, you'll find that in
the description down below. If you want
to build it from scratch though, and uh
I would want to build it from scratch
because I'm a builder. I'm going to show
you how to do that in this video. And
we'll use my actual my day page here as
our sort of example. So the first thing
we're going to do is start from a
ultimate tasks slate and rather than a
blank slate. A lot of my YouTube
tutorials, I start from a completely
blank page. Here we want an underlying
task manager to build the my day page on
top of. And the reason for that is the
ethos behind my day. The whole idea is
that we are using our traditional task
manager, but we're taking a look at it
each day and we're creating a sort of
separate list that shows just the tasks
we're going to work on today. And I've
already made an entire video about why
this is so important and given a whole
tour of the my day sort of uh dashboard
and everything about it. But to um sort
of summarize that video really quickly,
you can kind of do this in any system.
Even if you're using a different task
manager, uh you could look at that task
manager and you could write out what
you're going to do today on a sticky
note or on a whiteboard. The most
important thing here is that you're
creating a separate list of tasks that
you're planning to work on. That list is
deliberate. It's small and that's what
you look at while you're going through
the day. So, if you don't want to use
Notion, you don't have to. I think it's
pretty useful to use notion though
because unlike in many other task
management systems in notion we don't
have to duplicate from one system to a
sticky note. We can just check a box
like that. It goes to execute and then
we can check it off in execute without
having to duplicate effort. I really
like that and it's been super duper
useful for me. So starting from a
position of ultimate tasks again you can
get a free copy of this ultimate task
manager in the description down below.
Uh, what we're going to do is build a
page called my day. So, in my little nav
section, I'm going to open this up. This
is typically where I keep all the pages
inside of the system. I'm going to go
ahead and hit the plus icon here, type
slashpage,
and create myself a page. I'll call this
my day. And we're basically going to
build this off of my page here as the
example. So, we'll give it a nice little
sun icon
like that. Let's go with blue. I'm going
to make this a full width page. So, up
to the three dot menu, I'm going to go
let's go ahead and do full width. We'll
customize the page as well. Take off the
back links. We're going to turn page
discussions and table of contents off.
We'll set inline comments to default.
This is basically my default suite of
changes that I use when I'm building a
dashboard style page, a page that's
almost like a piece of software rather
than a note or task. And that gives us
our sort of blank canvas that we're
going to work from. And in this
tutorial, we're going to do a good bit
of copying and pasting database views
instead of having to build every single
one of them from scratch. And uh if you
build notion systems in any form, I
think if you don't already know how to
do this, it's going to save you a lot of
work. So let's go back to ultimate tasks
here. Uh the plan section, like I
mentioned before, is literally just the
task manager itself. If we look at the
my day page here, again, the idea is
that we look at plan, we go through all
of our tasks, and we hit the myday
checkbox on the ones that we want to do,
that sends them down here. And it's not
that it really transports them. It just
makes sure that they fit the filter
criteria of this view here. And if you
don't know what I'm talking about, if
the word filter is confusing you, this
is going to be a tutorial that's really
centered around databases. So, you might
want to go watch my Notion databases for
beginners video as well. I'll link that
in the description in case you haven't
seen it. So, the first thing we're going
to do is make the sections for our my
day page and we're going to port the
traditional task manager that we already
have into the plan section that we
create. And since we're already on the
ultimate tasks page, here's how we can
do this. We can literally just click the
six dot menu next to the existing task
manager view we have. This is called a
linked database block. That will select
the block. I'm going to go ahead and
just click off. That keeps it selected.
If I copy it to my clipboard now, I'll
be able to paste the exact set of views.
So, let's go back into our my day page.
I'm gonna enter down. Let's do a heading
one. Call it plan. And right beneath
plan, we can command V. We do not want
to paste and sync because we are going
to make a couple of changes here. Uh, so
we'll hit dismiss. And just like that,
we have our traditional task manager on
a new page. It's just a bunch of
database views inside of a linked
database block. and we can copy and
paste them to our heart's desire. Now,
one thing that we are missing which is
crucial is the my day checkbox. So,
looking back at the actual my day page
in my brain system here, we've got this
checkbox on the right. And when we check
this box, it makes the task show up in
the execute section. We need to add this
checkbox right here. And you'll also
notice we have this little my day label.
The only reason we have that there is
because it makes it more clear that this
checkbox is something different than
this checkbox over here. I do wish
notion gave us the ability to have
checkboxes have different shapes or um
basically introduce something that would
allow us to do something like that. Uh
but in the meantime, I just sort of keep
them on opposite sides of the task to
differentiate them. So let's go ahead
and add that checkbox. To do that, we
need to go to the database itself that
holds our tasks. And a really reliable
way to get to any database is to open up
a page contained by that database, open
it as a full page, and then use the
breadcrumbs to go right back here to
tasks. Now, technically, it's contained
by something called a data source, but
I'm not going to go too much into that
difference. I've got a whole video on
data sources and databases. Pretty new
concept in Notion. I'll also link to
that below. Uh now that we're actually
at the database, we want to make sure
that it is unlocked so we can add new
properties to it and make general
changes to its structure. So up here, if
you see locked like that, you would want
to unlock it at least for yourself or
perhaps for everyone. If you're in a
solo workspace, you might not even see
this drop down. You'll just unlock it
like that. And now we can create our my
day property. I'm going to do it in this
way. You can create new properties in
tons of ways, but I'm going to
rightclick my name property and I'm
going to insert right. And then I'm
going to create a property called my
day. I'm going to give it the checkbox
type. Just like that. And then I'm going
to go ahead and edit it and give it a
nice little sun icon. In fact, that's
the most recent one right there. Uh, and
then check this out. With checkbox
properties, you can actually just drag
it down to just be that width right
there. Of course, you can also do this
any other property. If you hold option
or alt, it's kind of like a hidden
feature inside of Notion. But for
checkboxes, you don't even have to do
that. They'll just let you squeeze it
way way way down like that. So that's
really the only property we need to make
the uh sort of primary functionality of
this daily planning dashboard work. We
just need a checkbox called my day. So
I'm going to leave this unlocked for now
because we may be adding some additional
features a bit later in the tutorial.
But that is the main actual change we'll
need to make to the database. And we can
actually work our way back up to the
breadcrumbs and go back to the my day
page where we can make some changes to
our plan view. So for each of these
views, all we want to do is go into the
settings. We want to go to property
visibility and we want to find the my
day checkbox we created. We want to
unhide it and make sure it is the last
property in the list. Now we've got it
over here just like we have on my demo
copy. And then of course we have the
status property over here. So if we want
to actually finish a task, it's going to
be this one that we click. If we want to
add it to our daily plan, it's going to
be this one that we want to click. And
of course, you'd want to go ahead and do
that for all of these views, which I
will do with the power of time travel
now.
And there we go. We now have the my day
checkbox on all of these views, all the
list style views at least. That took
about 30 seconds. And we are basically
done with the plan view. So next, let's
go ahead and create another heading one
block. If you just type the pound symbol
and space, you get one like that. We'll
call it execute. And this is going to be
the most important part of our system.
Now, if we look at my version here, you
can see that we've got something that
looks pretty similar to the plan
section, at least in terms of its
layout. We have a list style uh database
view here or list style layout. And we
are grouping it by status. We are
showing pretty much a lot of the same
properties. Got a project here. We have
our status here, my day checkbox over
here. There's a couple of other ones,
these uh context tags that I'm going to
show a little bit later, but on the
whole, it looks pretty similar. So that
means we can again save effort by
copying and pasting. Instead of building
out a full database view, let's just
copy and paste this one more time. So
copy to my clipboard after I've clicked
that little six dot menu and clicked
away. We'll go beneath execute. Paste it
again. And instead of keeping all these
views, we're just going to keep the
first one. So I'm just going to delete
everything except for the today view. So
now let's go ahead and rename this view.
So I'm just going to click it, hit
rename, call it my day. We'll give it a
nice little sun icon. I think that's the
perfect icon for this. And then the most
important thing we need to do to this
view is change its filter criteria.
Right now it's filtered to show us uh
tasks that are not done and tasks that
are due today. It's our due today view.
But instead of that, what we want the
filters to do is only show us tasks
where the my day checkbox is checked.
And if we look at the filters for the
existing template, that is all we have
sitting there. We even show the done
tasks because with our sort of daily
list, we'd actually like to see the ones
that are done. So, going in here, we're
just going to edit those filters. We'll
go ahead and get rid of this status
filter. We'll get rid of this do filter.
And we're going to add one where my day
is checked.
And then along with that, we're going to
get rid of the sorts as well. And the
reason I like to get rid of the sorting
criteria is I like to be able to drag
the tasks around in my daily plan to
create an order for how I'm going to
tackle them. So if I said I'm going to
do all four of these tasks because they
are all due today. I could go ahead and
drag them around. Let's say I'll put the
trash bin out first. Really easy morning
task. Let's uh send the Black Friday
email. Get that done really really
quickly. Then we'll go into emails and
chats and oh actually I think we should
update the website with Black Friday
pricing first. So that actually goes up
there. You see this is just a really
really quick way to establish an order
of operations for the day and then you
can really easily go into it. So with
that we have established basically
everything you really need in the
execute view. A little later in this
video I want to show you how to add one
of the advanced features that I've built
into my own system. These context tags.
I also have a time tracking system
that's built in here but I think that
would add about 45 minutes to an hour of
uh extra tutorial to this video. So, I'm
going to split the time tracking portion
of this into its own video. It's easily
the most complex part of uh this whole
system here, and I also think it's less
useful than the basic part that I just
showed you. So, we're going to do that
in a separate video. Uh, but we will
actually bring in these tags in a bit.
For now, though, what I want to do is
finish up the basic part of this
dashboard by helping you build the
wrap-up section down here. And the
wrap-up section, which I kind of brushed
over in the intro, has two main
components to it. First, it has this
button. And the button is the most
important part because the button when
you click it will clear this entire my
day area up here. If we click clear my
day, now this is blank. One more time.
All the buttons really doing is
unchecking the my day checkbox for any
row where it is currently checked. But
conceptually, it's doing something
incredibly important. It is making sure
that at the end of the day, this becomes
empty again. And this needs to be empty
again because when you start your daily
planning session, whether it's the night
before or right before you start working
uh the day of, you want this to be
blank. So that way you are sure that
everything you add to it is deliberately
added in the moment. If you don't do
that, you kind of run into the same
problem a lot of people have with
traditional task managers where they
have this due today view here, but it
just sort of fills up with all these
overdue tasks overdue in quotes that
never actually had to be done. Like
there was no real consequence for not
getting it done. And they're all just
sort of screaming out like they're
urgent even though they're not. And if
you don't clear your execute view, you
basically just have gone through all
this effort to keep the same problem in
your life. The whole point is to have a
blank space. Blank space, baby. Uh to
start your daily planning every single
day. So we're going to start naturally
by creating that button and then I will
explain these views down here. So down
here, let's go ahead and make one more
heading one. We're going to call this uh
wrap-up. And then beneath beneath
wrap-up, we're going to create a button.
And we're going to call this button
clear. my day. I think the perfect icon
for this would be a sunset icon. So,
let's find sunset.
Is there a sunset icon? Maybe it's sun
down. Sun arrow down. Wow. I can't
believe sunset is not an alias for sun
arrow down. Okay, so we'll have sun
arrow down here. When the button is
clicked, we're going to find the edit
pages in action. Uh we're going to find
our tasks data source. Hopefully, it's
this one. I have a lot of tasks data
sources in this notion workspace because
I make a lot of tutorials. Uh and then
instead of editing all tasks, let's say
tasks where my day is checked.
That'll be the filter for this action.
We're going to edit once again the my
day property. And we are going to set it
to unchecked. Just like that. So we have
all these tasks in execute. If we hit
clear my day, boom, they're all gone.
Now, if you want to add a little bit of
a confirmation check, you might want to
come in here and add another action,
which is show confirmation and bring
that to the top. Are you sure you want
to continue? I don't know why it closed
on me. There we go. Are you sure you
want to continue? Continue or cancel.
Uh, and if you hit continue, it'll
actually do this. If you hit cancel, it
won't. So, that's how that looks. But
now you're kind of done with the broad
strokes. You've got your plan views
here. You've got your execute view here.
And then you have this wrap-up section
which will clear it. Now in talking with
some of the people in our customer
community when they tested the the my
day feature after I created it in
Ultimate Brain, some of them said, "Hey,
I love the idea of clearing my day every
single day, but I have meticulously
picked all the tasks that needed to go
into the daily plan and the ones that
aren't done, I want to make sure that I
can easily find them again. But some of
them are in projects, some of them
didn't have due dates, so it's not super
easy to find them from the plan view
again. Uh I wish there was a way to just
sort of like restore my daily plan. And
so basically that is what this set of
views is for. The set of database views
that have table layout beneath that
clear my day button right there. So let
me quickly explain what these views are
and then we can build them together. Uh
first this clear my day is basically a
table style view of the execute views up
here. And I need to add a task back to
the execute view. Let's just add all
these to be honest. Uh so you can see
how it works here. This is really
simple. It's list style. It's entirely
based on the idea that you just want to
check things off. But down here we have
a table style view and that allows you
to more easily edit the property values
of these uh entries on a computer. So
the reason this is here is let's say
that something urgent came up uh after
you've already planned your day. Let's
say that uh you're a developer and
somebody adds a really urgent GitHub
issue that you need to get fixed today
or you at least think is pretty urgent.
Uh so you add it to your daily plan.
Let's just say fix the GitHub issue. And
I've added it to my plan really really
quickly. So it doesn't have a project.
Uh it doesn't have a due date. It
doesn't have anything. And I'm hoping
that I get it done today. But for
whatever reason I don't. Okay. So I need
to clear my execute view. That's the
rule. But down here, I want to make sure
that I add any needed information to
this task that I just brain dumped into
my daily plan before I clear my day.
Otherwise, this just gets lost in the
inbox somewhere, right? So, let's just
go ahead and say, uh, well, I didn't get
it done today. I got it done. I'll do it
tomorrow. Um, and it is a work ongoing
task. Let's just make sure that I put it
in one of these projects. Or maybe it
has to do with a specific uh project
that I'm working on like notion helper
upgrades. So, I'll put it right there.
And now I've added these useful
properties that allow me to find it
later on if I don't happen to get to it.
And I can very easily clear my day once
again. So that's kind of the point of
clear my day. Once I hit clear my day,
this is going to be empty like you'd
expect. Uh and now we have a couple of
additional views that help us to sort of
prime our brains for how we're going to
plan our day tomorrow or maybe even get
the jump on daily planning. There's one
called review calendar. This is just
going to show any tasks that have hard
deadlines. So I can sort of prime my
brain on what needs to get done
tomorrow. And then finally we have the
view that I built to sort of assuage
some of those anxieties people had
around clearing the my day list. Uh and
that is a very very very simple database
view that shows our tasks sorted by the
last edited time in descending order.
The reason that is so useful is that
when we click clear my day, it's going
to uncheck the my day checkbox on any uh
task where it was checked. that counts
as an edit. So the edited time stamp
gets updated and that means everything
that I was working on is going to be
right here at the top. So if I want to
get a jump on planning my next day, now
that I've done the required thing of
clearing out this list, I can go ahead
and add stuff back to it. So yeah, I
didn't get any of these done. Let's just
go ahead and populate the list again. It
looks the same as before, but there was
a crucial step that happened. you
actually took the time to clear it off
and then deliberately say, "Yes, this is
what I'm working on tomorrow." I think
that's the most important part. So, we
can go ahead and build that out. Now, we
don't have a whole lot of table style
views inside of Ultimate Tasks, but I do
believe we can probably just take this
view once again, copy it, and we can
change the layout type. I like doing
this where I can um instead of building
database views from scratch. So, I'm
going to go ahead and add a few more
tasks back to the execute view. That way
we can see them here as well. And to
make it look like mine, all we need to
do is come into the settings. We can go
to layout and we can set it to table
like that. That's going to give it a
table layout. I typically like to wrap
all content in my table views so I don't
have truncations going on. I do not want
to show the data source title. I'm going
to show vertical lines and I'm not going
to show the page icon. Typically not
useful to show the icon for task type
data sources. So going back to my actual
version here, let's go ahead and look at
the other settings for this first clear
my day view. We have two sorts do in
ascending order with this subtask sorter
in ascending order. Uh I don't know if
we're going to mess with the subtask
sorter in the free ultimate tasks
template. So I'll just go ahead and
create a sort where do is in ascending
order like that. And then if we take a
look at the filters, we have only one
rule which is where my day is checked.
And that is exactly what we had already
since we copied and pasted our view. So
I'll just rename this to clear my day.
I'm going to go into the group settings
and I'm going to group this by the
status property.
And typically I don't use doing uh but I
don't want to hide the empty groups
either. I think it would be nice to see
finished tasks. So I'm going to uncheck
hide empty groups. And then optionally,
if you don't use the doing status, I
usually just check a task between todo
and done, you could hide that one
manually. So you're going to get
something that looks like this. Anything
that got finished, like say send me that
email is down here. Anything that is not
finished is going to show right here.
And like I said earlier, you can use
this view to quickly add projects or
change due dates or add any additional
details before you once again clear my
day like that. So, next, let's go ahead
and create another view. Again, I like
to duplicate that. Just make sure I
already have my data source selected.
We're going to call this one uh I
believe it was like calendar or review
calendar. Yep. So, we'll call this one
review calendar. I'm going to give it a
nice calendar icon.
And the layout is going to be a calendar
just like that. Let's look at our
reference to see what the calendar is
actually set up to do. We have a couple
of rules. Status is not done and my day
is unchecked. And then uh we are sorting
by a subtask sorter property. I need to
check to see if we actually have that in
the free version of the template, but we
can definitely set up those filters real
quick. So my day is unchecked was one of
them. And then status
is not complete. So this will show us
all of our upcoming required tasks that
we need to do.
And looks like we've got a few right
there. We may even want to show some of
their properties. So, under property
visibility, maybe you want to show
status like that.
And that pretty much gives you that view
right there. Okay. To finish this up,
looking back at my my day dashboard
here, we've got one additional view
called plan tomorrow. This is again a
table style view. So, of course, we can
copy and duplicate instead of building
it from scratch. Uh, this one is going
to show anything where the status is not
done and it's going to uh sort it by the
last edited date. Again, the point of
this view is to have all the tasks that
were most recently edited, which are
usually going to be the ones where we've
cleared them off of my day, percolate to
the top. That way, we have a centralized
place to find them, and we can rebuild
our list if we want to. So, let's just
go ahead and duplicate clear my day.
We'll call this one uh plan tomorrow.
Find a sun up emoji or icon for that
one. And uh while I'm thinking about it,
I'm going to go back to clear my day and
I'm going to give this one a sun down
icon instead of the regular sun emoji.
Uh I don't know why I keep saying emoji
icon. Okay. So for plan tomorrow, my
short-term memory is not great. Status
is not done and edited in descending
order. So we'll go ahead and change this
from my day is checked to status is not
complete. Like that. And then we'll
change our sort from due in ascending
order to I think it's called edited.
Yep. This is just a last edited time
property you can add by default to any
database. And we'll set that to
descending order.
Now we have all of the required views in
our wrap-up section and we've pretty
much finished the broad strokes of the
my day page. So this is how you can add
a super duper useful daily planner
directly to any task manager inside of
notion. All you really need to do is add
this my day checkbox to your tasks
database and then you can create this
set of views that again gives you this
most important execute view right here
that shows you exactly what you've
planned to do and nothing else. Now, if
you want to add something extra to this
system, I now want to show you how to
add context tags. And I already covered
basically the why for these tags in this
whole tagging system in my video that
explains everything about this system
without it being a build tutorial. Uh,
but to do a really quick overview before
we build it, there is this location tag
here, this PI tag here, which I'll
explain in a second, and this energy
tag. And basically, for the tasks that
you add to your execute section, you can
use these properties to help yourself
batch uh similar tasks together and help
yourself order tasks more intelligently.
For example, if we open up this send
initial sales email task right here, and
we open up the little view details side
pane here, we've got all these
properties in this prioritization side
panel section. This one is called
energy. So, you could batch tasks by
high energy or low energy. Maybe you
want to do a whole bunch of low energy
tasks and then go into a high mental
energy task or vice versa. You can batch
tasks by the location. For example,
maybe you've got like three errands.
Well, if you know their errands, go
ahead and get them all done while you're
out doing errands. And then there is
this pi property which I think is
actually the most important one. Like I
said in that earlier video that I made
that's sort of a companion to this one.
I explained the full thing. But the 30
secondond version of it is immersive
tasks are tasks that you have to focus
completely on the entire time you're
doing them. Whereas process tasks are
tasks that you kind of just have to get
the ball rolling on and then they kind
of take care of themselves. So a process
task might be say putting a pan on the
oven to get it heating up or giving
details to someone who works for you so
they can go off and do a task and not be
blocked anymore. And using these tags,
you can more efficiently order the tasks
in your daily plan. And I personally
think that the PI tag is actually the
most important one because if you can
get good at getting your process tasks
in play and then switch over to your
immersive tasks, you get more done for
literally the same amount of effort. And
if you switch those around, well, you've
got a whole bunch of blocked tasks that
are then waiting for you to finish these
longer, more immersive tasks. So, if we
want to add this into our system, and
like I said earlier, we're not going to
do time tracking in this video. That'll
be an upcoming video. But if we want to
add this into our system, we first need
to add those three select properties:
energy, location, and PI. So, to do
that, once again, we are going to
navigate back to our source tasks
database. So, I'm going to open up any
one of these tasks. I'm going to full
screen it just like that. And I'm going
to go one uh level up the beantock, up
the breadcrumbs to tasks right here.
Again, we're already unlocked, but you
would want to make sure to unlock if you
were locked. And then we're going to add
three more properties. So, I'll just
shift scroll over to the end here. We're
going to add a select property called
energy.
We'll add another one called location.
And we'll add one called P / I. I just
don't really have a better name for
process/emersive.
If you've got a better suggestion, let
me know in the comments. Select property
for that one as well. Let's go ahead and
set their icons. Energy. Maybe there's a
battery. I think I think we use this one
right here actually. Uh for location, I
think there's like a city icon.
And then for PI, this entire idea comes
from the world of professional cooking,
uh the misison plus concept. There's a
whole book called Work Clean that
details it. So, we're going to go with a
frying pan and an egg for that one. Uh,
let's go ahead and fill out our sort of
default options. So, we're going to go
with high and low for energy.
For location, we can add errand. We
could add home.
Could add office, maybe underground
volcano layer if you have one of those.
And then for PI, we're only going to
have process and immersive.
Now that we have those, we might want to
make them look pretty inside of our task
pages. So, if we open up any one of our
task pages once again, full screen it,
we can go to customize layout. And by
default, we're probably going to find
those uh if we click the property group,
we're going to probably going to find
them at the bottom here. So, we want to
go ahead and move them to a new section.
I think I'm actually going to create a
new section. So, we'll go add section up
here in the layout builder. Call this
prioritization.
maybe one of the most important sections
that you can add to a task manager
because if you can't set priorities, you
can't really get much done. Uh, and
we're just going to drag them up.
Energy, add pi, we'll add location, and
while we're here, uh, my day, I think,
should actually go in our pinned
properties. So, I'm going to click
heading here. Let me zoom out a couple
of ticks just to make it look more like
how you'd probably see it. Um, that's
better. We're gonna find my day.
There it is. And I actually want to pin
it.
And the reason that I want to pin it,
I'll hit apply to all pages here. The
reason I want to pin it is that now when
I open any task as a full page or inside
peak, I'm going to see my day right
there. So even if I'm not in my actual
my day worksheet, I'm just looking at my
tasks from any of the other views, I can
very easily open the task and boom, add
it to my day. Just like that. So, now
that we've got our properties created,
let's actually head back to our My Day
worksheet.
And inside of the My Day view that we
created, we can go into our property
visibility and we can add those new
properties. Energy, we'll add location.
We'll add PI. And I think I want to put
those
right around here. We'll put them before
due. And this makes sure that I think
most importantly my day is over here. I
think I'll also put meta labels down
there as well. So now if we want to add
those tags, we can just hit edit and we
can add them very easily like this or we
can create specific views. So we can
drag them around and that's typically
how I like to use them. So instead of
hitting uh edit and adding there and
then hitting edit, adding them there,
very very slow process. We actually just
have an energy view here. It's just a
grouped list view and we can drag them
like so. Super duper easy. So, let's go
ahead and create that real quick. Once
again, we can just duplicate one of
these views. So, we'll just duplicate
the my day view there. We'll call it
energy.
We'll go with the little battery icon
that we were using before. And the cool
thing is the filters are the same
because we still want to only see tasks
where my day is checked. So, we don't
even have to change the filters. We
don't want sorts because this is a drag
and drop view. All we need to do is go
into our settings, go to group, find
energy, group by energy. And I don't
want to hide empty groups. The entire
point is to drag from the no energy
group into one of these empty groups. So
that's basically all we need. And now we
can be like update website. I think it's
a high energy task. Boom. There we go.
For the other two views, just duplicate
and tweak. Instead of energy, we'll call
this one location. Find our little
building icon. Change our grouping
criteria from energy to location.
Once again, uncheck hide empty groups.
Good to go. Finally, duplicate pi.
Find our little frying pan and egg.
Change the grouping one more time.
And uncheck hide empty groups. I think
I'll put process at the top because it's
generally good to do your process tasks
first. Again, the entire idea is to get
those process tasks uh rolling while you
then switch over to immersive tasks and
they're kind of doing their thing. So, I
think process really really makes sense
uh to be at the top there. And then, of
course, you can drag things around as
needed like that. And actually, this is
more of an immersive task. And once
you're done just sort of dragging things
around in these three views, you're
going to have your tags set in your
actual my day view. To wrap this up, I
always think it's a good idea to
navigate back to your database. Again,
going to the breadcrumbs and lock it one
more time. When you're not making
changes to the structure of your
database, adding or changing properties,
it's a really, really good idea to keep
those databases locked, especially if
you're working with other people. But
even if you're in a solo workspace, it's
usually just good practice. And that, my
friends, is how you create your own
version of the my day worksheet that
comes inside of Ultimate Brain and that
I use every single day. Seriously, this
is in my opinion the most important part
of the template. It is the page that I
generally run my life from. I also do a
lot of note-taking and I'll use the
general task manager views. But in terms
of getting things done, this is easily
the most important part of the template.
And that's why even though I include it
in the template that I sell, I wanted to
show you how to build it from scratch in
case you don't want to pay for a
template and you want to build things
from scratch. Now, if you like having
things done for you, if you would rather
just have the shortcut, we have included
this directly inside of our Ultimate
Brain template that looks more or less
like this. Ultimate Brain is an
all-in-one system for organizing your
entire life inside of Notion. And you
can run your life from just a couple of
pages. You've got the homepage here, and
I'm just showing you mine instead of
doing slick B-roll. Um, we got the
homepage here. You've got your task
manager views. There is the most
advanced recurring task system you are
ever going to find inside of Notion
built into this. We even include
automations that work on Notion's free
plan, which you can't build yourself
unless you upgrade to their paid plan,
but they do work in the template, which
is pretty sweet on the free plan. Uh, we
have a note-taking system with free
automations that come with the template
for taking voice notes. Uh, we have a
super advanced web clipper called Fly
Lighter for really easily clipping stuff
from the web that works super well with
this. There's a project management
section. There is a tagging system that
uses Thiagofore's paramethod projects,
areas, resources, and an archive for
organizing everything that comes into
your life. So, this is sort of the
command center. This is where you can do
everything for managing your life at a
high level. And then you have the my day
page, of course, for getting things done
at a lower level. And there's a whole
bunch of other bells and whistles if
you're interested in that kind of stuff.
A recipe tracker, a book tracker, a CRM
for managing your contacts, and a lot
more. You can check out all the details
over at thomasjfrank.com/brain.
And if you do want all this done for you
along with the template, you also get
world-class tutorials. We have both
video tutorials and written guides. We
also give you access to a customer
support community. So, if you have
questions, you can ask those questions
and you'll get them answered by Notion
experts. Once again,
thomasjfrank.com/brain.
If you want to build the task manager
from scratch that we based this entire
build off of, then you can check out
this video right here. This will show
you how to build ultimate tasks
completely from scratch. So, if you want
a really, really great video for
learning the ins and outs of Notion, I
highly recommend that one right there.
Otherwise, check out this video right
here if you want more clarity on the why
behind my day and how it works.