notion just released a game-changing new
feature called buttons for the first
time we can now create honest to
goodness multi-step automations directly
inside of notion so you can do things
like clicking a button to track your
habits which will automatically change
properties inside of a habits database
or you can create a brand new project
and click a button to create default
tasks for that project which have their
statuses and their assignees already set
or you can create a centralized place
for spawning new tasks or notes or even
projects inside of your second brain
this feature just started rolling out
today I am super excited about it and in
this video I'm going to teach you
everything you need to know to master it
timestamps as always are right there so
you can skip around the video to your
heart's content but we're going to start
things out by going a little bit more in
depth on the examples I just showed you
here in the intro and then I'm going to
jump in and teach you how to actually
start creating your own buttons let's
get started so here I am in a very basic
habit tracker that I've built which I
showed off in the intro here and I just
want to use this to show you just how
much buttons can do inside of your
notion work space so if I click this new
day button right here and I will
position the screen so you can see this
records database down here I'm going to
get a brand new record in this database
with its date set and with a title
referencing the day as well but even
cooler when I click these buttons you're
going to see that the checkbox
properties down here actually get
checked off and then this day score
formula property starts to fill up with
the score for the day so what exactly is
going on here well if we click the
little gear icon next to this button we
can see that we've actually got a lot of
configuration options for what we can do
when the button is clicked in this case
we are adding a brand new page to a
specific database called habits we're
giving it a name and we are referencing
today with the at today command here and
then we're also setting its date to
today which is a dynamic value so when I
click this button I get a brand new row
in this database with those properties
set likewise with these buttons here
opening this one up here I am am editing
a page in habits and I can actually set
filters just like I would when I'm
creating a database view to choose which
page I'm going to edit and then I'm
simply changing the value of this drink
water checkbox property so when I click
it any row that matches the filters
inside of the button is going to have
its property updated pretty cool but
even cooler is that buttons now will
allow us to actually create default
tasks inside of new projects that we
create inside a notion and this is
something that people have been
requesting for a very long time myself
included I even made a video about it in
the past but at this point that video is
now obsolete because buttons give us a
much better way to do it so to show you
that I've created this demo content
planning Hub that has modeled sort of
after my creators companion template
it's a bit simpler for video purposes
here and I'm going to go into a YouTube
video and I've actually set up a brand
new YouTube video template that has one
of these buttons inside of it so by
default we don't have any tasks that are
associated with this project and in the
past we've had to do some really hacky
things to get default tasks into a
project like dragging checkbox items up
into the database here but we don't have
to do anymore because I now have this
add default video tasks button and when
I click it I'm going to get a
confirmation window right here I will
hit confirm and boom I have all of these
default tasks if I click into any of
them we're going to see that they are
actually brand new rows in the tasks
database and they're related to this
exact YouTube video they also have an
assignee automatically set and they have
their status automatically set to get a
little bit fancier and I might show this
to you at the end of the video I also
have a suggested due date which is
actually dynamically determined from the
publish date of the video itself which
is really really cool so I'll show you
that near the end of the video because
that gets into some formula stuff and
it's a bit more advanced for now I want
to show you one other really cool trick
so here I have the dashboard page for my
ultimate brain template which you can
find over at
thomasjfrank.combrain Link in the
description down below and this is sort
of a hub for the entire template we have
all of our task manager views we have
all of our notes views but still if I
want to create something I have to go
into a specific toggle or a specific
page like the task manager page or the
notes page or the projects page except
now I don't have to because I have
buttons so here I've created this little
toggle called create and inside of it I
have all these different buttons that
are going to create new things for me
these will create new tasks these will
create new notes new projects new areas
of resources and this gives me a
centralized place that I could sync to
any part of my workspace so I could see
it basically anywhere I want where I can
create something new so if I'm on the go
I would want to have this in my quick
capture page I can pull it up on my
phone I can hit a button and I can say
create a brand new task so let's create
a task that is due today I click that it
automatically opens the task I have a
title here
and I can already see that it's due
today and the priority is set as well if
I want to create a brand new project I
can do that as well I've got a brand new
project I've got a status set and we can
do that for basically any database that
we're working with inside of notion and
again the configuration is really not
that complicated it looks pretty similar
to what I showed you already we have add
a new page to a specific database all
notes bub in this case and then I'm
opening that newly created page in this
case in the site Peak View so even at
launch here buttons already have a ton
of use cases a ton of flexibility and I
want to now start teaching you how to
actually create your own buttons we're
going to start very very simple and then
we're going to go into some more
advanced use cases I'm actually going to
show you how to build each of the
examples I just showed you and demoed
here but first we're going to start very
very simple so I'm on a brand new page
I'm calling this daily tasks and I want
to create a button that just gives me a
checklist of items that I want to do
every single day maybe some habits or
like my daily chores so to do that I'm
going to hit the slash button here I'm
going to type button and there it is run
on custom automations with a click so
once I click that I'm going to get this
new interface where first I can name the
button and I can give it an emoji or an
icon and I can also choose one of five
main actions so I can insert blocks into
the current page which is very simple to
the predecessor of this feature the
template button if you've seen that
before but I can also add new pages to
databases I can edit existing pages and
databases I can show a confirmation
which will ensure that I actually want
to click the button and do what it's
going to do and then I can actually open
a new page either the page I just
created if I use this ad page action
here or I can open any other page in my
workspace so there's a lot you can do
with these I'm going to choose insert
blocks as my first action here and I'm
just going to call this uh daily chores
So within this area it's just another
notion window remember with notion it is
literally blocks all the way down that
is what makes up the entire notion
universe so in here I can do anything up
to and including adding additional
buttons and getting really crazy and
we're not going to do that I just wanted
to show you that you can actually do it
so I'll go ahead and get rid of that
button if I can here and instead I'm
going to just create a simple list of to
Do's so back bracket forward bracket
space is going to give me a to do and
I'm going to type out some chores here
okay so now I have four chores that I
want to do every single day I will go
ahead and hit done here and now when I
click this daily chores button boom so
now we have four brand new to do blocks
on our page I could check these off as
needed I can delete them at the end of
the day I can create new ones tomorrow
but where buttons really get powerful is
when we start messing with databases and
also when we create multi-step
automations so to show you how to do
that I'm going to navigate over to my
content planning Hub little demo here
and we are going to build what I showed
you here this little default video tasks
button where when I create a new project
I can actually spawn a whole list of
default tasks that are going to be
associated with that project and this is
very useful because if you work in a
company or if you go through lots of
repeated processes you'll have projects
in your work that often have the same
exact tasks every single time great
example here is a YouTube video every
single time we make a video we need to
research and write the video we need to
set a video title we need to film it
edit it all that good stuff and we want
to have those in our task database and
we want to have each of those tasks
associated with the video that we are
creating so let's go ahead and actually
build that and the way that I'm going to
do that is I'm just going to create a
brand new YouTube video so let me give
that a title here
I'm going to spawn this from the YouTube
video template that I've set up here and
I've got a whole database tutorial that
teaches you how to make database
templates if you're curious about that
link is in the description below but
what I'm going to do here is actually
get rid of this button or at least move
it to the bottom because we're going to
recreate it so just as a brief overview
what we want to do we want to when we
come in this project hit a button create
brand new default tasks in this tasks
window here and have them be associated
with the video that we've just created
now if we look at the filters on this
tasks table here we can see that we are
only going to see tasks where the
content relation contains this video so
we don't have to do anything with the
filters or with this view in particular
we just need to create brand new tasks
in our tasks database that are
associated with this video so here's how
we can do that with a button first I
will hit button one more time create
that button window here let's name it
add or create how about create default
video tasks I'm going to give it a nice
little icon I think there's a video one
yeah there we go that seems YouTubey and
I can also little bonus tip here I can
change the color of the icon I think red
is going to be more YouTubey so I'll go
with that and now I can start adding
steps so let's think through exactly
what we want to do here we want to get a
list of default tasks in this tasks
table which is itself just a linked
database that is pulling from our Master
tasks database which means every task we
create is going to be an individual Row
in that database so we're going to have
a step for every single task we want to
create and to keep things short I'm just
going to do three tasks in this one even
though we had like seven or eight
earlier so first I will add a step here
and I think before we start adding new
pages to our databases all willy-nilly I
do want to add a show confirmation step
just to make sure that we actually want
to do what we're trying to do here
because it's very easy to accidentally
click one of these buttons If you're not
paying attention so I'll just leave this
as default and it's going to show that
little total and I'm going to have to
click continue before the rest of the
automation is going to kick off second
let's choose add page two and this is
going to let us add a page to a specific
database so I'm going to select my
database here we are going to choose
tasks 2 which is my database here and
then we can set all of our properties as
if we were creating a brand new page in
that database normally so let's say film
or script video will be the first one
that we do I'm going to add another
property here I'm going to choose the
assignee and I'm going to set that as uh
how about person who clicked the button
this is an example of one of the dynamic
variables that has come out with the
buttons featured today whoever clicks
this button if we choose the from this
automation person who clicked this
button feature they're going to be the
assignee for that task on this row that
gets created so I'll go ahead and click
that here it's going to assign it to me
because I'm going to be the person
clicking the button here in the video
and I'm going to add another property
here let's go with status I want to make
sure the status is not started and
that's going to be a default for the
status property but we're just going to
add here for demonstration purposes and
then the most important one the content
relation so we're going to select this
page and this is an example of another
Dynamic variable and possibly one of the
most useful ones that came out with this
feature I can choose this page it's
going to pull this context that we're on
the page that we're on and use that as
the actual relation value so I will set
that there and we have other things here
I'll show you offset near the end of the
video that's actually going to help us
create some Dynamic dates that are
pulled from the actual publish date of
the video but that's a bit more advanced
so stick around to the end if you want
to see that I'm going to skip it for now
so we've created that there and because
we're creating default tasks and all
these settings are going to be pretty
similar to one another I'm just going to
go ahead and click this three dot here
and duplicate below and then just make
this film video now for film video I
know that I am the person who has to
film it I'm the guy on camera so instead
of person who clicked the button I'm
going to go ahead and change that to
thomasfrank and the rest of these things
can actually stay the same we want the
content to still pull from this page
status will be not started good to go
one more duplication we're going to say
edit video and that one I'm going to
assign to my editor Tony so instead of
me being the assignee let's go ahead and
find Tony Santos there we go and we're
all good there so we could add
additional steps here we could say open
the page or open a specific page but
we're kind of on the page we want to be
on so we're pretty much done creating
this button I'm going to hit done now
and then to demonstrate this once more I
will click create default video tasks I
will continue
and there we have our three default
tasks edit film and script with their
assignees with their statuses and that
takes a whole lot of work out of the
process of creating default tasks inside
of projects okay let's go to our third
example here I'm going to go to my copy
of ultimate brain and we are going to
recreate just a couple of the buttons
from this little create area and as a
reminder these are buttons that give us
a single centralized place where we can
create brand new tasks new notes new
projects and new areas or resources
inside of the second brain if you're I'm
not familiar with the areas and
resources concept I will link to my
whole second brain tutorial and overview
video in the description check that out
if you're curious but let's just go
ahead and recreate a mini version of
this again keeping things short and
sweet I'm going to call this once again
create so let's open up my little Emoji
picker and I'm going to find that brush
Emoji actually it isn't on brush maybe
it's under paint it is indeed so I will
find my little paint Emoji I guess it's
even different uh than that oh there it
is and we will bold and hit create and
let's just say create two just so we can
visually differentiate I'm going to open
this up and I'm going to make myself uh
two columns so slash 2C is going to give
me two columns I'm going to do slash
three for heading three and call that
one tasks and then I'm going to call
this one notes so once again slash three
notes and then I can use three dashes to
get that nice little horizontal rule
which is just nice for Aesthetics and
Visually dividing your workspace up so
let's go ahead and create another button
slash button
and uh we're going to actually add a
page to once again for this one let's
call it new task due today so I'll show
you how to actually set a dynamic due
date
and let's go with a hammer that seems
tasky so we're going to add a page to a
selected database and it's going to be a
database called all tasks and I know I
gave this one the bub prefix or suffix
in particular there it is
so I'll select that uh the task I'm
going to leave Untitled and I will show
you how to actually open this page
automatically so you can then name it
instead of giving it a name that's
always going to be the same so we'll
leave it Untitled here but we are going
to add some additional properties that
we want to actually set a default values
for So within ultimate brain I know that
priorities are always supposed to be
medium by default I'm going to set that
I know that kanban status is always
supposed to be to do by default so I'll
always set that and because this task is
supposed to be due today we can actually
use one of those Dynamic values so I'm
going to choose my do property here I
will go to select and you can see that
from this automation inside this menu
here I have two Dynamic values I have
now and I have today so today is just
going to be today's date now is going to
be pretty much the same thing but also
with the exact time as well and I'm
hoping that in the future we get
additional Dynamic options like one week
from now or X days from now or something
like that but at least for today here at
launch we have these two so I'm going to
pick today and that's going to be pre
pretty much good for this button so I'll
click done here and oh actually I want
to open it back up and I want to add one
more step which is going to be open page
so I've got two options here I can
select the page and I can also select
the style in which I'm going to open it
my favorite way to open pages is side
Peak normally at least so I'm going to
choose that and then for select page
note that we can choose any existing
page inside of our workspace we can
search just like we would when we're
linking to pages but I'm going to choose
new page added because I want to open up
the brand new task I've created so I can
give it a name I'll hit done and then if
I create my brand new task boom there it
is we're walking the dog once again and
we can see that it is due today so let's
finish up this example by now creating a
notes example and I will do slash button
one more time I'm going to find oh maybe
like a pencil icon that seems very note
like and I'm going to say a new inbox
note
and actually instead of inbox note I'm
going to choose new fleeting note
I'll show you a cool little feature from
Ultimate brain so I'm going to go add
step just like before we're going to add
page two we are going to select the
database and that is going to be uh all
notes bub
Ley we actually find to the top my
screen is not playing nice with me there
it is cool once again we're gonna leave
the title blank so we can set it when
the new page is created but we do want
to add one additional property and that
is actually going to be the type
property which we will set to this
little fleeting tag here and this is
going to ensure that when we create this
brand new page it becomes a fleeting
note which will make sure that it's
archived later on when we don't need it
anymore finally We'll add one more step
we are going to open the page that we
just created so again we'll do new page
added from this automation I'm going to
set this to side Peak because again that
is my favorite and I will hit done and
create myself a brand new fleeting note
and let's just call this uh how about
Christmas gifts this is a type of note
that is only going to be relevant for a
temporary period of time it's not going
to be always nice to have in your inbox
or in your areas things like that so I
want it to be fleeting and because we
set the type is fleeting in our button
there it is it is fleeting and just to
show you kind of how ultimate brain
works I can come down to this fleeting
notes toggle here and now I see
Christmas gifts here but after 30 days
it's going to automatically archive
itself that's kind of the point of a
fleeting note as opposed to what I'd
call a permanent note that you'd want to
actually put into a resource or an area
or maybe in your favorites list like
that okay so far we have added new pages
to a database we have shown
confirmations we have gone to new pages
the one thing I haven't showed you yet
is how to edit existing pages that are
already in a database and that is
exactly what we are doing with these
buttons here in the habit tracker so I'm
going to recreate one of these for you
and I'll show you how it actually
affects a new page inside of a database
so the first thing I'm going to do is go
ahead and delete this record because we
already have all these values checked so
I'm going to delete that and then we're
going to walk through one more time all
the configurations in this new day
button which is actually just one step
we have ADD page to our habits database
we're calling it at today we are setting
its date at today that's one of those
two Dynamic date values we have
available to us right now so when I
click this I'm going to get a brand new
record inside of my database which I
will use these buttons to actually edit
later on so let's go ahead and delete
this in bed by 10 button right here and
we are going to recreate it but before
we do that let's open up another one
walk 30 minutes and let's see exactly
what's in here again it's just one step
we are editing a page in the habits
database and we can choose any database
we want and how we're editing the pages
is we're not selecting a page in the
database specifically instead we're
setting up filter criteria just like we
would when creating a new database View
and then we are going to make changes to
properties in any page within this
database that fits our filter criteria
so the goal here would be to set up our
filters in such a way that they only
target one page namely today's page and
we can easily do that with a date
property so let's go ahead and do that
and we'll start once again by typing but
with an o n in the end and we'll get our
little button block here I'm going to
call this in by 10
that's the Habit I'm tracking I'm going
to give it a nice little blue bedtime
Emoji so let's get a bed there good good
and then when the button is clicked we
are going to choose the final thing we
have not chosen yet edit pages in so we
will select our database and we're going
to choose the habits database right here
and here is where we would actually set
up our filter rules but before we do
that let's go ahead and actually choose
the property that we're going to edit so
here I have in bed by 10 which is a
check box property and we can see when I
select it I can choose how I want to
modify this checkbox so when I click it
I want that checkbox to be checked and
checkbox is a notion are by default
unchecked so you're going to be changing
its state and then the last thing we
have to do here is just edit the filters
so that we only target the page for
today which we are tracking so how would
we do that well we can see here that our
date property has a specific data in it
which is March 22 2023 that is today so
what we can do in our filters is
actually choose that date property and
instead of is relative to today or a
specific hard-coded date we can do is
and then today
so ideally if you're only making one
record in the habits database per day
and I don't know why you would do
anything different it's only going to
hit one of those pages because the
filter we just set up so I'll hit done
right there I'll come up and hit embed
by 10 and now we can see our little
checkbox property for that habit has
been checked and for a little bit of
extra flare I've also added a day score
formula and this is using those new
progress bars if I go to edit property
because this formula is outputting a
numeric value I can actually choose to
represent it as a bar and if I go into
the formula this is a little bit more
advanced but if you're curious I'm
basically just turning each of these
check boxes into a one or a zero using
this little plus prefix right here it's
called unary plus and then I'm dividing
by four so I'm getting the percentage of
completion and we're all good there so
to wrap this video up I did promise that
I would show you how to do that relative
dates trick so this is going to be a bit
more of an advanced use case but if you
are curious about how to get some
relative dates based on a Project's
published date on your tasks we are
going to do do that now so I'm going to
go over to this seven ways to be more
organized project here and uh because we
set this up before we already have our
default tasks here our due dates are
empty and they're going to stay that way
that's an ocean limitation but we also
have this little do suggested formula
property here and if I drag this over
what we can actually do this is kind of
a stop Gap until we get better
automation tools for this particular
workflow from notion is we can suggest a
date for each of these tasks based on
the published date of the video so for
example if this video is going to go
live a week from now I might want to
have the script locked two days from now
or maybe five days from the publish date
I might want to make sure that we have
the video filmed four days from the
publish date and edited fully two days
from the published date so we have time
for review and all kinds of other
projects could have this type of schema
where you have a overall done date for
the project and then you dynamically set
the dates of all the tasks within it so
that you have an nice little Cascade of
due dates well how could we do that well
if we look at our tasks here I have
added a little numeric property called
offset and this is just going to be a
number I've also added this formula
property called do suggested and I'll
show you the formula real quick it's
actually pretty simple it's just the
date subtract function and we are taking
the publish date of the project at large
which we're pulling in from a roll up
and then we're also taking the offset
that numeric value and we're subtracting
that many days from the overall publish
date so for example if I set the offset
here as 5 and I went back and actually
set a publish date for this video Let's
just say a week from now March 29th 2023
now we have a due date that is suggested
for us March 24th 2023 if we open this
back up we can see that our offset is
now modifying the content publish date
and giving us a new date as a suggestion
so what we could do is add offsets
automatically for each one of our tasks
here and then the project manager and a
company could go through and be like yep
I think March 24th is perfect for that
let's go ahead and set it so it at least
gives you guidance and a suggestion for
your due dates even though it can't
actually set these date properties here
and hey if you're cool with a formula
being your date property then you could
just use that so let me show you how to
actually do that it's one simple
configuration change to this create
default video tasks button here for each
of these tasks all we need to do is set
an offset property so the first task is
script video I'm going to change the
offset property and I'm going to set
that to let's say five because I want to
have it done five days before the video
is publish date for film video let's set
offset to say three I want to have
filmed three days before publish date
and then for edit video let's go ahead
and set that to two so that way my video
editor only has one day after I film
because I'm a mean boss and we'll go
ahead and hit done there so I'll delete
these so we have a brand new empty tasks
database here and I'll hit this one more
time
I'll hit continue and now you can see we
have our suggested due dates and they
are factored based off of our offset
value and our content publish date which
is pretty cool by the way if you want to
learn about notion formulas we just
released a brand new section on my main
website thomasjfrank.com which is a full
and complete formula reference for
notion so you can check that out if you
have any questions or you need to look
at how to write any function or operator
or constant within Notions formula
feature literally the entire thing is
documented I spent four months writing
it my team spent a ton of time
transferring it over to our main website
and building this great new section
where it's easy to to navigate through
the pages so check that out if you're
curious and that's about going to do it
for this video hopefully you liked it
hopefully you found something useful
that you can take away and apply to your
own notion workspace if you want to get
new notion tips every single week when I
publish them join my notion tips
newsletter you can find that over at
thomasjfrank.com fundamentals that is as
the whole Hub page for all my notion
Basics content that there is a very
prevalent newsletter box on there where
you can sign up and when you sign up you
can also get all my free templates and
all my resources reference guides there
is a ton of stuff so if you want a
master notion that is the way to do it
and I did show my ultimate brain
template in this video if you want to
check out ultimatebrain and if you want
a complete and done for you second brain
like a complete productivity system
inside a notion Thomas jfrank.com brain
is the place to go and you can even use
let's go 2023 at checkout to get 50 off
of that template thanks as always for
watching if you have any questions leave
them down in the comments section below
or you can hit me up on Twitter at
tomfrankly I'm pretty darn responsive
over there so follow me uh for also like
all kinds of thread boy stuff I like to
tweet about business and notion so if
you want more tips follow me there
there's a couple more videos on screen
check those out if you want something
else to watch hit that subscribe button
if you haven't already do a bunch of
other action items that you can just
make up at this point and I'll see you
in the next one
foreign