If you're already running a business and
using Zoho to send invoices or manage
your products and customers, Zoho Books
is a good next step because you have to
know how much money you're spending and
how much you're making. Zoho Books helps
you exactly there with the accounting.
It keeps your invoices and inventory
organized, and you can use it on your
phone or tablet from anywhere. In this
video, we'll show you what Zoho Books
does and what's good and not so good
about it, so you can see if it's a good
fit for your
[Music]
business. Okay, before making this Zoho
Books review, we already tested a lot of
other accounting software. You can go
and check them out and subscribe to get
more accounting software related videos
in the future. Now, let's get back to
Zoho Books. The first thing you'll
notice about Zoho Books is its clean,
modern interface. The dashboard is
designed to provide an instant picture
of your financial health that displays
key metrics like cash flow, receivables,
and payables in an approachable manner.
As you can see, the left navigation is
the home of all the features, and
navigating through the system felt
natural thanks to the wellorganized
sidebar for categorizing essential
functions. The design caters to both
newcomers and more experienced users.
However, some might find that exploring
deeper features like custom workflows
and multi-layered reports takes a bit of
time. As we've already used other Zoho
software, Zoho Books seemed quite
similar in terms of interface. Overall,
the interface is good enough for anyone
to get started
instantly. In Zoho Books, the item
section forms the backbone of inventory
management. When you add items, you are
not just listing products. You're
setting up detailed records that include
pricing, stock levels, and unit
measures. A particularly useful function
is the inventory adjustment tool, which
allows you to keep your records accurate
by accommodating quantity or value
adjustments. Say a shipment arrives and
you discover the cost of an item changes
due to market dynamics. Zoho Books
enables you to update these details
swiftly. At the same time, Zoho Books
takes the pressure off your banking
tasks. It links directly to your bank
accounts and credit cards, so your
transactions show up automatically. That
makes it way easier to match everything
up and get your books balanced without
all the back and
forth. Moving to the sales side, Zoho
Books delivers a wide suite of features
that streamline every step in the sales
process. When you add a customer, all
their past quotes, invoices, and
payments stay linked to their profile,
so you're never left guessing. You can
send a quote right from the system. And
once your customer agrees, that quote
turns into an invoice in seconds. Those
invoices aren't just templates. You can
make them yours with branding, item
descriptions, and payment details that
actually reflect how your business
works. If a client pays immediately,
it's easy to record it with a sales
receipt. Zoho Books tracks incoming
payments for you, so you're always up to
date. If you bill on a schedule, monthly
services for example, the recurring
invoice feature takes care of that
automatically. And when a refund or
price adjustment is needed, Credit Notes
let you handle it cleanly, which keeps
your record straight without extra
hassle. When it comes to managing
purchases, Zoho Books provides a full
set of tools to keep everything on
track. You can handle your vendor
relationships directly within the
platform. It stores supplier
information, tracks past transactions,
and lets you record new ones with
minimal effort. When you need to create
a bill, you just plug in the items. And
if it's something that happens
regularly, like your internet or
subscription services, you can set it up
to repeat on its own. Once a payment
goes out, it's easy to link it back to
the specific bill it covered. That makes
audits and reconciliation
straightforward. The system also
accommodates vendor credits. So, if a
vendor sends you a credit note for a
return or a pricing error, you can apply
that credit to your outstanding balance
and keep everything
aligned. If you're an accountant working
in Zoho Books, there's a whole module
built just for you. See, it's packed
with features that make your job
smoother. Let's say you come across a
transaction that doesn't really fit
anywhere. you can just create a manual
journal entry for it. And when you've
got a bunch of entries to tweak, the
bulk update tool lets you handle them
all at once, which saves a lot of time.
If you're dealing with foreign
currencies, the system adjusts
everything automatically, so your books
always reflect real world values. You've
also got full control over the chart of
accounts. You can edit, rearrange, or
import accounts as needed. Budgets are
easy to set up, too, and they help keep
spending in check. Plus, when you close
your books for a period, you can lock
those transactions so nothing gets
changed by
mistake. When you're running a business,
you need quick, clear insights into how
things are going. Zoho Books gives you a
full lineup of built-in reports that
cover everything from your profits and
losses to your balance sheet, future
cash flow, and inventory levels. You can
adjust these reports however you want
and even set them to run automatically
so you get regular updates without
lifting a finger. And it's not just
about numbers. All your business
documents like invoices, receipts, and
contracts are stored in one spot, so
you're not digging through folders or
chasing down files when you need them.
So, if you're using Zoho Books and you
need to keep track of time, whether it's
for hourly jobs or full-on projects,
it's all built in. You start by setting
up a project and breaking it into
specific tasks. Once that's done, you or
your team can log time against each of
those tasks. Every minute is captured
through the time sheet feature, which
builds a complete timeline of your work.
That data feeds directly into your
billing, ensuring every billable hour
gets invoiced properly. You can clearly
mark which hours are billable and which
aren't, giving you a solid way to
evaluate how much time is actually
making money. Plus, when you connect it
to Zoho Projects or Zoho Invoice, your
logged time transfers straight into
invoices. That means no duplicate
entries, no switching tools, just a
streamlined process from task to
payment.
Pricing becomes one of the deciding
aspects for Zoho Books. And to be
honest, it gets full marks here. Zoho
Books offers six distinct pricing plans
in total, including a free plan that is
available for companies with annual
revenues below a certain amount. The
free plan is surprisingly good,
supporting basic invoicing, expense
tracking, and bank feeds for a loan user
and one accountant. As your needs grow,
you can upgrade to the standard plan,
which increases the number of users and
extends additional features like
advanced reporting and recurring
transaction management. Moving up, the
professional and premium plans offer
even more capabilities, including
multicurrency handling and deeper
purchase order integration. For
businesses that require more
comprehensive inventory management or
multilocation operations, the Elite and
Ultimate plans provide advanced tools
such as warehouse management, batch
tracking, and enhanced data analytics.
And still, if you're unsure to pick one,
you can avail their 14-day free trial to
get a hands-on experience.
Every solution has its strengths and
weaknesses, and Zoho Books is no
exception. It does a lot to make
accounting easier. It covers the
essentials and then some, with tools
that automate the boring stuff, like
sending out recurring invoices or
pulling in your bank data so you don't
have to enter it all manually. It even
reminds customers to pay so you're not
chasing down invoices every week. And if
you're just starting out, the free plan
gives you plenty to work with without
locking you into a big expense. But
there are tradeoffs. Some folks find
that once they move past the basics, the
interface can get a little dense.
Advanced reporting and customization
take time to learn. And if you're trying
to fit the software to a very specific
workflow, it might take extra effort or
some third party help to get there. It
works well out of the box, but
fine-tuning it isn't always
simple. So, after spending some real
time testing Zoho Books, here's what we
found. It's honestly a great fit for
small businesses. The features are all
meaningful, especially if you're looking
for something that automates a lot of
your accounting tasks and gives you
accurate financial reports without a lot
of extra work. The pricing feels right,
too, especially if you're just starting
out or keeping things lean. Sure,
there's a bit of a learning curve in the
beginning, but once you get the hang of
it, it really helps you stay on top of
things. So, what do you think about Zoho
Books? Let us know in the comments
below. and be productive. Thanks for
watching. Like, share, and subscribe to
get more videos like this.