When I talk to other people who use
Notion, one of the most common missing
features that I hear about, which I
personally agree with, is the lack of a
timer or a stopwatch function. There is
no way in Notion to start a timer, to
see how much time has elapsed, to stop
it. And that means that you can't really
do something in Notion that a lot of
other productivity apps let you do, and
that's time tracking. Now, if you work
at an agency, if you work with clients,
and you bill by the hour, time tracking
is an obvious benefit to you. But even
if you're just doing your own work, time
tracking can be really, really useful
for helping you to literally see and
record how long it takes you to get
things done and then to compare that
against how long you thought it was
going to take you to get a task done,
your estimates. And that can help you
become more effective at daily planning.
So, it would be awesome if notion
supported this. And it kind of sucks
that it doesn't is what I would say if
it actually were impossible. But you can
in fact build time tracking in Notion
because Notion gives you everything you
need to build some really powerful time
tracking setups from the basic building
blocks that are already in the app. And
you can build them without needing to
integrate with any thirdparty tools like
Toggle Track. And you can do most of it
for free. Check this out. In this daily
planning dashboard that I've got set up
here, uh which I covered in my my most
recent video on daily planning, I've got
a time tab. And for every task that I've
planned to do on this particular day,
there's a start button. There is an end
button and I've got a little timetracked
property right here. So I can very
easily start a time tracking session.
And once I'm finished with that, we can
go ahead and end it. So I'm going to let
that run for a couple of seconds while I
dig into something else here that's even
perhaps cooler. If we go into this uh
clear email inbox task, you can see I've
created a history tab here. And this
actually shows me the time that I
tracked on each instance of this
recurring task. I even built a time
chart so I could see how many minutes it
took me on each instance where I did
this specific recurring task. And that
means I can track whether or not I'm
getting more efficient over time or
perhaps less efficient. And if I'm
getting less efficient, I can go ahead
and make fixes. So what I want to do
today is show you how you can build time
tracking into Notion. And it's actually
quite simple. So here we go. We're just
going to jump right in with this little
demo that I've created here. Now I'm
going to show you time tracking at a few
different levels. And we're going to
start extremely simply, but I will say
you probably want to know at least a
little bit about Notion databases before
diving into this. If you haven't messed
with them before, I think you'll
probably be able to follow along, but I
do have a notion databases for beginners
video, and I'll link that in the
description in case you're curious. So,
uh, assuming you know a little bit about
databases, here we've got a very simple
tasks database, and this shows us how we
can do time tracking at the simplest
possible level. In addition to our
default name property where we've got
some very important tasks that I need to
do because of course you've never seen
me and Spider-Man in the same room at
the same time. You do the math. Uh we
also have a couple of date properties.
We've got start time and we have end
time. And then we have an extremely
simple formula property called duration.
Now I'm not going to be delving too deep
into the formula syntax in this video,
but every formula that I have uh created
for this video is in the description
down below if you want to study it. Uh
but here this one is super duper simple.
We've got the date between function.
We're just comparing the end time
property, the start time property, and
we're specifying minutes as the unit.
So, we calculate the number of minutes
between the end time and the start time.
And in the case of our test new web
shooters task right here, it's 45
minutes. That is time tracking in
notion. The way in which you would track
a task is you'd click the start time
when you're ready to start a task. You
already have the current day on there.
So, we just go include time. We could
click now. And boom, we have started
time tracking as it were. When we're
done time tracking, we come into the end
time property and we do the exact same
thing. We include the time. I'll go
ahead and hit now just to get that in
there. And we'll just edit it to 10
minutes from now. So boom, we have just
tracked 10 minutes of time. And at the
simplest possible level, this is how you
can do time tracking in Notion. Now, you
might already be looking at this and
going, just doesn't feel very good. And
you would be correct. And of course,
it's not nearly as good as what I showed
you at the beginning of the video. If we
go back to my dashboard here, I think
it's been a few minutes. So, we can go
ahead and hit this end button. You can
see we've tracked 3 minutes of time.
We'll go ahead and end it. And if we pop
into our clear email inbox task now, we
have a time view. And uh we can see
we've tracked 3 minutes of time right
there. Uh and it didn't require going
into any date properties and doing
manual editing like that, right? So,
let's now start improving this. And
we're going to do that in three
different ways. Or rather, we're going
to solve three specific problems.
Problem number one, this is just not
going to fly. Clicking into a date
property, having to click include time,
do all that stuff. It's super duper
annoying, which means you're not going
to do it right. So, we're going to make
that way, way easier. We are also going
to fix this formula property here
because you probably don't want to track
time in just numbers of raw minutes. If
you tracked like I don't know 200
minutes on a task, you'd know if you do
some mental math that that's three hours
and 20 minutes. But uh you don't want to
do that. You want to see something nice
like this. You want to see hours,
minutes, and seconds. Even though Notion
doesn't actually track seconds, you want
to see that that set of zeros there. Uh
so we're going to fix that as well with
a nice little upgraded formula that I'll
share with you. And finally, we're going
to fix the biggest problem, which is the
fact that this kind of sort of isn't
doing time tracking right now. And that
has to do with the fact that a lot of
tasks take multiple sessions of work. If
I'm trying to locate the Green Goblin, I
might take a lunch break in the middle
of that, right? And I don't actually
want to track the lunch break time. I
want to track how much time I actually
spent working on the task. And to do
that, we're going to have to get a
little bit smarter. That's going to be
the final problem we solve because it's
going to involve upgrading our database
knowledge a little bit. So, let's wet
our pallet or appetite, whatever that
turn of phrase is, uh, and do the easier
things first. So, first things first, I
really don't want to click into this
date property. And uh I can completely
automate that behavior by bringing in
some button properties. So, let's go
ahead and do that. I'm going to go ahead
and squeeze the title or the name
property down here just so you can see
more of what I'm doing. Uh and over
here, we are going to find ourselves a
button property, and I'm going to call
it start. So, if I'm in a table view, I
can very easily create new properties
just from the table view itself. Uh,
otherwise I would go into the settings
here, go to properties or edit
properties, and I could make a new
property just like that. It's very, very
easy in table view, though. So, I'm
going to call this one start. Uh, it
doesn't intersect with the start time
because I I cleverly named that one
start time instead of start. And we're
going to find the button type property.
So, a button property, and I've got a
whole video on this, by the way. A
button property basically allows you to
configure one or more uh sort of if
this, then that actions that will happen
when you click the button. And unlike
the database automations feature, which
you can access right here, buttons are
completely free to build and use, so you
can use them on Notion's free plan. So,
we're going to drag this start button
over here, and we're going to do
something extremely simple. We're going
to hook this button up so that when you
click start, it goes ahead and starts
our tracking here by filling in the
start time. So, let's create a new task
here. And let's think of something
Spider-Man would do. Um, catch the bus
he was late for. At least the Toby
Magcguire one was. And uh we can go into
our start property. We can edit the
automation like the automation engineers
we now are. And you can see that in the
button sort of modal here. The when is
always going to have this single
trigger. Button is clicked. But the do
section down here gives us a lot of
flexibility. And in this case, we're
going to do something very very simple.
We're going to do one single new action.
It's going to be called edit property.
We're going to find our start time
property. and we're going to set it to
this nice little dynamic timet triggered
value. And that is all we have to do. So
check this out. Now when I want to start
time tracking, instead of going in here
and setting all these different values,
I just go boom, there it is. And we can
build the exact same button for our end
time property. In fact, we can make it
easy on ourselves. We can just
rightclick the start one, duplicate the
property right here. We'll go ahead and
uh change its name to end. And then if
we go to edit automation, literally all
we're going to do is change the start
time property to the end time property.
Set it the time triggered and we are
done. So now we can end our time
tracking. We've tracked 1 minute. I
think that is about as much time as it
would take Spider-Man to catch the bus
he was late for. So that seems like a
pretty good example right there. And
with that, we've solved our first
problem. Now starting and ending our
time tracking is near effortless, which
means we've removed the friction
involved in doing it. and that means
you're probably actually going to do it.
Uh, so at this point, you've got a
fairly usable time tracker, but you
still have these raw minute counts here.
And what if you had tracked a lot of
time? Like what if for whatever reason
it took uh Toby Magguire here, oops, I
gave away his secret identity. Uh, what
if it took him like many, many hours to
locate the Green Goblin? Let's go ahead
and set this uh time back here to oh, I
don't know, 1:45 a.m. It took him 610
minutes. Now, maybe you can do the math
in your head really quickly to see how
many hours and minutes 610 minutes is. I
can't do it while I'm on the spot on
camera right here at the very least. So,
let's go ahead and fix this up. Uh, and
the way in which we're going to fix this
is by making this formula smarter. So,
again, this is not going to be a formula
syntax lesson. For one, you got this AI
bar up here that can write most formulas
for you these days anyway. And for two,
I'm just going to give you the formulas
so you don't even have to ask the robot
to do it for you. But, uh, thinking
through it logically, what we would
actually want to do, and what might be a
nice little puzzle for you to try to
solve for yourself, maybe pause the
video, is we want to take this raw
number of minutes, and we want to
somehow subdivide it into a certain
number of hours. And then we want to
take the remainder, the number of
minutes that don't fit into a nice
little hour bucket, and we'll use that
for our our minutes place. And then
we'll nicely format it as a string. in
that sort of like 00 colon format. And
that's basically all we have to do. So,
luckily for you, I've created a nice
little time tracking formulas page that
I will link in the description down
below. And you will be able to just copy
and paste these formulas if you want,
including this really, really simple
one. Uh, I'm also going to make a little
template so you can just actually grab
these time trackers and you can play
around with them. Uh, and that'll ensure
that your properties are named
correctly. So you can copy and paste
these formulas and uh the property names
will not throw errors. So we're going to
grab this second formula I've created. I
called it a formatted duration formula.
And you can see it's a little bit more
complicated. But if you look in here,
you can actually see the heart of our
original formula. That's what's
calculating the number of minutes.
Everything else here is just doing the
formatting. And it's a bit more verbose.
Uh but it does some magic. So, if we
come back here, we can replace the
contents of our old formula with our new
one. And boom, 610 minutes is apparently
10 hours and 10 minutes. And all of our
other time tracking sessions also are
now giving us time in the format that
most of us expect to see it in. So,
problem number two is now solved. And
we're going to uh make sure that problem
number two is solved in the next
iteration, which is going to solve our
biggest problem yet. and the one that's
going to require us to learn some new
database knowledge. So, like I mentioned
before, what we've been doing this
entire time is only kind of sort of time
tracking. What it actually is, if you
think about this in database terms or
record terms is we are recording the
time at which this work was started on
this task and then we're recording the
time at which work was ended on this
task. In other words, the time at which
the task was finished. What we don't
really know, especially here for this
10-hour one, is how much of that time we
spent uh checking our phone to see like
the latest Pokémon card prices. Um how
much time was spent eating a KitKat, how
much time was spent taking a nice little
siesta, how much time was spent goofing
around on Overwatch since the new season
is so good. We don't know. And that is
because we're not really tracking time
here. We're tracking just when work was
started, when work was ended. So, if we
think about it, and again, I'm going to
have you think about it before we get
into the actual nitty-gritty of the
database setup. If you think about it,
how would you do this? How would you
upgrade this setup so you can more
accurately track the time spent on a
task, especially if you started and then
stopped, took breaks, sometimes did
multiple sessions, maybe multiple
Pomodoro sessions. Well, I'm not going
to keep you in suspense because you're
allowed to pause the video if you want
to. You need a second database. And that
is because databases, and this is
really, really important to your
understanding of notion and building
notion setups. So, pay attention to
this. Databases have rows and a row
needs to sort of conceptually represent
some kind of entity. In this case, in
this tasks database, each row represents
a task that needs to be done. What it
doesn't represent is a singular session
of work on that task. So the only thing
we can really do is track the time again
at which it started and the time at
which it was finished. Now you could do
some bad database design and you could
maybe have like multiple pairs of start
and end time. So you could have like
start time first session, start time
second session if you knew that you were
only ever going to do like two sessions
of work on every task. Uh but there's a
much better way to do this. And the
nerds among me who are watching this
video for some reason, uh the nerds
among you, not me, uh will be screaming
like, "Yes, first normal form, second
normal form, database normalization." Uh
if you don't know what that means, don't
worry about it. But there's a very cool
video on YouTube with a Simpsons
character in the thumbnail, which will
teach you it if you do want to
understand it. Uh so you're going to
learn a little bit of what goes into
that here and a little bit of good
database design by looking at this. So
again, a database contains rows and
every single row represents some sort of
singular conceptual entity and most
importantly the properties that are on
the database, they need to rely on the
row itself. In other words, each
property here needs to contain
information about this conceptual
entity. So down here, we've created a
second database called work sessions.
And this database has a completely
different purpose than the tasks
database up here. Instead of
representing the conceptual entity that
is a thing that needs to be done, a
thing that my mom yelled at me to get
done, a task down here, this is almost
like a journal. This every single row
here in this is recording a session of
work. I started working on something and
eventually I finished working on it. Uh
maybe I didn't actually accomplish it,
but I did stop working because I needed
to uh grab a potato chip and eat it
instead of continuing to do homework,
right? Uh so this is what we have here.
We have a test session. And actually the
name kind of doesn't matter here right
now. Uh but what does matter is that
we've recorded the start time and the
end time, not of when a task was
necessarily started and completed, but
when we sat down to start working and
when we finished working. And again we
have the exact same original formula
here. We have duration and I've uh sort
of added minutes to the name of the
property just to sort of clarify that is
what we are tracking here. Again it's
the exact same formula date between end
and start time. Minutes is our unit and
that helps us to calculate uh how many
minutes was spent on this work session.
So the one thing that we're missing here
on this work sessions database is a way
to track which task we were working on.
Now, back in ye olden days when we had
wagon wheels instead of rubber tires and
we didn't have spreadsheet applications,
we had like paper journals, we would do
something like literally writing down
what task we worked on. So, we'd edit
this here and we'd say like do a flip
session one um and you know then you
could like look at the number of
sessions you did for do a flip and you
could mentally calculate how many
minutes across all of them that you
spent and that would be time tracking.
But of course, now we have these magical
things called computers, which these
days we can even talk to and they'll
talk back. It's pretty cool, right? Uh
but we don't have jetpacks yet, so don't
get too excited. So, what we can do now
is use the power of those computers to
do all the calculations for us. And the
way in which we're going to do that is
by connecting these two databases
together via something called a
relation. And before we build a relation
here in this example, I want to go over
to another page I set up that's going to
very clearly explain what a relation
does. So a relation is a type of
property that you can put on one
database. And it allows you to relate a
row in that database to other rows.
Sometimes can be in the same database,
but can also be in a completely
different database altogether. So this I
think makes it pretty clear. We have a
movies database with some movies here
and we have a director relation
property. Now this director relation
property is connected to a paired
relation property on another database
called directors. And what this allows
us to do is associate movie records.
Again, every database has rows and every
row is representing some sort of
consistent conceptual entity. So here we
would just want to have movies. Uh here
we are allowed to relate our our movie
records or rows to director records or
rows over here on our director's table.
And you can see if I go ahead and I pick
the director of Titanic, which oh man,
who was it again? H you're probably
feeling very frustrated right now
because this is obvious. It's clearly
Greta Gerwig, right? No. Uh if I pick
James Cameron here for Titanic over
here, it actually popped in. Now Titanic
is listed underneath the movies relation
for James Cameron. So that is what
relations do. They allow us to connect
records together. Sometimes in the same
database like in the case of parent
tasks and subtasks in a singular tasks
database or in uh in many cases perhaps
more often across multiple different
databases in this case movies and
directors and in the case that we were
building over here tasks and one or more
work sessions that are related to that
task. In other words, a record of work
we did on do a flip or test new web
shooters or whatever it is. So the way
we can make this connection is we can
create a property. It's going to be
called uh I think I'll just call it
task. That makes sense. And we're going
to find the relation type right here.
And then we're going to be asked to link
it to a data source. Now you can see I
actually have many different databases
of the same exact name. But luckily I'm
smart and I use color coding on my icons
so I can tell which one that I'm looking
at. And you can see here if you've never
created a relation before, we can see
that this one indicates this little I
indicates that this is uh this database.
So you could do a same database
relation, but what we really want to do
is relate this to our tasks database. So
now we've got our new relation property.
It is called task. And we're going to
turn on the two-way relation option
here, which allows us to create that
paired property. You saw it earlier in
the movies and directors database. We
can pop over to that again. uh we have
that paired property director is a
linked to the movies property over here.
You actually don't have to do that. You
can do it without a two-way relation,
but in this case, I'm going to call it
work sessions. Now, you could normally
call whatever you want, but since I
pre-created the formulas with the proper
property names in there, I got to make
sure I get it right. We'll hit add
relation. And what you're going to see
is we have a task relation property here
on work sessions. And then we have this
now paired property, this two-way
relation. Uh, we have this other
property on tasks. So now when I go
ahead and associate this work session,
do a flip session one with the do a flip
task, check that out. It's going to pop
in here. So now this session of work is
related to the do a flip task. And if we
did another session of work, do a flip
session two. And while I'm typing this,
I will mention that we're going to make
it way way easier and automatic to
create these. But just for illustrative
purposes, if I do do a flip session 2,
we go ahead and just say uh include time
and now 12:04. And uh for whatever
reason, I just know in the future I
finished this at 1 p.m. So I'm going to
go ahead and record it there. We've got
56. So now conceptually at least in our
minds, we know that we have 29 + 56,
which is kind of like 30 + 56, which is
86, but it's actually 85. So that is 85
minutes tracked or 1 hour and 25 minutes
tracked on this particular task across
two different work sessions. Now if you
don't want to do that crazy under
pressure on camera uh mental math there
we can again let the computers do it for
us. So here's how. So what we want to do
is go up here into our tasks database
and we want to create a formula and the
formula is going to be called duration.
And we actually had the duration formula
earlier on our more simple which is
actually better expressed as the word
simpler fun fact on our simpler uh
single database time tracker. So we're
going to go formula here duration just
like that. And if we go back to the time
tracker you can see that what we had
earlier was that kind of crazy
gobbledygook formula where we were just
taking the difference between end time
and start time and then formatting it.
But what we want to do in our new setup
is a little bit different because we are
not taking the difference between start
time and end time. Instead, we want to
add up all of these duration in minutes
properties down here for each related
work session. And let's go ahead while
we're thinking about it and relate that
second session to do a flip. Again, this
is not going to be a crazy formula
lesson. I literally have created the
final formula which you can copy and
paste. But just to show you a little bit
of theory here, if we go into the
formula editor and we find our work
sessions relation, you can see that
right now what this formula outputs is a
list of uh all of the pages related to
this particular page, which in this case
is do a flip. So we've got session one,
session two. What we can do is pass it
into the map function. And with the map
function, we could use current and we
could do dot duration minutes. And that
gives us a list with those two minute
values. And then because you don't want
to do that crazy under pressure mental
math in your head, we could just do
some. And there it is, 85 minutes. And
that is proper time tracking. That is
looking into our journal of records that
actually represent uh a session of work,
adding up all the sessions of work that
are related to a specific task, and
giving us our final minute count. Now,
for the past resistance here, uh, we're
going to grab our final formula, and
hopefully I didn't screw something up
because that would be quite the, uh,
splat on my face in terms of this
flourish. We paste that in there, and we
get exactly what we wanted. We get our
nice formatted duration, which
represents the total time across all
sessions that we tracked. So, to finish
this up, we want to bring back in those
buttons. Earlier, we created these nice
little buttons which allow us to start
tracking and end tracking extremely
easily. And we want to bring that into
our more advanced and proper setup. But
it's going to be a little more
complicated than what we had here
because as a bit of a recap, all we
needed to do here was just edit a
property of the exact same page and we
set the start time to the time
triggered. Here we're doing something a
little different. We actually need that
start button not to set a time or date
here or here. In fact, we can just hide
these. These are kind of no longer
needed, at least for time tracking. What
we need to do is have that start button
actually create a new entry in our work
sessions journal and record the time.
And then uh somewhat more complicatedly,
and I'm not actually sure if that's a
word, but some more uh somewhat more
complicatedly going to make it a word.
Uh the end button needs to actually find
the correct entry and end it. So let's
start building those. We're going to
find a button property in this list of
property types. Once again, it's called
start. I'm going to go ahead and make it
nice and narrow because it's just a
button with the word start in it. Uh and
we're going to go ahead and build out
that automation. So this one's actually
pretty easy to start with at least.
Instead of editing a property, we're
going to add a page to a different data
source. And remember, if you've not
watched my video on Notion data sources,
Notion kind of renamed databases to data
sources and then they allow databases to
contain multiple data sources. And then
I feel like they sort of hidden that
capability because it's really
confusing. Uh, but if you're curious as
to why it says data source, that's why.
Check out that video link in the
description below if you really want to
understand the nitty-gritty. Uh but for
the most part, if you're not doing
multiple data sources on the same
database, you can use the terms
interchangeably. Okay, so we're going to
say we're going to add a new page to the
work sessions data source here. Uh the
name kind of doesn't matter. Now, we're
going to give it a name just to be
fancy, I suppose, but what really
matters is that we set that start time
to the time triggered. And what also
matters and this is really important. We
set the task relation property to this
page. And this page right here, this
dynamic value, this page represents the
page on which the button was clicked. So
if we click it on the do a flip page, um
the task relation property is going to
be set to the do a flip page. And for
the session, we can do something that
just sort of makes it descriptive. So
let's just go ahead and uh do a string
called session colon space. We'll do
plus. We'll grab the this page. Um, and
honestly, that's kind of all you need.
You have the rest of the data you need
outside of the name property. And to
just get a little nerdy for a second, if
we weren't building this in Notion, if
we were building this in like an actual
SQL database, we wouldn't worry about a
special name here because all the
information we really need is right
here. What's the time? What's the
related task from our tasks table?
That's the SQL term for database in
Notion. Um, and then we'd have like a
unique ID that automatically gets
generated. So, the name really doesn't
matter and I'm just kind of putting it
there for aesthetic value. Uh, so we'll
hit save. And now I'll show you how it
works. So, let's say that uh we're going
to start locating Green Goblin. We'll
hit start. Boom. There we go. We've got
session locate Green Goblin. We've got
the start time recorded. That is now.
And very importantly, locate Green
Goblin is our task relation value, which
means we already have this brand new
session related to the locate Green
Goblin task. Step one complete of our
little button adventure here. Uh, now
what we need to do is add the end
button. And I will tease the fact that
actually we're not done with the start
button. And if you want to try to puzzle
it out in your head while we're doing
the end thing, that'll be a nice little
puzzle for you. Um, because yeah, the
start button is kind of incomplete. But
I'll reveal why that is a little bit
later. So, we're going to go ahead and
just duplicate the property. I love
duplicating properties. It reduces
clicks, makes things nice and easy, and
uh as an engineer, I am lazy, but
questionably brilliant. Let's go into
edit automation for end here. And we're
just going to go ahead and get rid of
add page to work sessions because we
already know that when we click end, we
don't want to add a page to work
sessions. We want to find the current
page that represents the current work
session and we want to sort of just
close it out. Add that end time property
value. So let's go ahead and get rid of
this action here. And now let's think.
Let's use our minds here. How do we even
know which page to get. Now there's a
couple of different ways you can do it.
In this extremely simple example, which
by the way, I will note that we are not
building for team use cases. We're
building for an individual use case. So,
we're not even bringing in people
properties, things like that. Uh, but in
this very extremely simple example,
usually you're only going to be tracking
one task at a time. So, what we could do
is do the edit pages in and we could do
select data source. We could find our
work sessions data source right there.
And then we could do a filter and we
could just say where uh end time is
empty. And uh that would pretty reliably
find the one task or the one work
session rather uh the one work session
that has an empty end time and then we
could just go ahead and set that end
time. I want to show you a smarter way
to do it though. Uh and this will
actually teach you a little bit about
buttons and how far you can take them.
So instead of just filtering the data
source directly, what we can do is grab
the define variables action here in our
button. This is a extremely versatile
action here. Um, and though I have
criticized Notion for like leaving some
really important features out of the
automations feature thus far, like loops
and things like that, define variables
does allow us to do some really cool
stuff. So, I'm going to define a
variable. I'm going to call it current
session. And you will see that we have
this nice little field which includes a
formula icon. And that means we can
define a variable that contains a lot of
different kind of stuff including a list
of pages. So, we are going to use the
formula editor here to create a list of
of the uh of any work sessions that are
currently not done for this particular
task. And that list, I'm putting list in
quotes because it's only ever going to
be one or zero pages. Either that
there's no currently running um session
or there is one. So, it's going to be a
list of either zero or one elements. So,
what we're going to do is go with this
page like that. We'll do dot work
sessions. And if we left it at this, we
would get a list of every single work
session that was ever done for this
task, even the finished ones. So, we
want to finish this up by passing it
into the filter function. And we're
going to go current.end
time. This is representing the end time
property of uh all potential pages in
this list. And we're just going to
compare it against empty. It's a nice
newer functionality in notion formulas.
You can literally compare, you can do an
equality comparison against the empty
functions output. Uh, which literally
lets you check if something is empty
rather than just false. That's kind of a
new thing and I love notion for doing
that. So, this will give us a here it is
list of blocks because pages are blocks.
Remember that. This will give us a list
of I'm just going to say pages. Um, and
it's going to either be a single page
inside of that list, the one that is not
done, or if we click the end time button
or the end button on accident and we
already had ended it before, that list
will be no pages and simply nothing will
happen. So, click save there. And here
is the cool thing. If we go back to add
action and we bring back in that edit
pages in action here, what we can do is
instead of selecting a data source, we
get to select the current session
variable. Now, I want to explain why
we're able to select it. Because you're
not always going to be able to select
current session or variable that you
define in this edit pages action. Very
specifically, what your variable needs
to be returning is, and we can look at
it again, a list of blocks. And
remember, when we say blocks in this
case, in this case, it's pages. And it's
pretty much always pages. Um, so if we
are returning a list of pages, then we
can actually operate on the properties
of those pages in that list by choosing
our current session right here, our
variable. It's a really, really nice
trick inside of notion buttons and
automations. So here we're going to do
the same thing. We're just going to go
with end time, set that to time
triggered, and save it. And now, as I've
been yapping this entire time, we have
located the Green Goblin. Or actually
maybe instead of locating him, we we
actually just uh took a lunch break. So
let's end for now. And you can see we
tracked six minutes of time on that
particular session for locating the
Green Goblin. Now that means our end
button is fixed. But think about the
fact that I am imperfect
uh like most human beings. And sometimes
I'm forgetful. And sometimes what that
means is I might already have a session
of work running when I go click start.
And that could mean I could have two
sessions running at the same time and I
could be tracking two minutes of work
for every minute that I exist in this
world. And until cloning technology
comes into being, that's not a thing I
can do. So as I alluded to before uh or
actually outright stated, our start
button is not complete. we need to add a
guard. And this is actually uh something
that's very important concept in systems
design all the way from notion on the
kind of simple end to like programming
and building apps on the more
complicated end. Um you want to add sort
of guard conditions to guard against
erroneous user behavior which is a $10
or 10 cent or 25cent term or whatever
that term for that term is. Uh we want
to guard against errors you know
mistakes people make. In this case, we
want to guard against the fact that they
might click the start button before
they've ended the currently running
task. So, let's go into our edit
automation one more time. And in this
case, all we need to do is do an edit
pages in. We're going to drag it to the
top here. And we're going to find our
work sessions database. And we're going
to do what I showed you as the first
option in the end button before. We're
just going to say uh for any page where
the end time is empty. So or go there is
a currently running session. We're going
to set that end time to the time
triggered. Now again, I want to stress
that this example is purposefully simple
and it's purposefully single player. If
you're trying to build a teamwide
tracking system, you need to get a
little bit fancier with your filtering
here. Uh you would want to say like also
end time is empty and also the person on
the work session. You'd want a person
property uh is the person who clicked or
I think it's going to be is me. there's
like this me variable there. So, that's
how you would add that in there. But,
I'm keeping this as simple as possible
for this particular video. Um, let me
know in the comments if there's like a
lot of demand for a team version of it.
Um, but that's kind of all you need. So,
now if we hit save, um, and we started
test new web shooters. So, now we have
one work session going across the entire
work sessions database that doesn't have
an end time. And then we are like, oh, I
need to do some work on locating the
Green Goblin. We hit start.
Now we again only have one running
because the other one we created right
here gets automatically ended before the
new one starts. And that my friends is
how you build time tracking inside of
notion at least at a simplistic level.
Now I'm going to make all of what I've
shown you here available as a free
template in the description down below
so you can play with it. And like I
showed you near the beginning of the
video, you can take this really far. And
most importantly, instead of it being an
isolated example here that's useful as a
toy or useful for learning, you can
build this into larger systems and you
can integrate this into things that you
may actually be using either in your
personal life or perhaps with a team.
You can do things like what I showed you
at the beginning of the video. Let's go
ahead and recap it. Now that we have
sort of gotten the foundation and we
understand what's going on underneath
the hood, you already know when I click
the start button on this clear email
inbox task, it's creating a work session
entry in my work sessions database and
it's making sure that it's related to
this particular task. And if I click
end, it's going to find that work
session. It's going to end it. And that
means I can track multiple sessions of
work just like you would on any other
full-fledged time tracking app. Now, of
course, we don't get the nice ticking up
timer here. And boy, would I love it if
Notion added that in the future. But we
do get perfectly usable time tracking
functionality. And even more important
than that, with Notion and with all of
the additional blocks and systems that
we have at our disposal here, we can
upgrade that and we can do things that
most apps don't let us do. Like I showed
you earlier, if we are building out a
more robust task management system, we
can build these tabs. By the way, check
out my uh database layouts video linked
below if you want to figure out how to
build these tabs. But we can build these
tabs that show us all of our work
sessions. We can even get really fancy
and we can uh make sure that we have
time tracking on recurring tasks. And we
can literally create charts like this
one here that shows us how many minutes
we took on each instance of our
recurring task. And you can see here in
this example, I'm getting more and more
efficient over time at it. So, if you
want to uh build this for yourself, you
are now equipped with all the knowledge
you need. And if you want to go further
with things like charts, with things
like these tabs and layouts, I have
other videos on my channel that will
teach you exactly how to do that. If you
want all of this done for you, what I've
been showing you as the example here,
the bigger example, uh is a part of my
ultimate brain template. This is one
single system inside of notion that lets
you organize your entire life. It comes
with, as you can see here, a really
powerful daily planning dashboard called
my day where you can very easily choose
the tasks deliberately that you're going
to work on. And then you have this very
nice execute session that keeps your
focus on those tasks and keeps you from
getting distracted by other things that
you weren't going to do today. In
addition to this daily planning
dashboard, you've got the best task
management system you're going to find
for Notion. Seriously, it has recurring
tasks with tons of different uh
recurring intervals that you're not
going to find anywhere else. We invested
months and months of work into making
that work. Uh they automatically process
themselves. Recurring tasks work well
with time tracking as you've seen. You
can get a historical record of all the
tasks you've done. And on top of that
task management system, or rather sort
of next to it and connected, you have a
really powerful notetaking system that
works very well with our web clipper
flylighter for capturing research and
highlights from the web. You've got goal
tracking. You have a lot of other pieces
that basically make this a one-stop shop
for organizing your entire life and
making sure that nothing slips through
the cracks. You can find this over at
thomasjfrank.com/brain.
You also get built-in support and
really, really great tutorials and
videos, documentation, everything you
could possibly need to customize the
template and to make sure you understand
how to use it. We have a support
community where notion experts answer
your questions. And as a thank you for
hanging out with me today and learning
some cool stuff about time tracking, you
can use the code on screen right now to
get 50 bucks off of any edition of the
template. Once again,
thomasjfrank.com/brain
to get your personal copy of Ultimate
Brain and to start organizing your life
more effectively. And as always, thanks
so much for hanging out with me today.
If you want to uh further your notion
knowledge, number one, I've got this
task manager build guide video right
here. This is probably my best current
piece of content if you really want to
learn the ins and outs of Notion. It'll
teach you databases. It'll teach you a
lot and it's also very practical. Also,
we talked about my daily planning
dashboard in this video.