You need to use N right now. It's the
most powerful automation tool I've ever
seen. On top of that, it's open- source,
local, private, and free. It makes
Zapier and ift crop. But hold up, I'm
warning you. N is addicting because you
can automate everything right here from
this beautiful guey. We can start with
something simple. Aggregating your news,
YouTube, subreddits, hacker news, a nice
daily digest sent to your inbox. Maybe
sprinkle in a little bit of AI
summarization. Let's get crazier and
automate your home lab. Run commands on
a schedule. Create an AI agent that will
troubleshoot your home lab before you
even know there's an issue. You can even
talk with your home lab. Think about
that. If you're in it in any capacity,
you need to run Nate. They have
connections to every service you use.
And if they don't, you can make your
own. And I'm not sure you heard me. You
can automate everything. Your email
inbox, social media post, your toilet,
it can do anything. Honestly, the
hardest part is figuring out what to do
first. Let me help you with that. In
this video, I'm going to walk you
through every step of setting up N8N in
your lab, teaching you the basics of
N8N, and walking you through a few of
your very first automation projects,
which I think you're going to love. To
get your coffee ready, let's automate.
Now, real quick, have you hacked the
YouTube algorithm? Let's make sure you
do. Hit that like button, subscribe,
comment, notification bell. You got to
hack YouTube today. Ethically, of
course. I'm going to show you two ways
you can install an AM. I encourage you
to take a glance at both paths so you
can kind of get a feel for what's best
for you. The first way is on prem in
your home lab in your house. This option
will be a bit more complex, but that
just makes it more fun. The good news is
that NAN is light. You'll need some
Linux, so think a server or a desktop
computer, but it doesn't have to be big.
It can be as small as a Raspberry Pi. In
fact, it can be much smaller. What's
funny is their official documentation is
like, eh, you don't need much. It's not
CPU intensive. And no matter what
hardware you choose, we will be
installing this with Docker, which is
amazing. If you don't know what that is,
that's fine. I'm going to walk you
through it. The second option is my
favorite and recommended path, the
cloud. For this, you've got options. I'm
going to walk you through setting it up
on Hostinger. They are the sponsor of
this video and where I host a lot of my
home lab now. Now, the reason I like
this option is because N8 connects to a
ton of things and it has a ton of
things. Connect to it. The cloud option
is less complex and you'll be up and
running in a few sips of coffee. One
more to go. The first thing you'll do is
set up your cloud account. We're going
to do it on Hostinger. Head out to
hostinger.com/n.
>> Now, real quick, check this out. If I go
to services and go to VPS, which is a
virtual private server is what we're
doing. You can jump right into nan VPS
hosting. It's like they knew we were
coming. Click on that. Choose your plan.
KVM2 is perfect. With all of this, you
can have an entire home lab, not just
Nate. Run a website. Run open web UI. A
lot of the projects I've talked about on
this channel can be run with this one
virtual machine in the cloud. And don't
forget to put in coupon code network
chuck. Some magic stuff will happen.
Now, if you chose that special nan
option, you're pretty much done. If
however you already had a hostinger
server, maybe running Ubuntu or
something or any other type of VPS,
continue on to the on-prem installation,
it's going to be pretty much the same.
Hey, Network Chuck from the future here.
I decided to pop out the section for the
on-prem install into its own video,
which you can see right here. Why?
Because I did not want you to wait to
see how powerful N is, which I'm about
to show you right now. Once it finishes
setting up and you're at the server
console, just click on manage app and it
takes you right to the NAN signup page
for your own hosted NAN. Anyways, let's
get logged in or signed up. I don't want
to receive any updates. Next, we don't
have to fill any of that out. And you
actually do want this free activation
key. So, go ahead and have it send that
to you. Check your email. I just
received my key. So, I'll go to the
usage and plan area to enter my
activation key. Again, this is all free.
And done. So, now here we are at the
overview. NAN is installed.
Now what? Let's set up your first
automation. And what NAN calls an
automation is a workflow. We'll start
right up here. Click on create workflow.
Now you're about to have a whole world
open up to you. This is so fun. Now for
me, I always feel like I'm behind. Like
I I have it's so hard for me to keep up
with all the tech news coming out.
Checking bleeping computer, hacker news,
subreddits, YouTube. It's all so much. I
need a better solution. We're going to
make that right now. Now, we're going to
start small, something very simple. And
then we're gonna slowly get more insane.
It's like a skinny dude just getting to
the gym. We're starting slim. By the
end, we're going to be yolked and
insane. All right, n basics. Here we
stinking go. Click on the square to add
our first step. Boom. What's happening
here? We're adding our first trigger.
What's going to make our workflows flow,
do its thing? 99% of the time, you're
going to start with trigger manually
right here. Your workflows can always
have this trigger along with other
triggers. We'll cover that here in a
second. Actually, you know what? Let's
add another trigger right now. So, at
the top right, you'll see we have our
plus icon. Let's add another one. Plus,
and then down here, we have add another
trigger. This time, we'll do on a
schedule. And we'll say every 1 day at
Yeah, midnight's actually great. Done.
So, now we have two triggers. Both ready
to do some things. Let's click on that
first plus icon to add our next node.
Now, here you have a billion options. We
have a fun AI section, which we'll cover
a little bit here in a moment. You can
do something in an app and they have a
bajillion connections to whatever
service you can think of. Just know we
have a bunch of nodes and they help us
do things. The first thing I want to do
is search for RSS. We're going to do an
RSS read trigger. And notice it
immediately threw us into the node. We
can click out of it just by clicking
some blank space. It's sitting right
here. It's got like a little angry thing
because we haven't configured it yet.
But notice how it connects. We can also
take our schedule trigger and connect it
here too. Boom. Just like that. Or we
can delete it. Boom. And we're going to
start with one RSS feed. It's going to
be from bleeping computer. Put it in
there. Get out of there. Let's save our
config. You want to save often like
everything in it. Top right. Click on
save. We're saved. And now let's test
our RSS read. Let's jump in there. Just
double click your icon, your node, and
click on execute step right here at the
top. Go. Did you see all that? It just
went out and pulled all the stuff, all
the articles from bleeping computer.
Notice our fields are the creator, the
title. Unified CM has a hardcoded root
SSH group. That's bad. Um, anyways, we
have a whole bunch of fields. Even has
the entire content. And notice a few
things here. We actually have our number
of items. It pulled 13 articles from the
feed. We don't control that. That's just
how many were available in the RSS feed.
And also notice over here, we can change
how we view this data. Now, you're about
to become an expert in JSON because NAN
is very JSON heavy. We can view it in
JSON or JSON or we can view the schema
all the available fields. Now if we
click out, notice that we have on our
little timeline connector here. The
trigger was like one item which is just
go the RSS read when it read the RSS
feed. It pulled in 13 items and that's
what it's going to hand off to the next
step. All right, cool. We pulled in 13
articles from bleeding computer. Let's
send it somewhere. Let's say Discord. So
I'm going to add another node right
here. Boom. I'll search for Discord.
They do have a built-in Discord node.
And look at all these options. You can
do so many things for me. I'm going to
send a message. Yes, that's what I'm
doing. Now, immediately we're thrust
into this and we have a lot of options.
The first is our connection type. Now,
keep in mind, every node is going to
have their own configuration. Now, for
our connection type, I want to do a
simple web hook because all I want to do
is send a message to one particular
channel. But in order to do that, I'll
need a credential, something to connect
to this service. Now, you'll see this a
lot with N8. You can connect all kinds
of things like your Gmail account, your
Gmail calendar, notion, open AAI, Grock,
Anthropic, a lot of connections, a lot
of credentials. Let's go and add one
right now for Discord. Now, for this
particular use case, it will only be a
web hook URL. Very simple. Feel free to
follow along. Like, it's free to set up
a Discord server. I just did it just now
as we're talking. I'm going to create a
new channel. Sweet sweet news. creating
it and then I'll go into my server
settings, go to integrations and create
a quick web hook which will post to
sweet news. I'll copy that URL, paste it
here, click save and we have our first
credential created and notice how we
have a drop down because we can have
multiple Discord credentials but we just
have the one now we're going to send a
message and we're going to say
something. Now first I'm just going to
test it. I'm going to say hi and
execute. Excellent. We got a success
true. Now is that true? Let's go check.
Oh gosh, it just said hi a million times
in general. I hadn't saved it for the
other thing yet. Now, real quick, why do
you think it said hi 13 times? Watch,
I'll do it again. By the way, isn't this
like playing with video game? Like, why
do people even play video games when you
can do stuff like this in your home lab?
Are you kidding me? Let's say I bet you
there will be 13 of these. Go. Done.
Look back in Discord. We have 13
messages. Why? That's how n handles
things. Notice that we're handing off 13
articles or items from our RSS read
node. The Discord node is going to go
through each one of those 13 items and
perform 13 individual actions. Now, the
reason I only said like hi or that dumb
sentence I had is because I didn't put
anything specific to those articles in
the message. Let's change that right
now. So, let's start with hey, here is
your news for the day. And here's where
things get very fun. Let's hit enter a
few times. Give us some space. and let's
start adding some of the content from
these articles. Let's add the creator.
I'm just going to grab this right here.
See this how notice how my mouse
highlights it? I'm going to drag it over
right there. Look at that. Notice it's
going to be JSON.creator. It's pulling
from this JSON information. And this
notation right here is actually
JavaScript. Don't get scared. You won't
have to know JavaScript to move forward
with N8. You're going to get better at
JavaScript because it does rely on that
quite a bit. But we've got Chatbt and
Claude to help us figure out some other
things. But you for now you won't have
to know that. Just notice what I did
there. I dragged and it created that. So
we'll put the creator. Let's put the uh
title. We'll put the link and the
publish date. How about that? And notice
how below us we're seeing the result,
the example, what those variables are
forming into. Let's test that out.
Execute step. Let's go see what
happened. Ah, look at that actual news.
Notice it sent out 13 messages. But also
notice it said, "Hey, here's your news
for the day 13 times, one for each
article." Not ideal. We'll definitely
fix that. But so far, we've done
something pretty cool. I'm going click
save one more time. We set up a node to
pull information from an RSS feed. And
then we're sending that information to a
Discord channel. But honestly, 13 is too
much. I don't want to see 13 things.
Let's limit that information. So, right
here between the Discord node and the
RSS read node, I'm going to add
something called limit, which will
restrict the number of items. I'm going
to say I only want to see five things.
Now, I could execute it from here. I
don't have to. I can jump out, hit the
play button right here. Boom. And now
we're only sending five items. Now, do
you want to see something really cool?
This has nothing to do with news, but I
can't I can't wait to show Oh, I almost
want my coffee. That's how excited I am.
I can't wait to show you this. Now, we
don't have to click on anything to add a
new node. We can just go up here to the
plus sign or even just hit tab and open
up the node selector. I'm going to
search for command line. We can execute
commands on the host.
So, I'm click out of it. Look at that.
That's pretty sick. I'm going to have
this click to execute button make that
go off, too. Now, look at that. I can
actually make both of these go off
another branch. Let's have it do
something. So, let's jump into our node.
This will be a command that we're
actually doing, executing on our Docker
host. I'm going to say ping 1.1.1.1.
And we'll do that for account. So, - C
of three. Let's try it out. Look at
that. We are able to run commands. Now,
I don't know about you, but when I see
that, I'm like, oh my gosh, I'm starting
to get this. I have a billion ideas.
Now, let's let's say that we're doing a
test for our internet and we know that
when we ping 1.1.1.1 and we get
responses back, we know it's working and
maybe we want to have that sent to us in
our Discord message. Let's do that right
now. So, I'm actually going to delete
this connection between Discord and the
limit node. Now, I'm teaching you a
little bit about how we manipulate data
inside N. I'm going to add a new node
right here called the merge node. We can
merge sets of data. Notice how it has
two inputs, limits going into one. Let's
add our command output into the other.
For merge, we have a few options or more
than a few. We have a lot. But appending
is great. So, it's going to append one
input to another. I'll show you what
that looks like here in a second. But
notice something kind of weird. Notice
how our command output shows one item
going out, but our RSS feed or read and
our limit is outputting nothing. It kind
of reset, didn't it? So, now we have to
go back in there and run them again to
pull fresh data. So, I'll jump into RSS
read. Execute the step again. Notice how
our command output is now gone. and it
kind of resets as you're going through.
That's annoying, especially as you get
to later steps. There's a way to get
beyond that when you're testing. I can
jump into this RSS read. Notice how we
have our results here on the right. And
I have a little thumb tag. I can pin
that data. Say, keep that data there.
Don't ever remove it. Same thing goes
for limit. When I execute limit, I can
say boom, pin that there. So no matter
what happens, that stays there. I'll do
the same thing for command. Pin that
sucker. Notice we have a pen on each of
the nodes when we do that. And then
we'll execute our merge. And I'll show
you what it does here. So, it actually
just did our five articles we're pushing
over. And at the end, we have a bunch of
weird fields, but at the end, it added
in our ping results, which is standard
out, a new column that has. And notice
we're outputting six items. Now, let's
connect that back to Discord and let's
jump into the Discord node and mess with
a few things. Actually, I'm just going
to add one more new piece of data. We're
going to add our standard out here. So,
notice the ping results are down here
with standard out or stout. No doubt.
Now let's run it. True true true a lot
of stuff. If we check Discord, there's
all our articles and at the end is our
ping result. Now sidebar, beyond just
doing the command, execute a command on
the Docker host, we can also add an SSH
node that will log into any computer or
server with SSH access and execute any
command you want. Network, switch,
router, anything. I know your gears are
turning. Stop it. You can't do that
right now. You're going to get
distracted. We got to learn the basics
before you move on. Sorry, that was my
fault. Now, one of the killer things
that I have not shown you yet with NA is
the power of AI. Now, already NA is cool
because you can do all of this and we
haven't even touched AI.
Let's add AI to it. Let's say we've got
all these articles coming in, these five
items from Bleeping Computer, but who
has time to read that? Let's have AI
summarize that for us. So, right here
between the limit and the merge, I'm
going to add a new node. I'll choose AI
and we have a bunch of options. The most
common one is right here, the basic LLM
chain. We'll select that and we'll jump
out of it real quick so you can see it
nice and clean here. Let's make some
room for our new family member, our new
friend. Notice our LLM chain. He's a
bigger node and he has this weird thing
jutting out of him. And this is for our
AI model. We can choose whatever AI
model we want to connect to this and be
the brains. Let's do that right now.
Click on plus and we have some options.
Anthropic, Azure, Deepseek, OpenAI, or
even Olma, a local model. So here I'll
select Olama. Why not? We will need a
credential. I'll create one right now.
And it's just going to be connecting to
a host. Now my local host is not running
my Olama server. It's going to be Terry
here in my data center. They might be
wondering, Chuck, how are you doing
this? You're right now connected to
Hostinger, but you're somehow accessing
your stuff on prem. And that magic is
with Twin. They're not sponsoring this
video, but I use them all the time for
stuff like this. It's insanely secure
and awesome. If you want to learn more,
I've got a video about it here. So,
anyways, let's see if this works. Click
on save. It's going to test the
connection. Okay, I think it worked. And
then now I can select all of my local
models. I'll run llama 3.2. Why not? So
now the LLM chain, I've got my model
connected. Now let's have it do
something. So I'll double click the LM
chain node. So it's hoping to have a
chat trigger connected to it. Instead of
that, we're going to define our own
message, a prompt, and I'll say, "Hey,
your job is to summarize this article in
two sentences. Go." And then I'll add in
the content. Now, the content is very
much abbreviated. And how is Oama going
to summarize what's not there? So, let's
try this. I'm going to change my RSS
feed from Bleeping Computer to Krebs,
another securitybased blog. Krebs on
security. And I believe when I do that,
I should get the entire blog and the
content. Yeah, it's like every bit of
it. That's awesome. I'm gonna pin that.
Jump into my limit. Execute again.
Unpin, and test. There it is. I'll pin
that now. So now when I jump into my
LLM, I'll add the content and coded. And
that should be everything. Let's take a
look by expanding the box. Yep, every
bit of it. So now let's execute the step
and see how Oama handles this. Now I'm
worried because that is a lot of
content. And if I as I step out, you can
see it's working, which is this is so
cool. Look at this. And there goes
three, four, five items. It finished up.
Let's check it out. The output now is
okay. It didn't quite summarize each
article in two sentences because we're
dealing with the local model. And the
context window of a local model is
smaller. Oh, Lama did. Okay. But if we
trade it out for more of a frontier
model, let's do uh chat GBT. I'll create
a new credential for OpenAI. I'll use 41
mini. That's fine. Let's see how that
does.
Not too bad at all. That's awesome.
Check this out. Let's add a LLM chain
between our execute command and the
merge. Let's do AI. We'll do standard LM
chain. And let's do something like this.
Tell me if the internet is up. If you
see successful pings from the output
below, that means it's good. Tell me in
a funny way. Impersonating Eddie Murphy.
Let's grab the standard out. Put it
right there. We'll give it open AI.
Let's see how it does.
[Laughter]
That's
stupid,
but it's powerful. You get what I'm kind
of trying to do here. But come on. I
know what you're thinking. Like, what
else can you do with that? So, let's
expand this a bit more. I'm going to
save this. This will be like our part
one project. And I'll go up to the top
left here. See where it says my
workflow? We're going to click in there
and just name this my first one. And
then we're going to go up here to the
top right, click the buttons or the dots
here and say duplicate. We'll say my
second one
and duplicate. Now we have another
workflow. If I go back to personal on
the side here, I can see I have my two
workflows. I can go to credentials. See,
I have all my credentials here that I've
created. Executions. Every time we've
run something, you can jump in and
analyze exactly what happened. Like,
isn't that amazing? This thing's too
powerful. Let's get back to our second
one. Let's add some more fun stuff. So,
what I want to do actually is finish up
this project. Let's combine all the
information that we now have from our AI
powered stuff.
And I should have uh pinned that
information. Pinned that.
This is where pinning information is
great because you don't want to waste
tokens on AI. Speaking of tokens, look
at this. I'm going to run it again. We
got a log here. What's going on? It
shows you in real time the tokens being
used on the bottom left here. Isn't that
cool? All right. Now, we're really going
to pin that information. Now, before we
get to merge, I want to mess with our
data over here for a second because
right now, if we look at our LLM chain,
right, it's outputting just the summary.
That's all it's handing out and these
five items, that's all we're seeing. But
I also want to include information from
our limit, like the creator and the
title and the link. So, we can do
something pretty cool with a node called
the set field node. I'm going to add it
right here. Search for it. Set or edit
fields. There it is. So, it's sitting
right here. What we can do is just take
certain things we want to include. So,
I'm going to go back to previous steps.
I'll go to the limit step. So, give me
uh give me the creator, give me the
title. I'm just dragging stuff over.
Give me the link publication date. And
then I'll add in the summary that Chad
GPT made. So, if I execute that, bam, it
created those fields, just the ones I
want. And then we'll send them to our
Discord. And actually what I want to do
now is remove the merge because it gets
messy having six items from over here
and only one item from over here. I'll
remove that and just duplicate my
Discord node just like this. So now set
fields puts out all the info.
Say hey here is what you need to know
today.
Then over here here is how the internet
is doing. Let's
try it out. Let's check our internet.
Look. Oh, there we go. That's so cursed.
And then let's execute our um news
articles. Let's check it out. Oh, we
forgot our link. Got to have the link in
there.
Much better. Now, we're going to start
going faster here, but let's add some
more news. Let's say YouTube videos. And
did you know that every YouTube channel
has their own RSS feed? So, check this
out. I'm going to add a new node for set
fields. We're going to set some
information here and we're going to put
this at the root of our flow here. We're
going to add a field called channel IDs.
We're going to make this an array which
will be a list of items and it's going
to be a list of YouTube channel IDs.
We'll grab a few. So, let's go grab
mine, which you can find a channel ID
from going to more and going to share
channel and copy channel ID there. Let's
go find David Bombell
and Tyler Ramsby. All great friends.
This way, you're not relying on the
stupid YouTube notification system. So,
now our array will look like this. When
I execute this, boom, clean list. Now,
here's what I'm going to do. I'm going
to add just after this an RSS read. To
find an RSS feed for any YouTube
channel, it's going to be like this.
Blah blah blah channel ID equals. And
we're just going to add in at the end of
that the channel IDs.
So notice it filled it in the variable
over here. Oh, wait. Do you see what's
happening? Oh, no. It's taking it as one
object and putting it all in there at
the same time. I've got a fix for that.
You're learning some serious data
manipulation here in N. What we have to
do, notice it's spitting out one item.
One item right here. We need to have
that spit out as many items as there is
YouTube channel IDs. So, we're going to
add another node in between called split
out, not Splunk. And yes, you can do
Splunk stuff. Split out based on channel
IDs. Execute. Boom. Three items kicked
out. Perfect. Now it's working. Awesome.
So, if we execute the step for the RSS
read one, we'll change that to YouTube
channels. It's going to go grab some
YouTube videos and their links. And we
got 45 videos to watch. We don't need
that many. What do you say we filter it?
Let's filter by the ISO date. So, this
will be essentially when the video is
published. Let's grab that. Put it in
there. Now, notice it's like the time as
well. And we don't really need to filter
off the time. All I care about is the
day. So, I'm going to use some fancy
expression like this that'll just grab
the year, month, date. Now, again, I'm
no wizard with this. This is just chat
GPT. Hey, how do I do this really
quickly? And I'll say is the publish
date after or equal to? And we'll put in
3 days from now. again with some uh AI
magic. Cool. Notice how it's changing to
July 1st for that particular date and
then June 29th. Let's see how many
videos are within the last three days.
Eight. Cool. So, we've filtered it down
to eight. Our output looks okay. And
then let's add another Discord node and
edit what data we want to see.
Perfect. Let's try it out. And now we
have videos being delivered to our inbox
or to Discord. Now, we're going to have
to stop here because this video could
probably go on forever. I could sit here
and do this with you for a long time.
I'm going to save my stuff. Going to
zoom out for a second. And I just want
to point out a few things. First, what
we did here was not crazy complicated,
but it is powerful. And what I wanted to
hit home was the building blocks of N8.
My goal was to get you going, "Oh, I can
do that with the AI agent. I can execute
these commands. Oh, oh, I could do this
and that. Like, I want you to be just
brimming with ideas and I want to see
those in the comments. Think about this
food for thought because this is what
I'm going to build based on this instead
of just spitting out articles. Maybe you
have an AI rate the articles based on
your personal preference and rank them
and maybe the AI will tell you, hey, you
should definitely read this article or
don't waste your time with this. Maybe
it can go through a YouTube videos, look
at the comments, read the transcript,
summarize when you really don't need to
watch the entire video, or have it tell
you, "This video is a must. You have to
watch the entire thing." Like that kind
of thing. Having this crazy automated
news aggregator is totally possible with
this tool. And that's just one idea. And
by the way, I did kind of build this
already. I wanted to show this to you in
the video in this video, but I just
didn't have any time. But in the next
video, because there is something I want
to cover beyond this, I want to show you
something I teased in the beginning.
It's more around this workflow here,
executing commands and having AI analyze
your commands because N has one powerful
thing I haven't shown you yet. It's with
AI. I'm going to add one more AI thing
here. It's the AI agent. I'm just going
to put him out in the middle here. Let's
zoom in on him. Notice he's like the LLM
block, but he has a few more things
going on. He's got memory and tools.
What does that mean? Check this out. I'm
going to add for the chat model just
open AI. Cool. Then for the tool, I'm
going to add command line. And the
command will be ping networkchuck.com
for four pings. I'll describe it. This
is how you check if the
website is up. I'll add another tool.
Let's do another command
and say ping10.77.14.30
for three pings.
This is how you see if Terry is up. And
now I'm going to add a trigger for this
AI agent. It'll be a chat trigger. I'll
connect it right here. I'm going to open
the chat and I'm going to say, "Hey, is
the internet up?"
It's using chat GBT. It's going to use
one of our tools. It's using both for
some reason. Look at that. So, that's
pretty cool. I can say things like,
"Hey, is Terry up?" It's only going to
one thing. Terry, are you seeing this?
This is a simple example. We can connect
this whole thing to our whole home lab.
That's the next video. That's all I got.
I'll catch you guys next time.