Notions new layout Builder is seriously
my favorite feature of the year and if
you work with complex databases that
have a lot of different properties I
think you're going to agree with me
because now we can take those properties
and put them in a side panel that's very
easily shown or hidden with a keyboard
shortcut and there's a ton of
customization options as well we can
create specific sections for groups of
properties collapse sections if we don't
want to see certain properties and my
favorite we can actually pin properties
underneath the page title and they show
horizontally which means that the all
important content on the page body like
the video script for this video isn't
pushed a th000 miles beneath the fold
and when I open it up in s side peek I
can see it immediately so in this video
I'm going to teach you everything you
need to know about Notions new layout
Builder feature this is a free feature
anybody can use it in any notion
workspace and it's a feature that is
specific to database views like the
older tools we used to have for
customizing database pages when you use
layout Builder you're going to be
creating a custom layout that's going to
apply to every single page in a database
like this one if I have 500 pages in
this content database all of my changes
are going to applied to all of those
pages so what I'm going to do is first
give you a really quick tour of the
layout that I've built for this content
database and then we have another copy
of this database that I actually want to
go through and customize to basically
look like this one so looking through
this little layout Builder here first
and foremost I'm going to do command
backs slash to get rid of that sidebar
here we essentially have this nice
little side panel and the first thing
I'm going to point out is my favorite
little keyboard shortcut here if you're
in a full screen mode you can do command
shift back backlash or control shift
backslash to basically dismiss this
little property panel if you want to
open it you can use the exact same
keyboard shortcut just like that but
there are also a couple of other ways to
do it we have this little view details
icon up in the top right corner of the
UI right here and then if you have
pinned properties and I'm going to tell
you about those a little bit later you
have this little three dot icon which
will also open up all of the other
properties and let you view them if you
don't have any pin properties you're
just going to see view details right
here and that also applies to the mobile
app which I can quickly show you right
here if I open up my notion app and then
open up a page I'm going to see this
little view details link right beneath
the page title I can click that and I'm
going to see all the properties on
mobile just like that moving into the
actual property panel here you can see
that we actually have the ability to
create multiple sections of properties
so here I have a general details section
and I can collapse it if I want to I
have one for relations like this new
repurposing relation in creators
companion 3.0 which allows us to add
repurposed projects like shorts or
podcasts or live streams that are maybe
related to a sort of parent piece of
content and we have sponsorship details
and these sections make it really easy
to see only the properties that you want
to see in a specific context so if I'm
planning a piece of content right here I
can very easily see my media type
property I can see my description I can
assign writers and editors if I'm
working with a sponsored piece of
content I can come right down here and
set all my sponsorship details like the
sponsorship rate the URL that they want
me to link people people to Etc it's all
nicely parceled out here last but not
least we have this pinned property
section and this allows you to pin up to
four properties which get laid out in a
horizontal manner when there is actually
enough room for it and again this just
ensures that the actual page content the
stuff on the body of the page is not
tucked so far beneath the fold which is
really nice for when you want to quickly
access it I also want to point out that
this works really well in side peek mode
in fact this makes side Peak mode even
more amazing it's always been my
favorite way to interact with notion but
now I think it is like the way to do it
so I'm going to zoom out just a couple
of ticks here I'm usually very zoomed in
for YouTube videos but if I pop into
this notion formulas at five levels of
complexity video at the level of Zoom I
would normally work in I've got really
really easy access to all of my script
or outline details if I want to go into
another page in this project I can very
easily go into that page right ins side
Peak also Pro tip I can use command back
bracket or control back bracket on
Windows to go back I can also do uh
forward with the forward bracket command
just like that so this kind of gives me
access to the entire project in side
Peak mode and all of my properties are
right here now because we're a little
bit more horizontally constrained I've
got the property name actually stacking
on top of the property value here but I
have very very easy access to everything
and if I want to close it now I've got
more room to actually work with my
script or my outline I absolutely love
this and the fact that list views are
actually responsive so when I open side
peek it's sort of scrunches down like
this means that this is essentially a
pan that is useful still but separate
from this pan and if I want to go into
another video project I can very very
easily do that so let's quickly jump
into this other database that I'm
working in because we haven't actually
done the layout customization in this
database so I'm going to use uh this
customization job to actually show you
how to do all this in layout Builder so
in any page in a database if you hover
over the page title you're going to see
this customized layout button if you
don't see it it means your database is
locked and I'll have a link in the
description down below with a post on
how to unlock databases it's really easy
but if you click this you enter this
brand new experience that allows you to
customize the layout for all the pages
in this database and if you want to use
a different page for the preview you
actually now have this little preview
option up here and you can choose a
different page in the database if you
want to uh which just makes things
really really easy when you're wanting
to make sure things look really good for
all different types of Pages you can
even as you see here choose templates in
the database in addition to regular
pages so I'm just going to keep uh with
this notion formulas at five levels as
I've got a cover image here and that's
just going to make things a little bit
easier for us to work with so the first
thing I'm going to point out is this
here is the property group and this is
sort of like the traditional area where
properties typically live and if you
want to you can click this little three
dot menu here and you can move this to
the panel just like that you already
have improved things because now your
page body is not so far beneath the fold
and all of your properties are here in
the property group the next thing I'd
like to point out is this section over
here because I have the property group
selected currently this is sort of
dedicated to customizing that property
group I can change all the visibility
settings for my properties I can add
sections which I'll talk about in a
second but if I click another group like
this heading group over here my options
over here change a little bit in this
case I can pin properties which I'll
show in just a second and when we create
more sections later on the uh area over
here is going to be customized to those
sections if we click on them so the
first thing I think I want to do is
create different sections inside of this
property group so let's make one for
General Properties by clicking add
section right here I'm just going to
call this General properties and now all
the properties inside the property group
are nested inside of this General
properties section next let's create
another one I'm going to call this one
sponsorship properties and now if we
have any properties that are dedicated
to working with sponsors like sponsor
rate we can easily move these up into
this section
and that's how we can start to organize
all these different properties in our
database so I'm going to go ahead and
move pay du date there we'll move
sponsor performance as well and one
small nitpick that I'll point out here
is that moving properties doesn't
actually scroll things vertically as I
think it should especially if you have a
lot of properties so that's one thing I
would like to see notion fix but now
I've got my sponsorship properties here
in the sponsorship property section I'm
also going to create a section for
helper properties and this is going to
hold basically any propert properties
that sort of run my template but are not
really that useful for users to actually
see so in fact I might be better served
by putting that down there uh and we'll
go ahead and put things like task meta
localization key uh YouTube chapters all
these kind of readon properties that
really don't need to even be read that
often we'll put them down here typically
these are going to be properties that
are viewed in other views and notion
like say a gallery view or a list view
they don't need to be viewed here uh and
if they are in a helper property section
we can very easily keep this entire
section toggled closed most of the time
and it's just going to stay out of the
way and reduce visual clutter and that
also frees us up to do something that I
generally didn't do in my previous
notion templates and that's basically
make all properties that you could
potentially write to or edit visible by
default so right now we have this media
type property where you can uh label
something as like a short or long form
or a stream this currently is always
hidden and normally with these kind of
properties I would often say hide when
empty just to again reduce visual
clutter when there's nothing in there
but now because this is in the panel I'm
just going to set it to always show and
that way if you want to set that you're
going to see it by default and you're
not going to have to click this 17 more
properties button right here to reveal
it I'm going to do the same thing for
pretty much all of these properties here
and while I'm thinking about it paid
should probably go up in the sponsor uh
section but all of these should just be
visible by default that way I just have
much much quicker access to them if I
happen to need to edit them from this
page page so jumping forward a little
bit I now have my sponsorship property
section General section I've created a
more relations section stat property
section right here and then finally our
helper property section where everything
is hidden by default the next thing I
want to do is actually break one of
these properties out into its own
section so if I go to my files property
right here I can actually click it and
if I want I can add it to my layout and
this is going to give it its own section
in our layout Builder Now by default
it's going to go beneath our heading but
if we want to we can also move it over
to the panel just like this and then if
we want to move it above our other
properties we can move it up like that
or we can drag it and drop it if we had
more room now files in particular is a
property that I really like to have
broken out into its own sort of group
here and I'm going to go ahead and apply
this to all pages so I can show you on
my demo copy here if I go to uh this
other version that we have and we go
ahead and show our details here we can
see that files has actually been kind of
redesigned to show images in this much
more beautiful layout with rounded
Corners uh and there are actually some
other properties that have some specific
styling that has been applied to them
when you show them as their own property
if we go into this little image uh
database item here this is basically a
database that just has every single
property type in it for testing we can
also show numbers in large format and we
can show people properties in large
format as well if and only if they are
broken out into their own groups and I
expect we'll probably see some more
special design uh options for other
property types in in the future right
now as you can see basically every other
property type looks more or less like it
does when it's just in the property
group so I don't see a huge reason to
break these out into their own sections
but again uh person properties number
properties and especially file
properties look really really good if we
break them out just like this okay
heading back to our uh actual layout
that we're building here I'm going to go
back to customize layout the next thing
that I want to do now that I have my
files group up here where I want it is I
want to go into the heading area and I
want to pin some of the properties that
I'm going to use most often so basically
when I come into uh a page in notion
there's usually going to be some
properties that I'm always going to edit
like the status of the video the publish
date of the video and with the pinned
properties uh section here we can make
those really really easy to get to so
let's use the search bar right here
search for status uh and one thing that
I wish would happen is that it would
actually filter all these instead of
just highlighting them but it is a
pretty easy way still to find it so I'm
going to go ahead and pin status just
like that I'm going to find my publish
date property pin it there as well and
we have a couple of other slots because
we can do at most four pinned properties
right now so let's also go with the
channel relation and finally let's find
the url uh property as well so these I
think are going to be the most often
edited and also most often accessed
clicked on properties in this specific
content planning database so now they
are pinned I'm going to be able to see
them much more easily than I would
otherwise see them them here in the
property group so let's talk about
relations now last year notion released
a feature where you could display
relations in this little section beneath
the page header and that is still
present in the layout Builder but it's a
little bit hard to access and I do think
notion should improve this but I want to
cover in this video just so you know
exactly how to do it so if you want to
show relation property down here you
need to find it in the property group
and let's go with a sponsor and also
Focus keywords and tasks for this
demonstration first you need to click
this property and I think I'll try to
zoom just a couple more ticks to make
this really really easy to see and click
add to layout right here so this is
essentially going to make this relation
property its own section just like we
showed with the files property but now
that we have done this we can now click
this little three dot menu on this
section and there's this little Advanced
menu where we can click convert to
relations group that is how you get the
relations down here and it's also how
you enable yourself to minimally display
relation properties so now that I have
it here I can see this relation group
and I can see all the relations in it
and if I click one of them I have this
show as option and right now it's going
to show as a page section so if I added
a sponsor I would actually see that
sponsor here and I could actually show
properties from that sponsor which can
be pretty useful but in the case of this
template I want to keep the sponsor
minimal so you'd have to actually click
into it to see it uh so I'm going to go
here and I'm going to show this as a
minimal property again I think notion
really should improve this previously
you could see all of your relation
properties and you could see all all of
their display statuses without having to
click into them now I have to click into
each one go to show as and check it
there I think that's a bit of a
regression so hopefully they improve
that after this video comes out uh but
to finish this up instead of me just
complaining all day I'm going to go
ahead and do the same thing for these
other two properties first add to layout
then click the three do menu here go to
Advanced and add this to the relations
group and finally set this to minimal so
now that I have All My Relations there
let's go ahead and apply this to all the
pages in the database and I can show you
how this works so if I add a sponsor
right here let's see if we have a
sponsor we've got sponsor 2 I'm getting
big bucks from sponsor 2 over here if I
add that I'm just going to have one
sponsor and if I want to see who it is I
can click into this little picker here
and I can see that sponsor if I want to
I can click this little customize shown
properties button and I can also show uh
properties from this sponsor database so
let's just do uh pay structure and maybe
let's do status um I think that would be
pretty useful for sponsors uh and if I
wanted to I could also go back into
customize layout and if I always wanted
to see those sponsor details without
having to click into them I could change
this from show as to as page relation
just like that apply that to all pages
and now you can see without having to
click into that little minimal link I
see the sponsor right on the page just
like this now in addition to all these
specific property groups that we've been
playing with in this video there are
also some more Universal options that we
can set and there's a couple of places
to find them so if you go into the
heading area right here and you scroll
all the way down past all of your
properties you now have the show
backlinks option down here and I think
they put it there because now the
backlinks link is above the page title
previously I think it was down here so I
guess that kind of makes sense it's a
little bit hard to find in my opinion
but that's where it is uh and for all
the other options there's this little
slider icon next to your database name
so if you click that that's how you get
access to all of your page settings so
you can make inline comments show wide
like this or minimal which is my
preference you can show page discussions
and have an actual section for it like
that or you can turn it off again that's
typically my preference and then
something new you can actually turn off
property icons and that does actually
make things look a little bit cleaner so
if you're the kind of person who is a
bit more of a minimalist that might be
the setting for you finally if you did
all of this work you spent a bunch of
time customizing your layout and then
your boss is like hey I hate it don't
apply it I don't like it you don't
actually have to go back and manually
reset everything back to scratch you can
click the little blue arrow here and
reset this to the original page layout
if you want to I'm not going to do that
because I think my handiwork is
absolutely beautiful here except for one
thing I actually don't want to show my
back links so I'm going to go ahead and
turn that off then I'm going to apply to
all pages and now that we are done and
go ahead and do my command shift back
slsh shortcut one more time I'm going to
do a little bit of complaining about
this feature like I said this is maybe
my favorite feature release of the year
I know there were some technically
bigger ones that were announced at make
with notion this is my favorite but it's
not perfect so I want to go over three
little nitpicks that I hope anyone from
the notion team watching this video
takes to heart when they're doing
improvements first and foremost this
shortcut command shift back slash works
when you have the page fully open but
watch what happens if I open up a page
in side peek once again I'm going to go
back just a couple of ticks so I have
more room on the screen if I open this
up here it doesn't work so I have to
move my mouse like someone from the the
1800s oh so much labor and that just
takes I again so much labor like I
already went to the gym today I don't
want to have to move my mouse anymore
than I absolutely have to when I'm at
work so please dear notion make that
keyboard shortcut work in side Peak okay
complaint number two while I really
really like the way that files display
in their new sort of uh dedicated
property like right here I really wish
they had better handling for different
aspect ratios so for example if I go
into my book tracker in the brand new
Ultimate brain 3.0 which is actually
coming out at the end of this month by
the way um if I put a book cover in this
image property right here which I can
actually demonstrate for you it's just
not going to look that good once it
uploads because a book cover is quite a
tall image and this just has a fixed
aspect ratio we also have the exact same
problem with cover images if I upload
this as a cover image it's again not
going to look very good it will look
pretty good here in Gallery views like
that looks pretty good to me and I wish
that this was an option right here
either make this tall to actually match
the aspect ratio of the book image or at
the very least squash the book image
into this fixed height box so I can see
the entire thing instead of only being
able to see a slice of it now this isn't
the biggest issue in the world I can
click this to see the actual image just
like that it's not really a huge deal
but it would just look absolutely
beautiful if it actually respected those
aspect ratios finally complaint number
three I really wish we could create
multiple property groups so earlier in
the video I showed you how you can
create sections for your properties and
if I go back to a more complicated
database like this one you can see these
different sections here we can collapse
them that works pretty well but I really
wish that we could take a section that
we created in the property group and
split it out into its own section that
lives somewhere else now I know that we
can take individual properties and we
can split those out and we can put them
say over here but I think it would be
really really useful to be able to
create a nice compact section of
properties and maybe put it over here or
maybe have your nice little files
property on its own with its nice little
beautiful display in the middle of our
general details and our more relations
right there currently we can't do that
because everything in the property group
is in the property group and you can't
split a section out into its own
separate group so I really hope that
that becomes an additional feature we
have access to in the future now I know
the question on a lot of your minds is
hey Tom do your notion templates
actually support this new customized
layout feature and the answer is by the
end of this month yes if I pop back over
to my screen share you can see this is
the new version of ultimate brain it's
got this really slick and simple single
column workflow that I'm really enjoying
personally and when I open up my task
manager just like this all of my task
properties are in this nice little side
panel I've got recurring task properties
in their own group I can collapse that
if I want to not see them and everything
is just much much easier to access than
it was before so uh a little bit of a
PSA if you already have a copy of
ultimate brain If You' bought one in the
past we actually have a new beta space
in our Circle customer Community we
aren't fully launching these templates
as like a public launch until near the
end of this month for Black Friday but
if you already bought a copy you got
access to the beta now and the beta is
feature complete we're just working on
our tutorials and documentation so
anybody who wants to can customize their
templates using those tutorials in the
near future otherwise if you haven't
gotten your own copy yet either of
ultimate brain for personal productivity
task management note-taking all that
good stuff or Creator's companion the
exact system I use and showed off in
this video for planning all my YouTube
content and social media content you can
find links to both of those templates in
the description down below it's also a
great way to support the work I'm doing
on this channel if you want to learn
notion we have a great page over on my
website called thomasj frank.com
fundamentals also in the description
down below for those who like to click
mice instead of typing things in their
URL search bar that is where you can
find our notion Basics lessons as well
as a place to sign up for my notion tips
newsletter and beyond that there's a
couple of videos here and here that you
might find useful specifically this one
which is on another recently released
notion feature thanks for watching