oh my would you look at the time it's
new feature time so welcome back to the
thomas prank explains video today we are
going over
four brand new features that launched in
notion today
wednesday november 11th 2020 which is
almost certainly not the day i'm gonna
get this video out since i spend so much
time
positioning llamas on sets and all kinds
of other stuff but
in this video i'm gonna walk you through
these four features which include
number one and most excitingly the
timeline view for databases so for
anybody out there who wants to create
gantt charts this is going to be very
interesting for you
but personally the other three features
that launch today while they're a little
bit more subtle a little bit less
worthy of confetti for most people are
actually more exciting for me
these are things that i've been waiting
for for a very long time and they
include number one the ability to
customize what properties are shown on
pages
both regular pages and database pages
which means no more scrolling through
huge lists of properties for big
databases before you get to what you
actually want to see
i've been waiting for that for so long
number two the ability to change the
sharing settings on sub pages which
means they no longer have to be forced
to inherit the sharing settings of their
parent pages
really really useful and number three
small tweak but something i've been
wanting for quite a while
the ability to limit the number of rows
that are shown on inline databases so if
you have a huge database with hundreds
of rows
you can decide to see maybe only 10 or
20 on the first load when you're
creating like
maybe a dashboard for yourself so let's
roll that intro let's head on over to
the green screen computer view and i'm
going to show you in detail
each of these features
alrighty welcome to my new and improved
screen view
now there's no box or i guess circle
around my face cam so we're going to go
through these four features i'm going to
show you what they can do
talk a little bit about their
limitations and show you how you can
sort of
integrate them into your workspace and
edit your workspace
using them and we are going to start out
with the one that everyone is most
excited about but also the one that has
the most controversy which is
this timeline view here the reason
there's a little bit of controversy is
that
at launch notion decided to make this a
bit of a limited feature if you're on
the free plan
then you can only have three of these
timeline views if you're on a team plan
you can have five if you're on
enterprise you can have
unlimited so i wanted to integrate this
into my ultimate tasks template but if
you watch my videos on that you will
know
that we have a projects area here where
you can basically spawn an instance of a
project template
and you could have as many of these as
you want well problem being with these
timeline limitations if you have a bunch
of different projects every single one
of your timeline views in here
is going to be limited so i'll talk a
little bit about this later but what
i've done instead is add a timeline view
to ultimate tasks where you have a
single timeline and you can switch
projects just by changing
your filter but i want to show you sort
of how to build this from scratch
because right now we're looking at a lot
of stuff
so let's just look at this little
timeline test database that i've created
here
by default we have our table view and i
have a
video project that has several different
steps filming a video creating an egg
cut
we got our done check boxes we have our
due dates and if we want to
see all this on a timeline view we can
just click out of view and we can click
timeline now remember if you wanted to
save your filters and sorts from this
view you'd create a null view and then
you'd copy
this one you do that whole thing i talk
about that in my ultimate tasks build
video which i'll have linked in the
description down below we're just going
to create a timeline view
from scratch and by default we get all
of our items here in a table view and
then to the right we have the timeline
view
you can hide this table view if you want
and on mobile it's going to be hidden by
default
you will see a little bit later why
sometimes it may not be a good idea to
have
this hidden so with timeline view what
we can do is actually
stretch these out and give them all
specific
time frames and we can also adjust the
window that we're looking at so right
now by default we're looking at a
month-long timeline and if we create new
pages with this month view we're going
to create
a five day long project right here so
let's call this a five day project
and if we switch we've got several
different options here we have hours
days
weeks biweekly etc and by switching
these
views we also switch the amount of time
that new pages are going to be scheduled
for by default so if we're on hourly
view
you can see 9 30 to 10 30 we're gonna
get an hour block for any new
object here so if you're trying to map
out your day this could be a useful
window of time to view it in
if we go to our week view well then new
pages are going to be
simply one day so get to know how these
affect your default project durations
and figure out which one works best for
you in certain situations
now one thing you're going to notice by
default we can click here and look and
we can timeline by
by default we are simply timelining by a
specific
property in this case our due date
property
and when we stretch these out if we go
back over to our table view you will
notice
that we now have start and end dates for
this do property right here
this is a little bit problematic for
people using my ultimate tasks template
and for people who are generally using
due dates in
in general and i'll show you why if i go
ahead and filter
this where do is on or before
today well if i create
a new task and we'll just call this new
task it's due date is set to today
if i go over to the timeline view and i
stretch this out
well now the end date of the task is
november 16th
and the beginning date is november 12th
so in effect
the real due date is november 16th but
notion doesn't target the end date
of a date property when you're doing
filtering so if we go back over to table
we're going to see it here as if it was
due today on november 12th
for that reason i would recommend using
timeline view in a
slightly different way where instead of
timelining by a single property
you come over here and you choose to use
separate start
and end dates so now we can set the
start date as
start and we can set the end date as do
which is pretty sweet so now you can see
and if we go over to our table view we
can see that this end
date on the do property is now being
essentially ignored
so if we back over in the timeline view
start stretching things out
now we're going to see that for this one
publish and share
our start date has been set to november
14th and our due date has been set
to november 16th which is pretty nice
and as always you can do your sorting
and you're filtering so maybe we sort
by uh start date here in ascending order
so as we start creating our timeline
we're going to see it
in the order we really kind of want it
so actually publish and share should
probably be
after do the final edit gather b-row
items would be
before do the final edit and i could go
out and i could basically create a
timeline for my project right here
uh some other things you can do with
timeline view if you have enabled this
table view which you can hide by just
clicking here
or showing then you are able to display
properties
independently from the table and the
timeline so maybe on the timeline i want
the
done checkbox but i don't want it in the
table because i don't want it gunking
stuff up here
now i can see this and personally you
know if you've watched my other videos
you know i typically get rid of items
that are done with filtering but i think
on a timeline view i would want to see
my my done projects or my done tasks in
addition to the ones that are still
undone
so instead of getting rid of them i
would probably just leave them there and
be able to see when they're checked so i
do think that
timelining by a separate start and end
date property is a good idea however
there is
one slight problem with it which is that
if we have tasks like this one here
that just has let's actually strip this
start date off of here because when you
click it it's going to
throw a start date on there but if we
just have a due date
we can see it here list up b-roll ideas
it's got just a due date but if i hide
this table view
it's going to hide any item that doesn't
also have a start view
so right now i consider this feature to
be one that has some compromises
i i think it's got some some tweaks that
i could get from the notion team to be
really great
but in the meantime i think it's pretty
useful for
mapping out a project that has task
dependencies or mapping out a project
where you want to see
when things should start when they
should end and how that all works and
this could be really really useful if
you're running
a team now i did mention that i added
this into ultimate tasks
so if you are using my ultimate tasks
template then you will now notice that
there is a
timeline view here on the views list and
again the reason i did this is because
the people on the free plan are limited
to three timelines at present
moment so instead of building it into
the project template
i've just created a view or you can come
in and you can simply change your filter
criteria to target
a different project and uh to use up
your three timelines you could just
duplicate
this view a couple of times or duplicate
the entire page if this changes in the
future if notion
removes these limitations then i will
absolutely build timeline view
into ultimate tasks into the project
templates but
for now i think this is kind of like an
in-between solution
so from there let's move on to the next
feature
and these next three features that we're
going to talk about i actually find
more exciting than timeline view i know
they're not as flashy but they're things
that i've been waiting for for a very
very long time
the first one is the ability to
customize what you
see on individual pages and database
pages this is something that i've been
wanting for a very long time
and let me just show you uh an example
of why this is so useful
so if we go over to our content area
this is where i plan out all my youtube
videos
and we look at all the videos that are
associated with my thomas frank channel
and let's just find one that i've
already done here how to figure out what
to do with your life
usually in the past when i would open up
a page
because i have so many properties in
this database i would have to scroll
past all these properties to get to the
stuff that i was actually looking for
like my script area my publishing
checklist all that stuff
but if you'll notice i now have this
little button hide26 properties and when
i load this by default
all those properties are hidden and the
way you can do this is by going up to
the little three dot menu here
and hitting customize page and when you
hit customize page you're going to have
some options here for every property in
a database you can choose to always show
it
always hide it or hide it when it is
empty
so you can sort of create a customized
view for yourself here
and notice that when you're doing this
for a database page you pick a single
page in the database you make your
customizations
but they affect all pages within that
database so you don't gotta go do it for
every single page in the database which
is pretty nice
in addition to these property hiding and
showing options
you can choose to show your page
comments in certain ways and your
backlinks in certain ways
so for page comments if i turn them off
well there's no page comments here if i
turn them expanded
then if i add a comment to a page like
so
it's going to be shown by default now
this does not affect comments that are
added to specific lines of text but it
does affect the comments that are at the
top of the page here
so if you want to see these you can have
them like that otherwise you can go over
to customize page and choose to
turn them off same for backlinks but i'm
actually going to go to a different area
of my workspace to show you how that
works
so if i go over to our company knowledge
base
then we've got three backlinks right
here and by default i'm seeing these
in a popover which is my preferred way
to see these backlinks
but if i wanted to i can come up here
and i can choose to customize the page
and either expand them so i see them all
by default
or completely turn them off and let me
show you where
completely turning them off can be
actually pretty useful so we've got our
video workflow tutorial here which
contains
several different checklists and these
checklists
are sort of master checklists that are
within our wiki they're great for
reference
but our video project template actually
creates
copies of this master checklist so you
can check them off as you go through a
specific project without making changes
to the master and as you can see we've
got 38
backlinks and these are all different
video projects
with their own copy of the filming
checklist but here in the wiki
i don't really care to see this i don't
need to know how many projects are
backlinking here and i certainly don't
need to load a zillion of them
so here would be a great place for me to
simply
turn backlinks off and now i've got this
clean
simple filming checklist that i can come
make changes to
so that is pretty cool and that is
basically a primer on
customizing your pages again it's been
something that i've been wanting for a
really long time so i'm pretty happy to
see this in notion
and the next feature is another thing
that i've been wanting which is
granular sharing permissions you can now
change the sharing settings of subpages
even if they are different from that of
their parent page so in the past if we
go back to knowledge base here
whatever sharing settings i set for this
parent page
would propagate down to every subpage
and you couldn't change that which is
kind of a bummer
so let's say you know i've got everyone
in my company has access to this
knowledge base
but maybe i don't want to give everyone
in my company access to this sponsor
list here
well in the past i was just kind of out
of luck there but now if i want to i can
go ahead
and remove access to my workspace like
so
and then by default i'm going to get
full access because it's me
and if i wanted to add somebody else
like i know martin needs full access to
our sponsor database
and i know that my editor tony at least
needs view access so i can actually do
granular permissions like that i'm going
to give full access to martin
and then i'm going to give tony
view access to our sponsor database so
this is really really
powerful you can now create these sort
of granular permission trees
there are some limitations though so let
me go over to my
notes that i wrote out for this video
here
and i had a page set up where i wanted
to sort of show
uh some of these limitations but before
we do that i do want to show you one
other use case where these permissions
can be very
very helpful so we have a team
workspaces area
for each person in my company they all
have their own dashboards and if we look
at mine here
again in the past your permission
settings were sort of set in stone
and they sort of were based on the
parent page so everyone in my company
would have the ability to edit this
dashboard and i don't really want to do
that
what i really would want to do is for my
own dashboard
only let myself and maybe the manager of
our company have full access to it and
then everyone else can view it
and if we go to someone else's workspace
like martin's
well only he would want to have full
access to it and we only want
view access for everyone else so this is
great for if you're running a team if
you want to build dashboards for people
you can now create smarter edit access
to those dashboards
so let's go back to some of those
limitations i was talking about when
this feature launched the thing i
immediately thought of was okay can we
now
share linked database views that have
specific filters
without sharing the master database and
why would you want to do this well if
you had a master tasks database with
multiple people on a team
you might want to only show a team
member the tasks assigned to them
and you can create a filtered view to do
that but they can always just strip the
filter off or go to the master database
if they want to see every task so if
you're trying to restrict view access
or restrict edit access my immediate
thought was this is going to enable that
unfortunately it doesn't quite do that
uh if i have this embedded linked view
of a restricted task manager database
and i share this page with certain
people
but i do not share this page then what's
going to happen is
this page is going to be just blank
they're not going to be able to see it
so
right now you still do need to share
some kind of access to your master
databases to anybody who wants to see
them
but you can do some useful things so for
instance i have this alternate email
which is a guest of my workspace and it
has
view access to this entire database here
so
if i was logged in in this alternate
account i would still be able to see
every single task in this database
but what i can do is give this database
only view access
and then on a case-by-case basis i could
make say a task or a project for that
alternate account
and i can create full access permissions
and i can actually show you if i bring
this up in a browser
logged in with my alternate account i've
got a filtered view here which i cannot
edit because it's only view access
and i can only see tasks assigned to me
but this task has been given full edit
access
for this account so i can now interact
with it i can add text
inside of it so it's a little bit
tedious because you have to add these
page sharing settings on a case-by-case
basis i've tested templates and they do
not work
if you create a template with specific
sharing settings but they don't match
the sharing settings of the database
when you create an instance of that
template
the instance is going to take on the
databases sharing settings so that
doesn't work right now
but you could at least i mean maybe for
a big project template
you could create an instance of it and
you could change the sharing settings so
somebody on your team
has full edit access and they can come
in here my other wishlist item is
if you look here i can check this at
leisure but if i look at it from the
database view where i only have edit
access
i can't really do anything with it so i
would like that to be updated
at least but i think we're going to see
a lot of updates coming in the future
so that's sharing settings and we have
one more feature to talk about
really small feature it's going to be
something that doesn't take very much
time at all to talk about but
once again it's something that i have
been wanting for a very very long time
which is the ability to limit the number
of rows that are loaded
in an inline database view so let's go
back over to my content area where i can
show you how this works
again if we go over to my youtube
channels page here
uh i have a lot of youtube videos i've
made but
when i load this database view i'm only
seeing the first ten
and that's really really nice because
again there's like oh actually there's
221 we can look at the
the count here and if we're loading all
221 number one we have a ton
of stuff here but also here's not a
great place to show it because i have
nothing
under it but if i go over to my personal
workspace right now i don't have a ton
of tasks in this little task area but if
i had
tons of tasks assigned to me then i
might want to limit the number that are
loaded
at first load otherwise everything else
down here that i might want to look at
is going to get pushed down and i got to
scroll past it
which could especially be a pain on the
mobile app so
if we go back here i can show you how
this works if we look at the three dot
menu of this uh
this database and this works for regular
inline databases but also linked
database views
then we can go to the properties area
here and we can choose to show on first
load
a specific number of pages we can do all
of them we can do 100 of them or we can
just do 10 of them and of course after
the first load if you want to see more
you can just come down here and click
this load 50 more button to your heart's
content if you need to find something
older so again super quick feature but i
think it's going to be very very useful
it's a nice quality of life upgrade for
a lot of people
and that is going to do it for this
overview video hopefully this struck a
balance between being thorough enough to
show you sort of the
limitations and details of all these
features but also
uh short enough that it's not the half
an hour version that i first recorded
before i had to redo this video if you
enjoyed this video hit the like button
on youtube make sure you're subscribed
to this channel for more notion
tutorials coming in the future
and if you want to get all my templates
including my ultimate tasks template
which now has
this timeline view in it you can go over
to thomasjfrank.com
templates and you'll also have the
opportunity to sign up for my notion
tips newsletter
which will let you know all about new
templates that i create new content that
i create tutorials
all kinds of stuff build guides and all
kinds of cool stuff coming up in the
future i've got courses i'm working on
so i think you'll find it very very
helpful if you're trying to get the most
out of notion uh beyond that if you have
questions
let me know on twitter i'm at tomfrankly
over there or
leave them in the comments down below
your questions number one i try to
answer as many as i can in the comments
number two questions are great at giving
me ideas for future content so if you've
got something you want to see me cover
let me know about it and i think that is
about going to do it
for this video i don't have any other
weird calls to action to talk about
so let's just cut to that stupid clip
that i always put at the end