well hello there and welcome back to
Thomas Frank explains so notion just
launched a brand new formulas language
they're calling formulas 2.0 it is
massively more powerful than the
original formulas language and in this
video we are going to dive kind of into
the deep end and I'm going to show you
how to build something that was
completely impossible with formulas 1.0
and also something that I actually got a
lot of requests for so I'm very excited
that we can build this now so let's jump
in and I'm going to show you what we're
going to build and then this is going to
be kind of a nice introduction and kind
of a crash course into how to use some
of the more advanced functions of
formulas 2.0 so here I've got my own
copy of creators companion which is my
notion template for managing my YouTube
and blog content and I've got a nice
little YouTube tab now that shows me the
top three videos for each of my YouTube
channels with their view counts I also
have a link directly to the notion page
for that project and I can even click
the link and go right to the video on
YouTube itself so this is what we're
going to be building today but before we
start I'm want to show you one other
example because the code behind this
formula which looks complex now but
don't you worry we're going to go very
very step by step through it is actually
quite applicable to other use cases for
example here I've got a stores database
here and then for each of these stores I
have my sales by the day of the week so
now I can tell that quality Comics has
is making on average 3 300 bucks on
Mondays it's making 4 700 bucks on
Thursdays and that is pulling from a
sales database where I have individual
sale records per store from Gus's games
and wave table synths all these cool
made up store names and now we can
basically roll up that information in a
highly customized way so we're going to
start building this and we're going to
go step by step the entire process my
goal here is to give you sort of an
introduction to some of these more
advanced functions hopefully help you to
conceptually understand them so you can
apply them in your own way and then show
you how to build this from scratch if
you are a Creator you're going to be
able to add this to your own notion
templates for your YouTube videos if you
are using creators companion you could
add add it into that I'll probably ship
it in an update in the near future but
for now we're going to build it from
scratch so here I have a little bit of a
test area where I've got some YouTube
videos I've pulled in their views I've
got their URLs and everything and we're
just going to build this formula right
down here in this channel area so once
again for this channel which you can see
all of these videos are related to Via a
relation property we want to get the top
three videos and then we want to show
those view counts the title of the video
we want to link to the YouTube video
itself and also be able to link to the
notion page in case we want to go check
the script or the BR list or something
like that so we're going to start by
simply opening up this brand new formula
editor here and you can see it looks
pretty much like the old one but there
are a lot more functions and the biggest
update in my mind is we now have what
are called list functions so we can kind
of see here that we have functions like
match we have functions like if I go
down a little bit more I should be able
to find the other ones slice can cat
essentially if I create what's called a
list or in programming this would often
be called an array we can now work with
individual list values so here I've just
got one two three four five I am
enclosing those in Brackets to kind of
show that they are a list and now you
can see we've actually outputted a list
here this is super powerful and way way
more powerful than what we had in
formulas 1.0 because we can now do
operations on these list values so for
example if I just call sort on here I'm
going to get well it's sorted but if I
were to say change the order to say one
three and one type of one two now we can
see sort is sorting that list
numerically if I then were to do a
reverse on it so let's do sort and then
do reverse now we're going to get it in
reverse order from highest to lowest and
you can see that we now also have what's
called this method chaining syntax where
we can kind of call these functions by
using the dot operator here and then
calling the function on the thing we're
working on in this case a list and we
can kind of do that as many times as we
want so essentially what we're building
is sort of like a pipeline here a
multi-stage pipeline where we have an
object or a list or a piece of data
we're working on we are going to pipe
that into this function that's going to
return something that then gets piped
into the next function that is Chained
onto it and we can create this whole
chain of methods that return basically
whatever we want and if you ever get
into programming or coding I've got a
whole tutorial on how to work with the
notion API with JavaScript code if
you're curious you're going to recognize
a lot of similarities between
programming code and this so working
with motion formulas as I've learned is
actually a great way to start learning
how to code for real and to make this a
little bit more clear I want to go over
to a little presentation that I put
together in Whimsical you can find this
tool over at whimsical.com but I
essentially want to kind of give you a
visual example of what a list actually
is so a list is what's called a data
structure and it basically has a number
of elements in a specific order and each
of those elements has what's called an
index usually they start from zero we
call that zero based indexing so here we
have zero one two three four five uh
actually just through four but we have
five elements and you can see we have
some Pokemon here and they are kind of
unsorted they are in an order but
they're not really sorted if I were to
say call a method like sort on it then
I'm going to get a new list but now it's
in sorted order you can see now we have
our Pokemon in alphabetical order so
that's basically what list methods
actually do they take in a list as the
input and then they return a new list
that is basically the same but it's now
sorted if we are working with string
values basically text then they're going
to be sorted in alphabetical order if
we're working with numbers like we had
before they'd be sorted in numerical
order and so on so with that out of the
way how do we actually start getting our
uh sorted list of videos by their views
well to do that what we need to actually
do is instead of having a list of
numbers we need to get into the relation
property that basically has all those
related video pages that are related to
this channel so to do that we can simply
find our relation property which is
called videos and now you can see it is
outputting a list of all those videos in
fact if I hit done here this looks a lot
like the relation property itself it's
just outputting a list of the pages in
that property all the pages that are
related to this channel you can see once
again all these are related to that
channel that's why we're seeing them
there and if I click on them I can even
get into them which is pretty nice and
going back into the editor I can do the
same exact thing that I did with our
list of numbers I could call sort on
this and it's going to sort it in
alphabetical order I could reverse that
if I wanted to reverse alphabetical
order but what we really want to do is
sort by The View counts so what we
actually want to do is instead of just
working on what are essentially the
titles of each of these Pages we need to
figure out how we can get in to those
pages and access the properties of them
so the way that we can do that in
formulas 2.0 is with a method called map
and before I show you what map does here
in the notion formula editor I want to
go through it in my presentation because
it is a method that takes a little bit
of time to fully understand but what map
essentially does is it takes an input
list just like the sort method and then
it is going to run some kind of
operation that you define on every
single element in the list and then it's
going to return a brand new list that is
basically defined by all these elements
running through your function so here
we've got a very simple example of one
I've got a starter list of input Pokemon
every single one of them is going to go
through my map function and the actual
function that I have basically set up
inside of map is what I'm going to call
evolve so basically it's going to go
down the list Charmander is going to go
in there it's going to be returned as
Charmeleon Squirtle is now going to come
war total and then finally Bulbasaur
will go into our function and be evolved
into Ivysaur so inside of notion
formulas the way that we can reference
the current item of the list that we're
working on is by using the current
keyword and you can see here now it
looks basically exactly like it did
before when I just referenced the videos
token here I've got this list here but
now that I am operating on a specific
page in the relation instead of just the
entire list itself I can chain a DOT
onto current and I can access the
properties of the pages in that relation
and this is what's so powerful about
formulas 2.0 there's a lot of other
functions but this is huge so it's
basically like Roll-Ups but now we can
do a lot more with them and if I just
add views onto the end now you can see I
have a list being outputted of all the
view Counts from my videos relation
going back just to make sure this makes
total sense here again we are accessing
each element in this list and we're
running a specific function on it in
this case it's evolved to get some
evolved Pokemon in notion's case what
we're doing is accessing every video or
every related row In our relation
property called videos and for each one
we are accessing The View count of that
page and then we're building a brand new
list with all those view counts and it's
going to give us the list ordered by
default in the insertion order basically
the order in which these Pages were
created up here so if we want to get
these view counts sorted we can do the
exact same thing we did before with that
really basic list of numbers we can call
sort and now we're going to get our view
counts in ascending order and then we
can chain reverse onto the end and now
we get it in our descending order so now
we kind of have our view counts and they
are sorted in this descending order and
that is getting us very close to getting
those top three view counts so here's
what happens if I hit done I just have a
list of those view counts but if I come
back in here and now I call the slice
method I will be able to just get the
top three so if I go slice we'll go 0
and 3 and I'll explain this in just a
second now I have on the top three and
basically what this function is doing is
it's returning the items of a list from
a start index basically what position do
we want to start at and that is included
and then to an end index which is
exclusive which means the end index is
not going to be included here so by
passing 0 as the index and 3 as the end
index let's go back to our presentation
here just to sort of look at how this
would work we are going to be including
the zero number indexed item here one
and two and then we are excluding our
end index so if we're operating on this
list we would get Charmander Squirtle
and Bulbasaur and that'd be it we're
slicing this array to get a new array
and when I say array I basically mean
List array is how we talk about lists in
programming so going back to notion that
is how we get our top view counts so now
the question becomes how do we get from
here just showing view counts to
something like this where we have all of
this detail here and the answer is that
we're going to take these view counts
and we're going to essentially search
back through this relation to find the
rows that match these view counts this
is essentially how we have to do this
kind of operation here because at least
right now in formulas 2.0 the sort
method is as it is you can't really pass
any criteria in there it just sorts by
whatever you have so it's going to be
alphabetical if you're working with
string values it's going to be numerical
sort if you're working with number
values but what we can do is basically
get this list and then use it to sort of
search through our database to find the
matching records and the way we're going
to do that is once again by using this
map function now instead of mapping
through that list of all these video
titles we're going to map through this
resulting list and we are going to do
something to each one of these values so
let's do that by calling map one more
time and here I'll show you another huge
quality of life Improvement in formulas
2.0 if I use shift enter
I can actually go to a new line and in
fact I can indent I can even add
comments so if I did Slash and I believe
it's asterisk I could add a comment and
then uh close it with asterisk and slash
so you can actually comment your
formulas if they get really long and
really complex if you want to add
reminders for yourself you can do that
but for now I'm just going to go on to a
new line and we're going to start
figuring out how we can map through this
list and search through our database
using each of its values so once again I
could use that current keyword and you
can see here I have uh the exact same
list as I did before because I'm just
referencing the current value inside of
my map function that's basically not a
huge Improvement what I want to do is
now I want to take say 700 000 704 883
and I want to search back through this
database to try to find the record where
the views actually match that number and
the way that we need to do that I'm just
gonna
is to try to find the views that match
that number and the way that we need to
do that is by using another function
called find and find is yet another
function that is going to operate on a
list so I won't actually be able to call
it on current because current as we can
see here again represents the current
item in the list we're operating on
through map current is just a number so
let me go ahead and delete this just for
a second just so I can bring up the find
function and show you what it does it
says here Returns the first element in
the list the list that we're going to be
operating on with the find function for
which the condition returns true in this
case the condition that we want to
compare against is does the view count
of a row in this database match again
the current view count that we are
working on here with this current
keyword so instead of referencing
current here what I actually want to do
is get back into our videos relation and
from there I can call that find method
now you can see it actually comes up
because it knows we're working on a list
again and I can call all that but we are
going to run into a slight problem here
find also has its own current keyword
and you can see if I'm referencing
current here current is outputting all
of the pages in that video's relation
because it is referencing the find
method but you might be spotting a
problem here we needed to map through
our list of view counts and for each one
compare it against the records in our
videos relation but now current is not
referring to our view counts so how do
we access that well that brings us to
another huge quality of life and power
level Improvement in formulas 2.0 and
that's variables this is something that
I have been wanting for literal years
now we have What's called the let
function and let essentially lets us
Define a variable give it a value and
then use that variable in other parts of
our formula instead of having to write
tons and tons of the same repeated code
over and over again so the way I'm going
to do that is I'm going to give it a
name so the first argument and let is a
name let me see if I can find the
reference here yep here it is so assigns
a value to a variable and evaluates the
expression using that variable so right
here we can see exactly what's happening
uh the first argument in let is going to
be the name that we want the variable to
have the second argument is going to be
whatever the value of that variable is
and you can see here they are just
giving it a simple string value but this
could be a full calculation all on its
own if you wanted to or in our case it's
going to be current so let's use that
let function right here let's give it a
name I'm going to use current count as
the name the value is going to be
current so shift enter current and now
this current refers to the map function
again so its value is going to be
whatever the view count is and we can
actually see that if we just pass
current count
as the expression here once again this
looks exactly the same we have those
view counts and that means instead of
just referencing current count here we
can once again get into our videos
relation we can call that find method
once again but now we can actually
reference the current value of this
video's relation inside a find and
compare it against the view count that
is stored in current count so the way we
would do that is once again we're going
to use that current keyword and let me
go ahead and actually put this on its
own line just to make things a bit more
clear so I'm going to shift enter down a
couple of times just to do some nice
fancy formatting we're going to do
current dot again we can get into the
properties of the current page we're
working on in this relation so we're
going to grab the views once again and
now we're going to compare it against
the current count so if I just hit done
now you can see we have our top three
videos and if I go back up here and we
once again sort by view count and it
might already be sorted but I'm just
going to add this just as a reminder of
how to sort things uh a video for anyone
feeling behind in life has 704 000 views
10 best Windows productivity apps and so
on so 700 627 583 uh and let's see your
how to break your phone addiction was
that the third one yes it was so there
we have our top three videos sorted uh
by their views and if that's all that
you wanted then you are done you could
add this to your notion workspace but if
you wanted to get a little bit fancier
and add the view counts add the titles
here with the links to the actual
YouTube videos then you will want to
keep following along because we are now
going to modify this formula a little
bit to get something a bit more useful
so essentially what we have done here is
we've returned just the page reference
for each instance of this map function
right here but instead of just getting
the page reference we want to get again
that page title the URL we want to get
the view count we want to get the notion
ID these we can actually link to the
page we want to get a lot more stuff
than just this page reference so instead
of just having one variable here we can
actually change the let function to
Let's which actually will let us Define
multiple variables instead of just one
this is super powerful so if we hover
over let's here we can see it looks very
similar to the original let function
except we now just have a repetition of
this variable value pair here and we
could do that as many times as we want
so here in the example they are
assigning a value of hello to a a value
of world to B and then the final
argument of the uh the function call
here is a plus a space character plus b
and that gets us hello world so what we
want to do is basically take what we
have here and store it in another
variable so I'm just going to go right
up here by current I'm going to enter
down I'm going to give us another
variable name I'll just call it video
and now the value of this is going to be
stored in this video uh keyword here and
once again we can prove that by passing
just video as our final expression in
the let's function and there we have it
but I could go into that video keyword
and get the views or I could get the
name or I could get the URL
and now we have a sorted list these are
our top three videos once again because
we already know which values we're
mapping through by their view counts but
now I actually have their URLs so all we
need to do at this point is kind of
string multiple values together to get
something that looks a little bit more
like this so the way that we can do that
is by using what's called string
concatenation basically taking multiple
text values and mashing them together
and that's how we're going to build
basically this little fancy thing right
here so I'm going to instead of calling
video.url I'm going to call video dot
name and then if I do the plus operator
I can add say a space and then I could
plus and add video dot views and just
like that you can see we have our video
titles we have our view counts and it's
all still sorted in the correct order
and we're still getting the top three to
make this look a little bit better the
next thing we can do is add a bit of
styling so once again I'm going to go
ahead and use shift enter to put all
this stuff on its own new line and I
think I'll actually just let the space
character kind of hang out there but
this I want to put down here just so
everything looks a bit more uh readable
and easy to work with and uh basically
on anything you want you can call this
new style function and style see if I
can find it in the reference guide here
for whatever reason it's not coming up
so I'll just show you style can take a
lot of different oh here it is a lot of
different arguments you could pass B for
bold U for underline we have colors for
the text and colors for the background
as well so for the view counts I think
what I want to do is first give it code
styling because that kind of gives it
this nice little rounded text box I want
to have the text be green and then I
think I also want to have the background
be green as well and then I think I want
the entire thing to be bold as well so
instead of passing the B argument in
this style call which is only affecting
the video views I'm going to come on to
the very end of my entire chain and I'm
going to add style B and that's going to
bold the entire thing so now we're
getting something that looks a little
bit closer to our final product here
what we need to do to make this totally
perfect is truncate the titles here
because right now we can see those
titles are pretty long and even if we
stretch things out number one we need to
make sure they go on their own new lines
but sometimes you might have a really
long video title and it might make
things look really unorganized so we
want to truncate those video titles to
get our view counts sort of in the same
place vertically we want to add a little
page icon that actually links to the
notion page we want to link to the
YouTube video and then what might be one
of the more technical parts so I'm going
to save this for the end we want to get
commas in our numbers here and that's a
little harder than you might think it is
but stick with me and you are going to
understand exactly how to do it so first
and foremost let's go ahead and get our
YouTube video links and then our notion
page links because that's actually
pretty easy to do so if I go back into
our formula here you can see we have
video dot name and a new function that
I'm going to introduce you to is the
link function So within link you can
basically just pass a hyperlink to
anywhere and that's going to get you a
nice handy dandy clickable link so we
already have the videos URL per video in
this database here we're already
accessing all this database data via the
page relations so maybe think about this
in your head for a second but all we
have to do is call that video dot URL
property so once again I'm going to
enter down just to make this as easy and
clear as possible if we do video dot URL
we're accessing that URL property and
now we can see that these are clickable
if I click on this video here I get that
video on my YouTube channel with me
looking all pensive and stuff so going
back over here next I think I want to
get our our little video references on
their own lines because right now it's
just one kind of unbroken line and we've
got commas here we don't want those so
the next thing we want to do is come
down to the very end and remember that
even though this is kind of looking
really tall all of this is happening
within this specific map function call
it starts here at this parenthesis mark
and it ends here at this one so
everything is happening inside of map
and then the new list that map is
returning we are then passing into style
well one additional thing we can pass it
into is this join function so join
essentially will take a list of values
and turn that entire list into a single
string and then you can pass a separator
so if we passed a comma and a space as a
separator then we'd get a string where
every element is separated by Common of
space I'm actually going to pass
backslash n so backslash n that is the
character for a new line and if I hit
done here I apparently broke something
and actually the reason that I broke
something is that style already coerces
our list to a string so instead of
putting it at the end here I actually
want to put it before style so I'm going
to go Dot join and I'm going to pass my
backslash n right there
and now when I enter out of here we are
going to have every one of these videos
on its own new line now if I don't have
my property uh wrapping here then it's
going to just do that which is not very
good but if I choose wrap column on this
property then every element is going to
be on its own line and again this is now
a single string value but because we ran
it through that jointer function with a
new line every single one appears to be
on its own new line and appears to be a
separate thing and from a usability
perspective it basically is so the next
thing we want to do is get that little
page icon that links to the notion
project and this requires a little bit
of setup so I'm going to show you what I
did up here in the videos database first
this is really easy if I go into any one
of these videos you can see that I have
a formula property called ID if I click
into this all I am passing is a function
called ID which just Returns the page ID
for this particular page and this isn't
documented when I was trying things out
but I figured out that if you just link
to the page ID you get a clickable link
to the notion page so all we need to do
is add a little bit more string
concatenation so let's find the end of
that uh video views thing here let's
pass another space character just to get
some separation and then I'm going to
shift enter down onto another new line
and I'm going to do uh a page character
so I'll do I think it's control command
space yes it is I'm going to find that
page character right there to get an
emoji and then we can call Dot link on
this particular string value so between
these two quote symbols is a piece of
data just called a string this is an
individual string so we can pass link on
it and inside of Link we can do video
once again which again refers to the
current page we're working on in that
video's relation and we can go ID that
is a property and now we have a
clickable little page link if I click
that we now get a video for anyone
feeling behind in life so this I just
think is super useful because let's to
say you're on the dashboard of creators
companion and you're looking at your top
three videos uh you have a super quick
way to get to the video itself or you
can get to the actual notion page where
you might have your script you might
have b-roll you might have comments all
kinds of good stuff okay what's next on
the docket here we don't have our titles
being truncated yet so let's now add
that in and this is going to be the
first taste that a lot of you have
probably ever had of regular Expressions
which is basically a intimidating
looking but kind of simple when you
really break it down language all its
own for manipulating text I had to learn
regular expressions like a freaking
ninja because in formulas 1.0 we didn't
have lists we didn't have arrays we
didn't have a lot of these new fancy
functions so I had to get very creative
with regular Expressions do a lot of the
cool stuff you've seen in my templates
well we can still use those for some
more limited purposes here in formulas
2.0 so by clicking into our formula we
are now now going to try to truncate
these titles so they're all more or less
the same length and we can do that with
a function called replace so let's go to
video.name and one thing that you might
run into which I already know is that if
you try to call the replace function or
any kind of string manipulation function
after your link function here it's going
to strip that link out because it's
going to take in a text that might be a
hyperlink but it's going to return just
text so I want to do our replace call
before our link call so I'm going to add
link down here on its own line and I'm
going to add replace first and let's
take a quick look at what replace
actually does so it says it replaces the
first match of the regular expression
and I'll explain what that means in a
second with the replacement value and we
have a nice little example down here we
have the string notion notion and then
in the replace our first argument is
what's called a regular expression
basically it's an expression that
describes Vibes what kind of text we're
looking for in this case it is just a
capital N and the first one it finds
which will be this character here is
going to be replaced with an M so now we
get motion notion and that doesn't seem
super powerful Until you realize that
regular Expressions is a whole language
with a ton of special tools for
describing varied types of text that you
could access and you're going to see
that in just a second here so inside of
my replace call here I'm going to again
shift enter down and put our arguments
on their own lines and I'm just going to
do blank string blank strings right now
nothing is happening because we are
matching nothing and replacing it with
nothing if I did let's just say the
capital A then we could replace that
with capital B and then we get B video
for anyone feeling behind in life but we
want to get a bit fancier with it again
we're trying to truncate these titles so
they're all about the same length so
what we can do is actually put
parentheses characters in our regular
expression and this creates it's what's
called a capture group so basically you
could match against an entire expression
and within that expression you're going
to have a group of characters you
capture which you can then reference
later on so what I want to do is inside
this capture group try to get say the
first 25 characters of the title no
matter what they are and the way I can
do that is by using the period character
the period character basically says this
should match any character the only
character of the period won't match is a
new line now if you wanted to match
against an actual period you could put a
backslash there that does what's called
escaping it escapes this special
character here and tells the engine that
hey we want to actually match against a
period character not that special a
little wild card there but I actually
wanted to be a wild card there and then
we can use something called a quantifier
so right now it's just going to match a
single of any character really but if we
add a couple of curly braces and we put
say 25 in there then it's going to match
up to 25 characters so we're starting to
get a bit of truncation here but
remember we are capturing the first 25
characters and then we want to actually
replace everything else with just that
first 25 characters so after the capture
group I'm going to add another period in
there and then I'm going to add the uh
asterisk quantifier and the asterisk
quantifier basically says zero or more
of whatever is before it so period is
any character and asterisk is let's
match zero or more of them up until we
can't match anymore so if I go in here
instead of putting B I can actually put
dollar sign one
and with capture groups basically
whenever you build a capture group in a
regular expression it's going to be
assigned a value or a variable really of
dollar sign and then the number of
whichever capture group it is so if I
had multiple capture groups in this
regular expression I might have dollar
sign one two three Etc in this case I
just have one so dollar sign one does it
and then if we wanted to we could do
like a dot dot dot after it to sort of
show that truncation uh and this now
makes the title exactly the same length
every single time uh there are some
characters here that are different
widths but just to show you what we
could do here if we then uh ran this
through another style call so let's just
do style and we pass c as the argument
that's going to style it as code and
code fonts are what are called Mono
spaced every single character takes the
exact same amount of horizontal space so
if we hit done here they should be all
the exact same length and if that's what
you wanted if you want it to look almost
like a table here then you could do that
what I want though is for my words to
not be cut off here so we've got feeling
we have produ we have ah and over here
you can see that we actually end the
truncation on an actual word barrier so
we're not slicing words in half and we
need a little bit of extra trickery in
our regular expression to achieve that
so let's go back down to our replace
call you can see here we are matching 25
of any character so what we want to do
is add a little bit on the end of that
to make sure that we're matching any
word characters up until the next space
or piece of punctuation and there is in
fact a little wild card for just word
characters so alphanumerics like a
through z and zero through nine and that
is slash or backslash W so now we are
getting in this case just one of them
because we haven't added a quantifier
but if I add I think plus onto the end
now we get uh feeling we get
productivity we get phone addiction
we're good to go there plus is very much
like the asterisk except for it means
one or more instead of zero or more so
if there were zero of these it wouldn't
match at all but if there's one or more
it's going to match up until it can't
match anymore so the truncation is done
I'm gonna go ahead and get rid of that
styling so it's not code styling anymore
and now it is starting to look almost
like our final result here the only
thing we need to do to finish this up is
to get the commas in the numbers and
I've already introduced you to a little
bit of working with regular Expressions
so it probably isn't going to surprise
you to know that we have to once again
break out the regular Expressions to add
our commas in here the reason for that
is when we're getting our views here
it's not actually a number and what I
have found is with formulas even if you
are formatting a number property with a
comma here and pro tip you can do that
by just going to edit property on a
number property and then the number
format can be changed you number with
commas but even if we're doing that the
formula that actually references those
numbers isn't necessarily going to add
those commas in there if a formula is
returning just one number then you can
go ahead and add that formatting just as
you would with a number property but in
this case we are returning a lot of text
we are returning an emoji here so this
number is going to be coerced to a
string value basically it's still going
to look like a number but its type is no
longer a number we could no longer do
arithmetic on it it is just text using
numeric characters and that means
there's no built-in logic that is going
to add those commas meaning we have to
add them ourselves so let's go ahead and
do that and once you do this you are
going to be well on your way to being a
regular Expressions Master uh that old
guy who works at your company who's been
like in the basement running Linux
systems for 50 years is going to respect
you finally so let's go find our views
here we've styled them uh just like
before just to keep things kind of nice
and organized I'm going to move our
style call down and I'm going to call
our replace call first so I'm going to
do dot replace one more time and we're
going to have to use replace twice here
for reasons that will become clear in
just a second so again keeping things
nice and tidy on their own lines you can
keep things way more compact if you want
to I'm just putting everything on its
own new line for this video as clarity's
sake so what we want to do this time is
try to figure out where in this string
we need to place a comma and because
numbers actually start counting from the
right side like this is the ones place
this is the tens place and so on we need
to actually make our regular expression
look from the end of the string from the
right side to make its match that way it
knows to count from the right side one
two three oh there's my thousands place
let's insert a comma so to do that
there's actually a special character
that you can put at the end of your
regular expression uh the dollar sign
and earlier we were able to use a dollar
sign here to reference capture groups
but dollar signs are double duty and if
they are at the very end of a regular
expression uh itself then that basically
tells the engine hey start looking from
the end of the string instead of the
beginning or at least make sure the
match goes to the end of the string it
cannot be a match in the middle it has
to go to the very end so now that we are
basically ensuring we go to the end we
can look for three instances of a
numeric character and earlier we used
this backslash W Wild Card which
represents any alphanumeric so again A
through Z and zero through nine there is
yet another Wild Card which is backslash
d
that is going to find any numeric
character so you can see we just
replaced uh the final number in these
view counts with nothing if I put in an
emoji instead we now have a 704 and
whatever that is so that is essentially
what we can do but we need to capture
the first three so we can get the ones
tens and hundreds place and then put a
comma before it so just like we did
before let's use our curly braces to
define a specific number of characters
that we want to match up to which is
going to be curly brace three and now
you can see we are adding our little uh
smiley emoji laughing emoji uh instead
of these characters but again if we were
to reference a capture Group which we
actually have to build first so let's
wrap this in parentheses we could then
reference our capture group with dollar
sign one and now you can see we have an
emoji in between our uh thousands place
and our hundreds place just where a
comma should be so all we need to do is
replace that emoji with a comma and now
we have ourselves a nice comma but
there's a problem here it's only going
to work for videos that are between a
million and a thousand views and I can't
really show it to you very easily
because we're kind of sorting by the top
here but if you imagine we only had like
900 views in a video we're just gonna
have a comma there and no thousands
place and similarly if we have a video
over 1 million views I can show you that
problem by just changing one of these
views to uh a million and 700 000 we are
not going to have a comma there because
we're only matching the first three
characters from the end of the string
which is why we need another replace
call so we can add a comma in our
Millions place so once again we're going
to do dot replace and it's going to be
very similar to what we just did but
we're going to have a slight tweak so we
can account for the comma that we
already added so just like before we're
going to match from the end of the
string that we're looking through uh
just like before we're going to create a
capture group but this time we are going
to get our slash D and three that's
going to match the first three we also
want to match the comma we added and the
next three so the way we can do that is
add that comma in there and then do the
exact same thing one more time so to go
through this this first little group of
uh Slash D any numeric character for
three is capturing the hundreds tens and
ones place then we're capturing the
comma then we're capturing the hundred
thousands ten thousands and thousands
place in this next little group all
binding into the capture group that we
have here and now you can see because we
are replacing everything with nothing we
just get that one for the one million
view video and that's it if we come here
and we actually just pass say a comma
and then our dollar sign one we get a
comma just like that now there is a
little bit of additional robustness we
can add in here and I'm going to
actually change the formula up just a
little bit to show you why I'm gonna get
rid of this reverse right here and
that's going to give us our lowest
counted videos by default and you can
see here we actually have a comma before
our first number and that's not really
good in fact if I were to make one of
these videos really really low let's go
with 883 views not even a thousand we're
also going to have the same problem in
the thousands place here so what we need
to do is make a little bit of a tweak to
our regular Expressions to account for
the fact that there might not be a
number in the thousands place or in the
millions place and the way we can do
that is by defining additional matching
criteria inside of our regular
expression so here I'm just going to add
one additional capture group I'm going
to do the slash D once again but this
time I'm going to use the plus operator
this is going to specify that the match
needs to find one additional number
there otherwise this is basically going
to be ignored again we're starting from
the end here so if it does find
something it's going to be included in
the entire match if it it doesn't find
anything it's not going to be included
at all so we can actually now reference
dollar sign one on this side of the
comma and change this to dollar sign two
which is referencing the second capture
group we made and now you can see we
have fixed the problem for this video
that has less than a thousand views now
all we need to do is do the exact same
thing over on our second call so we'll
make another capture group slash D plus
ensuring that if there is a million view
video we are gonna get that Millions
place but if there's not then we are
only going to be capturing
um the first six digits and there will
be no comma inserted so again we're
going to change this over to dollar sign
one dollar sign two and now that is
totally fixed if I uh once again go back
in here and add our reverse call one
more time
then of course we get our videos in
their uh proper view order and if we
change this one uh it's down here now to
let's just say 1.700 million again we
will get at the top and the commas are
in place correctly so comparing against
our final product we have our link it
links to YouTube video we've already
tested that we have our view counts with
their commas we have our page icon links
to the notion page that all looks good
does that work yes it does we have built
this formula and hopefully if you've
paid attention you now have the skills
to build something like this yourself
and I'll just go ahead and show the
formula for this sales by day of week on
screen here we're not going to walk
through this one quite in the same way
um but it's using a lot of the same
exact ideas and principles here we're
basically defining a list of sort
criteria in this case we're actually
using the numbers that correspond to
specific days of the week again we're
mapping through that we're binding the
current value of map in a variable here
we're creating a sales variable this
time we're actually filtering through to
get the current day of each sale and
then we're doing some fancy math here
and some fancy formatting to get the
total dollar amount of sales that are on
each day of the week and then formatting
it in a nice way and I would urge you to
study this if you want to learn formulas
deeply and look through each of these
functions and look at what they do
because the more of these tools that
you're familiar with the more you're
going to be able to employ combine mix
and match to solve any kind of problem
you run across and it's at this point
that I want to let you guys know that
over on thomasjfrank.com we have a
complete notion formula reference and
Ben Smith on my team has been working
like crazy over the past couple of weeks
to completely transfer this from
formulas 1.0 to formulas 2.0 it is live
today so if you go over to Thomas
jfrank.com formulas or if you're just
anywhere on my site you can go to the
learn notion menu in the top up here you
can go to notion formulas you're going
to find a complete formulas tutorial we
have articles going over all the parts
of what formulas do we also have uh
individual articles for every single
piece of notion formulas every single
one of them is going to have a page that
shows you how to use it it's going to
have little tool tips and good to knows
it's going to have examples example
databases and we'll be building this out
and making it comprehensive in the
coming weeks so definitely bookmark this
as a resource if you do want to get more
confident and capable with notion
formulas last thing I'll mention here
because we were building a formula that
is really useful inside of creators
companion shows all these top three view
counts if you are a serious content
creator and especially if you're running
multiple channels like I am or you've
got a Blog YouTube channel social media
presence then you might like creators
companion this is the notion template
that I built for myself and my team to
completely manage our entire content
production pipeline we have all of our
content ideas in there we write scripts
in there we have research in there we
also manage the entire editing process
and then this one's really exciting
actually I just built this for myself
the other day I now have an automation
that will bring in accurate view comment
and light counts it will bring in the
thumbnails and the actual publish dates
with their time from the YouTube API so
now inside of my own copy of creators
companion I have all this up-to-date
data automatically set for all of the
YouTube videos that I published across
all of my channels and then I think
there's going to be some really cool
analysis stuff we can do with this in
the future so I've already built this
automation I'm going to be shipping it
to people who have bought creators
companion it may be a paid upgrade in
the future but at least for now I'm
going to be getting it out for a limited
time so if you want to try out creators
companion again if you are a serious
content creator Thomas jfrank.com cc is
the URL you can go to and right now you
can also use the code let's go 2023 to
get 50 bucks off of any edition of
creators companion once again thank you
for watching hopefully this was a little
bit of a good introduction to formulas
2.0 again that formula reference is
going to have articles for all the
functions I've got another video coming
out very soon it's going to go over a
lot of the new features in formulas in a
much more compact way so keep your eyes
peeled for that along with lots of
additional tutorials coming down the
pipeline since this one was a technical
one I'm also going to link to my notion
API tutorial if you do want to get a bit
more into coding specifically JavaScript
coding and you want to understand how to
actually work with the notion API that
is your video it is a two hour long
project you get to build a whole Pokedex
a notion that is generated automatically
and it is basically like a whole crash
course not only for the notion API but
kind of for JavaScript as well so check
that out and I will see you in the next
one