We'll guide you through how to cut and
trim a video in Clip Champ. If you find
this useful, then consider subscribing
and liking the video. Here we have a
video that I wish to go and cut and
trim. So perhaps it's part of a video
you don't want and so you want to go and
remove it. With this video, you're going
to go and be able to and so we can go
and use ClipChamp in order to go and do
this. So this video editor comes in
Windows 11. So you can go and press
search at the bottom, go and type in
ClipChamp. And as you can see, there it
is. We can then go and click on it. It's
now going to go and open up. Go and be
patient. It shouldn't go and take too
long. At the top, you can go and press
create a new video like so. And we're
now going to get a new project here.
I'll just double click on it to go and
make it full screen. Press import media
in the top left and go and find the
video you want to do it with. For me,
it's on my desktop. So, I'll scroll down
and I can then select it and press open.
Now, it's going to go and import. Just
be patient while this loads. It
shouldn't go and take too long. Now,
click, hold, and we can go and drag it
into the timeline like so. And there it
is. So, to go and get started, we can go
and trim the start and end point. So, to
go and do that, you go and see these
purple lines at the start and end. Place
your cursor there. It will go and change
to the arrow, and you can then click,
hold, and go, and drag like so to go and
find the point where you want to go and
start it. Then, you can click, hold, and
drag it to put it to the start of the
project again, just so there's no empty
space. And you can do the same thing at
the end as well. If there's a part
within it you want to go and remove when
you play it back. What you can do is
make a split by pressing on the split
which you can also go and press S to do.
You see it makes a split. Then you can
go and decide you want to go and make
another split. And you can then go and
press on the scissors or press S. And
then you have this clip here we went
split out. With it then selected. What
you can do is press delete or backspace
on your keyboard to go and remove it.
Then we can click, hold and drag the
clips together again like so. So there's
no space between them. That's it. So
you've now gone and successfully gone
and removed that part. When you're
finished, we can go and export it by
pressing export in the top right. You
can choose the quality to the left. I'll
turn off store in the cloud. And we can
then press export like so. And you can
press save to your computer. And we can
then go and save it where we want to. If
you found this useful, then consider
subscribing and liking the