Sometimes when you're talking to an LLM
like Chad GBT, it gets kind of dumb,
right? You'll be deep into a
conversation that you can't even scroll
to the top of because it's so long and
it starts to say weird things. It
hallucinates. It forgets what you're
talking about. It makes stuff up and
it's stinking slow. Why is this
happening? Context windows. What is
that? Did you know that LLMs like Chat
GBT, Gemini, Claude, even local models
like Llama or Deepseek, they're kind of
like us, you and me, and that they have
memories? Short-term memory, which means
they can remember things. That's
awesome. But also, sometimes they can
forget stuff. And it happens like this.
Let's say you and me, we're having some
coffee and we're talking for about 15
minutes. In that short amount of time,
we remember pretty much everything. I
remember that story you told. You
remember that dumb joke I said, but
you're pretty fun to talk to. So, we end
up talking for an hour, 2 hours, 3
hours, and at that point, it's kind of
hard to keep track of stuff. I forget
that amazing point you made. Thankfully,
you forgot that dumb thing I said. And
sometimes we forget the entire point of
the conversation. We talk so long. It
kind of reminds me of how sometimes when
I fight with my wife, we fight for so
long that we forget what we're fighting
about to begin with. Does it happen to
you? Chad GBT does the same thing. It's
like you and your wife. The longer that
conversation goes on, the more things
you say, the more things it says back to
you. It has to store all of that in its
short-term memory. And that short-term
memory has a limit. That limit is its
context window. Let me show you what
that looks like. Here I'm inside LM
Studio, which is a great way to run
local AI models on your computer. I'll
select a local model to load. We'll do
Gemma 34B. and we'll change our context
length or our context window to 20048.
Now, what does that mean? What is 2048?
What? Tokens. Tokens are how an AI
counts the words you say to it. I'll
show you. Let's uh load the model real
quick. I'll click on load model. It's
loading and we'll start a new chat. Now,
we might say this sentence is 133
characters or 26 words, but an LLM just
cares about tokens. So, this sentence
would actually be 38 tokens. Notice our
input token count, 38. And we can have
that broken down further if we copy and
paste this. And go to a website like
OpenAI's tokenizer and paste that text
in. And it actually sees that as only 34
tokens. Not every LLM will calculate
tokens in the same way. And notice it
might do an entire word as a token. It
might do a space in a word or just one
comma as a token. And right now the
model we loaded up, our Gemma 34B, has a
context window of 248 tokens. Meaning
that this is the maximum amount of
tokens this model can pay attention to
at any one time. Let me show you. I'm
going to make it forget something. So,
I'll start out by telling it something
about me. Right now, I'm reading a book
called How to Take Smart Notes. Cool.
That should be in its memory. And down
here, we can track our usage. 14.6%
full. Now, let's load it up. Tell me a
story about cows. The rain in Okin
Valley wasn't a gentle drizzle. It was a
44.4% full. Amazing story. Give me the
sequel. Okay, let's weave a sequel. Here
it is. Bessie and the Echoes. 82%. Wow.
Just wow. Now I'll do a prequel.
We're now at 118.4%. If I click on that,
it'll show me the tokens. 2400 tokens.
Let's see if it can remember the book I
told it. What book am I reading right
now? What does it tell? Oh, funny. It
mentions memory loss. Oh, memory, loss.
Forgot that extra token. No, I told you
about a book I was reading. What is it?
No, it doesn't remember at all. It
forgot the first things I told it. Let's
fix that. Let's increase its short-term
memory. Man, I wish I could do this for
myself. So, notice right now it's set to
20048. I'm going to eject the model, but
this time I'll change it context to
4,96. And I'll load the model. Let's see
now. What book am I reading right now?
Bam. It got it. It even apologized for
being stupid even though it wasn't his
fault. Now, by the way, a lot of things
can fill up the context window. The
obvious things are things we say and the
things it says back. But there also
might be system prompts, which are
instructions for our LLMs, LLMs. It's
kind of hard to say after a while. These
you might explicitly give to it or it's
included by default. You never see it.
You also might give it documents. You
might paste a PDF or an Excel
spreadsheet. That'll take up some more
tokens. And when you're doing some vibe
coding, the code the code is taking up
tokens filling up that context window.
Okay, there's our solution. Let's up the
context infinity. Let's do it right now.
Load up our model. Well, hold on. There
are limits. Like right now, it tells us
this model supports up to 131,000
tokens. Officially, you'll see that
written as 128,000. That's still pretty
big. Let's do that. Scoot the sucker on
up. Whoa, hold on. Setting this high
value for context length can
significantly impact your memory usage.
That's the kicker with running local
LLMs. While Gemma 34B has an astounding
128K,000 token context window, it
doesn't mean our GPU can support that
full context. Specifically, it's going
to be about VRAM or video RAM. LM Studio
is looking at my video card, which is a
4090 with 24 gigs of VRAM, and it's
like, "Buddy, you're reaching your
limits. calm down. And that's something
that may not be obvious to everyone.
Yes, to run a powerful model, you'll
want a powerful GPU, but we might
overlook that to have long
conversations, we'll need lots of VRAM.
Can I show you what happens when I try
to load up that full context window on
my computer? Watch this. It might break
my recording. So, sky's is the stinking
limit. 120,000 tokens. I'm going to
bring up my uh Oh no, it's going to kill
my recording. I just know it. Here's my
performance monitor. We'll load the
model now. And it's about to cry. Oh,
look at it down here. Yeah, it just
boom. All the way up. It took out all my
VRAM. Is it loaded yet? Oh man, my
computer is just dying. Look at this. Oh
no, you probably can't see it. Okay, the
model's loaded, but it's going to be
hard to talk to. Like before it was so
snappy. Look how slow this is. And what
you're seeing here is that bigger
context windows require more compute
power, more GPU resources in more ways
than one. Look at this. I'm going to
stop this and eject it. It's probably
not even like showing you right now. But
with cloud models, that's a whole
different story. You can use their full
advertised context windows. And they got
some big ones. GPT40 is rocking 128,000
tokens. And he thinks he's better than
everybody else. 03 Mini Claude 3.7
200,000 and the Gemini 2.5 from Google.
1 million tokens. Tell us your whole
life story. It's going to remember it.
And what's crazy is they're saying that
2 million is right around the corner.
What? Hey, number from the future here.
Neta just released Llama for Scout,
which has a 10 million token context
window. Are you serious? This is a local
model. I just had to say that. That's
crazy. Now, back to the video. But there
is a catch. Even if you have a super
large context window, it doesn't mean
the LLM won't kind of freak out and
forget stuff, become less accurate, or
start to go extremely slow. You'll
notice on those larger conversations,
it'll have some trouble paying
attention. And that's a big problem. AI
paying attention. Wait, what? Hey, real
quick. It's time for a coffee break.
This coffee break and this tip I'm about
to give you is sponsored by Twin. Now,
talking about context, what I like to do
a lot is go to a website, for example,
if I'm trying to learn about Twin, like,
how does it compare to a VPN? How does
it compare? It's awesome. That's how it
is. I might want to take the content of
this web page and put it into an LLM and
ask it questions about it. How do we do
that? Well, normally we'll just go a C
and then paste it into our LLM. Boom.
That's terrible. I hate that. It's ugly.
The format of all this information was
not meant to be read by an LLM. It was
meant to be read by humans, and
definitely not in this little chat box
here. There's a better way. I found this
cool tool. It's called Gina. All we have
to do is this. Whatever web page you're
on, go to the address bar and at the
very beginning, just scroll over, type
in r.gina with a j.ai, and then a
forward slash. Watch this. Boom. It
converts that entire web page into
markdown that LLM love. It's nice and
clean. And as you're about to see, LM do
have a hard time paying attention. This
definitely helps. Now, I can just paste
that sucker in there, say summarize
this, and I'm off to the races. So,
R.G.A.I., I just found this tool. I'm
going to start using it all the time.
And speaking of tools you should use all
the time, Twin Gate should be one of
those. It's a remote access solution,
Zero Trust, and it's what I use to stay
connected to my home lab, my studio, my
business, when I'm traveling, when I'm
out, when I have remote employees. I use
it when I was in Japan. I used it on my
road trip. It's fast, quick, and more
importantly, the most important thing
nowadays, it's secure. If you're still
using a VPN, you're crazy. And setting
up Twin Gate is easy. You can put it on
a Raspberry Pi inside your network. I've
shown that a few times here on my
channel. takes about 5 minutes and for
home labers it's free even though it
feels like it shouldn't be. There's too
many features they're giving us. Don't
believe me? Check it out. Link below.
Anyways, back to the video. There was a
paper released called Lost in the Middle
and it showed us how LLMs are kind of
like us with paying attention. And just
like my wife when she watches a long
movie, she'll watch the first part then
fall asleep and then wake up at the end
and that's the context she has. I'll ask
her to explain it to me. In the same
way, conversations with LLMs with large
context, the models were more accurate
with info at the beginning and even with
info at the end, but in the middle, huge
drop off. And across the board, we saw
this U shape. So, what does that tell
us? LM are falling asleep during a
conversation. Kind of. I'm telling you,
LM have problems paying attention just
like us. But that brings up a question.
How do LLMs pay attention? What does
that mean for a computer to do that?
It's actually incredibly fascinating.
It's called attention mechanisms.
Specifically with modern LLMs, it's
referred to as a self attention
mechanism. And honestly, I was going to
do a deep dive on that and this video
right here, but that would increase the
context window of this video, making it
harder for people to pay attention to.
And given this is probably the middle of
the video, you would forget it. So, I'll
have another video coming out on that.
But I still want to talk about it. There
will be another video somewhere around
here soon. TLDDR, when you say something
to an LLM like, "Hey, I want coffee, but
caffeine makes me jittery. What should I
get?" It will do something eerily
similar to how we process and think. It
will use some fancy semantic math to
decide which of these words is
important, which is relevant both to the
context of your entire conversation and
to how the words relate to each other.
It might look like this, and this is
very simplified. They essentially assign
attention scores saying, "Hey, in this
conversation, coffee is high, caffeine
is high, jittery." But words like I or
me kind of low relevance to the context.
And we kind of do the same thing. We
only remember the things that are
relevant. You said something about
coffee, jittery, caffeine, and we'll use
that context to process our responses.
AI does the same thing. Now, what's
crazy is this process is pretty complex.
All this math to assign attention
scores. And it does this every time you
send something to the LLM, every time
you add to the conversation. So, this
conversation, no big deal. ChatGBT can
keep track of it easily. But if you
start having a conversation where that
scroll bar is hard to find, you know
what I'm saying? Like it's you can't
even like find it to scroll up. Those
larger contacts not only have insane
VRAM requirements, they also have some
pretty healthy computational
requirements. Every time you add to that
conversation, that math problem that has
to run to figure out what's important
gets bigger and it requires more GPU
power. And that is why in those larger
conversations, the LLM starts to
hallucinate and it seems just a bit more
slow. It's using a ton of memory and
it's having to do some crazy math every
time you talk to it. And not only that,
think about this. If you're saying a lot
of different things, like I know some
people who just keep one conversation
open with JGBT and just shoot the
breeze. They'll talk about coffee, the
weather, explain quadratic equations to
me, and during the context of the
conversation is trying to weigh all of
these different words and how relevant
they are to the entire context of the
conversation. And that's crazy. And no
wonder it starts to hallucinate. So, a
quick solution to that, and this is a
rule I try to go by when I'm talking
with LLMs, when you change an idea, when
it's a significant shift from what
you're currently talking about, start a
new chat. The performance will be so
much better. In fact, when sometimes
when you're talking with other LLMs like
Claude, it'll even tell you at the
bottom, "Hey, you've been talking for a
minute, things are going to slow down.
Why don't you go and start a new chat so
things can be better?" But I'm hoping
sometime soon this won't be a problem
anymore. Especially with Google Gemini
coming out with a 2 million context
window. I wanted to be able to pay
attention to everything I'm saying. It's
kind of like you having a a notebook
with a bunch of stuff you've written
down. You've got the ability to have all
that stuff with you. That's your
context, but the ability to quickly find
what you need in that notebook might be
kind of limited. You can't remember
every page. Now, if you want to learn
more about self attention mechanisms,
that'll be its own video. It is
fascinating. But real quick, I want to
get back to the idea of context windows
because that is the context of this
video and it's actually good news for
some of us who want to run these local
AI models in their full context. There
are some optimizations that have come
out to help us do that. The first one is
called flash attention. Like, hey,
paying attention kind of like that.
Actually, it's not really at all. I just
wanted to do that, but now you're paying
attention. It's actually an option right
here when I want to load a model. So,
we'll choose Gemma 34B. And right here
under experimental features, we have
flash attention. I'll go ahead and
enable it. This will change how the
model will compute its attention and
assign those weights. Now, it's doing
the same kind of crazy semantic math
that regular self attention mechanisms
are doing, but he's like that lazy kid
in class who always got straight A's. It
will actually skip building the full
table of token comparisons by processing
tokens in chunks with optimized GPU
routines. Essentially, it never stores
the full matrix or all the complications
in memory at the same time, leading to
significant improvements in not only
memory, but speed. So, let's try it out
real quick. I'm going to go full 131 to
the limit. Making sure I have flash
attention ready to go. We'll pull up my
poor GPU and we'll see what happens.
It's slowly loading my model and it
still did max out my memory, but we'll
see how the speed
is. GPU is spiking. It's thinking. It's
lagging. Okay, still pretty slow, but
there's actually two more things we can
do. I'm going to stop it now. Eject.
Give me my memory back, please. Oh,
thank you. If I select the model once
more, choose GMA 34B, I'll select flash
attention, but we also have these Kcach
and Vcash optimizations. These two
options will actually compress our data,
so it takes up less room in VRAM. So,
let's enable both of those suckers. Bam.
Bam. And we'll change the amount. And
the lower the quantization, the better.
So, we'll go to quant 4 on both of
these. And we'll go to full 131. Let's
load the model. Let's watch our memory.
Look at that. It did not even max out
our memory, which is amazing. We're
using the full 128,000 context window.
Let's try and talk to
it. Significantly faster. Keeping in
mind I'm recording right now using my
GPU. I mean, that's stinking great. Now,
in addition to flashed attention and the
compression of our data, there's also a
thing called paged cache. Page cache
will actually move attention cache
between your GPU, so your VRAM, and your
system RAM. So, essentially, it's
sharing the RAM with your system.
Downside is that it's going to be
significantly slower than the VRAM
sitting right there on your GPU. And
yes, it is like your page file on your
system. Your system will have system
memory, your RAM. And when you max out
your RAM, your computer might be
configured to use a page file, aka your
hard drive or your SSD, which will be
significantly slower than your RAM. So,
let's bring this video home. I'm a
massive fan of larger context windows. I
want to give an LLM everything I could
possibly give it about me or a problem
I'm trying to solve and help me figure
it out. And if it's local, that's way
better. But there's a couple of massive
problems. A few we've already talked
about. you're going to take up a ton of
memory, GPU memory, your VRAMm memory
you may not have, and it's going to take
a ton of power to process your
conversation the longer it gets,
resulting in slower conversations. But I
think the scariest part, the scariest
downside is the larger attack surface.
Yes, LLMs can be hacked and they're
vulnerable to some creative prompting
that can jailbreak out of their
protection systems. The longer a
conversation is, the more it can kind of
like forget what's in the middle, as we
saw in that little U curve, and the
easier it will be for an attacker to
hide some malicious stuff in there that
could bypass its safety precautions.
Anyways, our context window is way too
big. We're going to end it right now.
I'll catch you guys in the next
one. Chat GBT can I can't talk right
now, which is bad for a guy making a
video. Okay, don't put that. That's
stupid.